{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This person's name was formerly used for the capital of Tajikistan, now known as Dushanbe (doo-SHAHN-bay), and for the mountain now called Ismail Samani (suh-MAH-nee) Peak, which was called \"Communism Peak\" after his death. For 10 points, identify this former namesake of Volgograd, where a major World War II battle was fought in the Soviet Union.",
      "answer": "Joseph Stalin"
    },
    {
      "question": "This modern-day country was converted by Saint Frumentius in the 4th century. The rock-cut city of Lalibela is in this country, where inscriptions in the Ge'ez language appear on stone stelae in the ancient city of Axum. The coffee plant was first grown in this modern-day country. For 10 points, name this African country which lost access to the Red Sea when Eritrea seceded.",
      "answer": "Ethiopia"
    },
    {
      "question": "William Gorgas helped manage sanitation for this project, drawing on Walter Reed's research into yellow fever. The Hay-Banau-Varilla treaty cleared the way for this structure, which cuts through Gatún Lake. John McCain was born in its namesake Zone, which the US ceded in 1979. For 10 points, name this Central American waterway linking the Atlantic and Pacific oceans.",
      "answer": "Panama Canal"
    },
    {
      "question": "U.S. doctors worked with a dictator of this country to eradicate yaws. This country was\nevacuated by U.S. troops as the major effect of Franklin Roosevelt's \"good neighbor\" policy;\nRoosevelt claimed to have written this country's constitution. For 10 points, name this country\nwhere the U.S. intervened in 1994 to restore Jean-Bertrand Aristide to Port-au-Prince.",
      "answer": "Haiti"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city constructed a paved road used to transport boats overland called the Diolkos. A\ndispute between this city and its colony of Corcyra was a cause of the Peloponnesian War.\nCypselid rulers of this city included its second tyrant, Periander. Capitals bedecked with\nacanthus leaves characterized this city’s namesake order of columns. For 10 points, name this\nancient Greek city located on a namesake isthmus.",
      "answer": [
        "Corinth",
        "Korinthos"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Much of the Roman conquest of this island was carried out under Gnaeus Julius Agricola. The mercenaries Hengist and Horsa were invited to this island by Vortigern. The Iceni were led in an uprising by their queen Boudicca on this island. Julius Caesar visited this island twice during his conquest of Gaul. For 10 points, which island experienced a fifth-century invasion by Jutes, Saxons, and Angles?",
      "answer": "Great Britain"
    },
    {
      "question": "The \"birdman cult\" emerged on this island, whose inhabitants have been divided into \"long- eared\" and \"short-eared\" groupings. This island, the key case study in Jared Diamond's book Collapse, has had its Polynesian natives ruled by Chile since 1888. For 10 points, name this Pacific island also called Rapa Nui, whose natives produced obsidian stone heads called moai.",
      "answer": "Easter Island"
    },
    {
      "question": "Leaders of a 1967 coup in this country compared themselves to doctors temporarily placing democracy in a sling. The “regime of the colonels” fell after a Turkish invasion of Cyprus put down a coup this country supported. The United States supported anti-Communist forces here during its civil war in the late 1940s. For 10 points, name this country.",
      "answer": "Greece"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thomas Henry Burge and Lord Frederick Cavendish were murdered in Phoenix Park in this city, and this city is home to a war memorial known as the Garden of Remembrance located on Parnell Square. It served as the capital of a free state until a 1937 constitution. The assassinations of the Cairo gang, a group of British intelligence officers, by the IRA sparked Bloody Sunday in this city. For ten points, name this capital of Ireland.",
      "answer": "Dublin"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Dutch built Fort Provintia on this island; today, Chihkan Tower stands at the former fort in the city of Tainan, which was this island’s capital during the Qing [CHING] dynasty. This island, once known as Formosa, was the destination of Chiang Kai-shek’s retreating Kuomintang. For ten points, name this island off the southeast coast of China, which disputes its sovereignty.",
      "answer": [
        "Taiwan or Republic of China",
        "Zhonghua Minguo",
        "Formosa before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1941, Lake Roosevelt was created in this state by the construction of the Grand Coulee Dam. In this state, the Cayuse Indians attacked missionaries in the Whitman massacre, sparking a war near modern-day Walla Walla. This state’s Elliott Bay is overlooked by the world’s largest public farmer’s market on Pike Place. Puget Sound juts into, for ten points, what Pacific Northwest state with capital Seattle, named in honor of the first U.S. President?",
      "answer": "Washington"
    },
    {
      "question": "A breach in the Porta Pia of this city led to its capture on the Venti Settembre, and Benvenuto Cellini claimed to have shot Charles, Duke of Orleans while defending the Castel Sant’Angelo in this city. Piedmont-Sardinia’s capture of this city was unsuccessfully resisted by Papal zouaves, leading to the capital of a new country being moved here from Florence. For ten points, name this capital city of Italy.",
      "answer": "Rome"
    },
    {
      "question": "A rebellion against Ottoman incursions into this modern-day country in the late 1400s was led by the nobleman Skanderbeg. An Italian invasion during the buildup to World War II ended monarchical rule in this nation under King Zog, and this Southeast European country was ruled for much of the Cold War by the Communist regime of Enver Hoxha [HAW-ja]. For ten points, name this Balkan nation whose capital is Tirana.",
      "answer": "Republic of Albania or Republika e Shqiperise"
    },
    {
      "question": "The destruction of Port Dover was used as an excuse to attack this city, but a hurricane allowed the defending side to move back from Brookeville. Robert Ross led the military force that attacked this city, following his success at the Battle of Bladensburg. Paul Jennings recounted Dolley Madison’s efforts to save the portrait of George Washington from a burning building in this city. For ten points, name this city, burned by British troops near the end of the War of 1812.",
      "answer": [
        "Washington D.C.",
        "either"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One construction in this city was covered with lapis lazuli and adorned with aurochs and dragons, symbolizing Adad and Marduk. Another construction in this city was legendarily built because Queen Amytis missed her Median homeland’s hills and greenery. For ten points, name this site of the Ishtar Gate, a Mesopotamian city where Nebuchadnezzar II built the Hanging Gardens.",
      "answer": "Babylon"
    },
    {
      "question": "Maurice Brodie developed a remedy for this disease while a research assistant at NYU, and John Enders was awarded the 1954 Nobel for his cultivation of this virus in the lab. The first live vaccine for this disease was tested at Letchworth Village in New York City. One sufferer of this disease had a bathtub installed on the USS Iowa for its treatment and founded the March of Dimes. For ten points, name this virus that paralyzed FDR.",
      "answer": "poliomyelitis"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country won the Battle of Breadfield, and it failed to subjugate Moldavia after the Battle of Baia. One campaign led by a king of this country lifted a siege of Belgrade, and that king lost the Battle of Kosovo to an empire that would later conquer this country at the Battle of Mohacs [MO-hotch]. For ten points, name this country led by Janos [YAH-nosh] Hunyadi, which was conquered by Suleiman the Magnificent and was once in a personal union with Austria.",
      "answer": [
        "Hungary",
        "Magyarorzag"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Francis Heney prosecuted this city’s Mayor Eugene Schmitz in a series of 1908 graft trials. William Ralston constructed the Palace Hotel in this city, which was later burned down after a disaster here killed the fire chief, Dennis Sullivan. The neighborhoods of North Beach and Telegraph Hill in this city were heavily damaged in that disaster, which featured heavy underreporting of casualties in this city’s Chinatown district. For ten points, name this California city which suffered a devastating earthquake in 1906.",
      "answer": "San Francisco"
    },
    {
      "question": "This river is crossed by the John Frost Bridge, which replaced a structure fought over in the Battle of Arnhem during Operation Market Garden. For many years, the Roman Empire’s Germanic frontier began at the Danube and this river, which also forms Liechtenstein’s western border. For ten points, name this longest river entirely within Western Europe, which flows from the Alps through Germany to the North Sea.",
      "answer": "Rhine River or Rijn River"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man started the Informbiro period after his country was expelled from the Cominform in 1948 after feuding with Joseph Stalin, and this leader was the only European who helped create the Non-AlignedMovement, servingasitsfirstSecretary-General. Thisman’scountry consistedofsixsocialist republics including Slovenia, Croatia, and Serbia. For ten points, name this longtime Communist ruler of Yugoslavia.",
      "answer": "Josip Tito"
    },
    {
      "question": "An empire situated in this modern day country was overthrown by the Sosso people after taking its capital at Koumbi Saleh. This country was home to the Ashanti Kingdom and is the birthplace of Kofi Annan. This was the first sub-Saharan African country to gain independence from a colonial power. Kwame Nkrumah led, for ten points, what country formerly known as the Gold Coast with capital Accra?",
      "answer": "Ghana"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1569, Francis Xavier’s men negotiated the use of this city as a Portuguese port, and it briefly became a Jesuit colony during the late Sengoku period. The Bockscar flew to this city after leaving cloud-obscured Kokura, where it released a plutonium bomb called the “Fat Man”. For ten points, name this Japanese city, the second target of a U.S. atomic bomb after Hiroshima.",
      "answer": "Nagasaki"
    },
    {
      "question": "Pittsburgh Pirates player Roberto Clemente died in an airplane accident en route to this nation. As a filibuster, William Walker overthrew this country’s government. Violeta Chamorro led this nation in the 1990s, ending a war in which one side was controversially supported by Ronald Reagan’s administration. Sandinista leader Daniel Ortega currently leads, for ten points, what Central American nation with capital Managua?",
      "answer": "Nicaragua"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s Moran Hill is home to a Friendship Tower built in 1959, as well as a triumphal arch commemorating the resistance against Japanese rule. The Taedong River flows through this city, passing by the Juche Tower. An unfinished 105-story pyramidal building, Ryugyong Hotel, dominates the skyline of, for ten points, what Asian capital city where Kim Jong-un governs?",
      "answer": "Pyongyang"
    },
    {
      "question": "A conservative newspaper in this city was run for years by Colonel Robert McCormick, whose slogan “World’s Greatest Newspaper” was applied to the local radio station, WGN. A paper from this city published the erroneous headline “Dewey Defeats Truman” during the election of 1948. According to legend, Mrs. O’Leary’s cow knocking over a lantern caused a Great Fire in October 1871 in this city. For ten points, name this home of the Tribune, the largest city in Illinois.",
      "answer": "Chicago"
    },
    {
      "question": "Apartment buildings in this city were called insulae, and it contained a sewage system known as the Cloaca Maxima that drained into the Tiber River. This city was built on the Palatine, Capitoline, and five other hills. For ten points, name this ancient city whose entertainment venues included the Circus Maximus and the Colosseum, the capital of a vast Italian empire.",
      "answer": "ancient Rome"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city was sacked two years after the surrender of Alamut fortress by the Assassins. This city was ruled by al-Musta’sim, until he was legendarily killed by being wrapped in a rug and trampled by horses, thereby preventing the shedding of royal blood. In 1258, Hulagu Khan made the Tigris River “run black with ink” after his Mongols sacked, for ten points, what capital of the Abbasid Empire that now serves as the capital of modern Iraq?",
      "answer": "Baghdad"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s Pioneer Park, on top of Telegraph Hill, contains a tower built in memory of Lillie Hitchcock Coit. Its Russian Hill neighborhood is known for a one-block stretch of Lombard Street with eight hairpin turns. This city’s Castro neighborhood was the launching pad for the political career of Harvey Milk. The Haight-Ashbury district nurtured the “hippie” counterculture in, for ten points, what “city by the bay” in Northern California?",
      "answer": "San Francisco"
    },
    {
      "question": "Six decades after one city lost this status, the Mississippi River changed course and separated the city from the rest of its state. After Kaskaskia and Vandalia held this status in the early 19th century, it was held by a city that is home to Oak Ridge Cemetery and was the site of the “House Divided” speech. For ten points, name this political status that has been held since 1837 by Springfield, where Abraham Lincoln thus served as a state representative.",
      "answer": "capitals of Illinois"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this country, a duel between Alan Breck and the son of an outlaw is settled by a contest involving musical instruments rather than with weapons. Frank Osbaldistone pursues his cousin to this country in a novel that was admired by this country’s native author, Robert Louis Stevenson. The primary setting of Kidnapped and Rob Roy is, for ten points, what country, the site of the Battle of Culloden during a Jacobite Rising?",
      "answer": "Scotland"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country’s Albay Province contains a volcano known for being a “perfect cone,” Mayon Volcano. Typhoon Diding hit this nation at the same time another volcano erupted here, in the second-largest eruption of the twentieth century. The capture of its Corregidor Island by Japan in World War II led Douglas MacArthur to proclaim “I will return.” This home country of Mount Pinatubo was the site of the Bataan Death March on Luzon, its largest island. For ten points, name this Asian country whose capital is on Manila Bay.",
      "answer": "the Philippines"
    },
    {
      "question": "This speech presents a metaphor between an island of poverty and an ocean of prosperity and claims that the government’s promissory note has been returned with an “insufficient funds” stamp. This speech’s final section begins by claiming that freedom should ring through every valley and every hamlet and closes with the repeated declaration “Free at last!” For ten points, name this 1963 speech delivered during the March on Washington by Martin Luther King.",
      "answer": "I Have a Dream speech"
    },
    {
      "question": "Engravings by William Hogarth are thought to be precursors to these works, especially one wherein the city of London is destroyed in 1720 by the South Sea Bubble. A creator of these works used them to popularize the elephant as a symbol for the GOP. One of these created after the Albany Congress shows a snake cut into 8 pieces and was made by Benjamin Franklin. Thomas Nast created, for ten points, what type of parody artworks often published in newspapers to comment on current events?",
      "answer": "political cartoons"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city gained its nickname of “City of Palaces” due to a comment by traveler Alexander von Humboldt. Ten days before this city hosted an Olympic games, a group of students and protesters were killed in its Plaza de las Tres Culturas in the Tlatelolco Massacre. Two American athletes displayed a Black Power salute during the 1968 Summer Olympics in, for ten points, what North American capital city?",
      "answer": "Mexico City"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country’s ruling party has been accused of holding slush funds through Senator Luis Barcenas’ Swiss bank accounts. The leadership of this country’s Socialist Worker’s Party is vacant after a dispute with Susana Diaz led Pedro Sanchez to resign. In October 2016, this country’s Prime Minister, Mariano Rajoy of the People’s Party, was sworn in for a second term after a 10-month period of political deadlock. For ten points, name this Iberian country whose capital is Madrid.",
      "answer": "Spain"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man besieged a city after a revolt by Ibn Jahhaf killed the city’s ruler, al-Qadir. After defeat at the Battle of Sagrajas [sah-grah-has], Alfonso VI recalled this man from exile to command his armies. Sancho II of Castile made this man his standard-bearer and allowed him to command the expedition against Zaragoza. This man established an independent state based at Valencia after defeating the Almoravid Berbers during the Reconquista. For ten points, name this national hero of Spain.",
      "answer": [
        "El Cid or Rodrigo D´ıaz de Vivar",
        "El Campeador"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Finland is investigating claims that Rami Adham, this city’s “toy smuggler,” has misused charity donations. Fighting in this city has destroyed parts of the Al-Madina Souq district. Omar Daqneesh was photographed sitting in an ambulance after surviving an air strike in this city. In an interview on MSNBC, Libertarian Party candidate Gary Johnson was widely mocked after asking “What is [this city]?” For ten points, name this city in northern Syria, its most populous prior to the Syrian Civil War.",
      "answer": "Aleppo or Halab"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man blamed stray American searchlights for providing vision for his enemy’s guns at Agua Prieta. This post-Madero head of the Divisi´on del Norte worked with Emiliano Zapata to overthrow Venustiano Carranza. George Patton was among the leaders of a force sent to capture this man following his cross-border raid on Columbus, New Mexico. “Blackjack” Pershing failed to kill, for ten points, what general of the Mexican revolution?",
      "answer": "Francisco “Pancho” Villa"
    },
    {
      "question": "The downtown of one city in this state was flooded in 1913 by the Great Miami River. A 1995 accord reached in this state ended the war in Bosnia-Herzegovina. Another river in this state caught fire several times, most famously in 1969. The northeastern portion of this state, once claimed by Connecticut as the Western Reserve, is home to the Cuyahoga River. For ten points, name this midwestern state, home to Dayton, Columbus, and Cleveland.",
      "answer": "Ohio"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Kuttabul was sunk in a harbor in this country by three raiding midget submarines. A commander of this country’s forces, Selwyn Porter, oversaw a series of defensive retreats in the Kokoda Track campaign. During World War II, this country was led by John Curtin and Robert Menzies. The Battle of Coral Sea effectively ended Japanese plans to isolate and invade this country. For ten points, name this Allied country that endured assaults on its harbors of Darwin and Sydney.",
      "answer": "Australia"
    },
    {
      "question": "Four children of the More family were boarded onto this ship after their mother was embroiled in an adultery scandal involving Jakob Blakeway. Christopher Jones was the captain of this ship, which was originally intended to be accompanied on an ocean crossing by the Speedwell. The journals of William Bradford preserve a governing document or compact named for this ship. For ten points, name this ship that established the Plymouth Colony after landing at Cape Cod.",
      "answer": "Mayflower"
    },
    {
      "question": "A duchy of this name was ruled by a monarch nicknamed “Longsword” and founded by his father, Rollo. A woman named Emma hailed from this region and married Ethelred the Unready. A duke of this region wed Matilda of Flanders and launched an invasion that culminated in the 1066 Battle of Hastings and conquest of Anglo-Saxon England. For ten points, name this region of north France, the home of William the Conqueror.",
      "answer": "Normandy"
    },
    {
      "question": "This body of water, also known as Lago Cochibola, contains a namesake population of freshwater sharks. The first registered Spanish settlement in mainland North America, Granada, is on its shores. The Bryan-Chamorro Treaty gave the US rights to build a canal through this lake, a proposal recently revived by an Hong Kong consortium. For ten points, name this largest lake in Central America, connected by the Tipitapa River to Lake Managua, found in a country also home to the Contras and Sandinistas.",
      "answer": "Lake Nicaragua"
    },
    {
      "question": "An attempt to dissolve this alliance ended at Rotebro when king Hans captured the peasant leader Sten Sture the Elder. This alliance was weakened when the Engelbrekt Rebellion managed to unseat Erik of Pomerania in favor of Christopher of Bavaria. The 1523 coronation of Gustav I Vasa marked the end of this alliance, which was constructed by Margaret I and Haakon VII in order to challenge the Hanseatic League. For ten points, name this medieval union of Denmark, Norway, and Sweden.",
      "answer": "Kalmar Union or the Union of Kalmaris"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s skyline features two cranes, known as “Samson and Goliath,” in the shipyards of Harland and Wolff. Its neighborhoods of Short Strand and Cluan Place are separated by a “peace line,” as are Falls Road and Shankill Road. The RMS Titanic was built in this city, which was home to a parliament at Stormont which was dissolved during the height of the Troubles. The Good Friday Agreement was signed in, for ten points, what city, the capital of Northern Ireland?",
      "answer": "Belfast"
    },
    {
      "question": "An unsuccessful 1970 fascist coup in this country was instigated by a man nicknamed “The Black Prince.” This country’s communist party forged a mainstream alliance in the Historic Compromise. Antonio Negri was arrested, then released, for leading the Red Brigades, who kidnapped and killed a prime minister of this country during its turbulent Years of Lead. For ten points, name this European country that chose to become a republic in 1946 and was led by Aldo Moro.",
      "answer": "Italy"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1755, this city was struck by the Cape Ann earthquake, the largest earthquake to hit the northeastern United States. This city’s namesake “Fruit Company” was a predecessor of the United Fruit Company in the 19th century. This city’s cultural elite were known as “Brahmins” and included the Lowell and Cabot families. John Adams gained fame for defending British soldiers accused of participating in a 1775 “Massacre” in, for ten points, what capital city of Massachusetts?",
      "answer": "Boston"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this city, Roland Freiser presided over the extra-judicial People’s Court. The communist Marinus van der Lubbe was convicted of arson in this city in 1933. This city’s Gauleiter for two decades was Joseph Goebbels, and a famous photo taken by Yevgeny Khaldei shows a soldier raising a Soviet flag over this city’s Reichstag. The Fu¨hrerbunker was constructed in, for ten points, what capital city of Nazi Germany?",
      "answer": "Berlin"
    },
    {
      "question": "A scandal in this country involved the changing of Ewha University’s standards to allow for nepotism. A leader of this country allegedly drew upon a shadow cabal of advisers known as the “Eight Heavenly Fairies.” An investigation in this country revealed that many presidential speeches had been altered ahead of time by the shaman Choi Soon-Sil. For ten points, name this country whose president Park Geun-Hye was impeached in 2017 in the midst of mass protests in Seoul.",
      "answer": "South Korea or the Republic of Korea"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city was the destination of retreating troops in the Bladensburg Races. Alexander Hamilton convinced several delegates from this city to support his Assumption Bill by supporting the Residence Act, which provided for the purchase of lands near this city. Pierre L’Enfant designed a plan that established the layout of this city, which was burned by British forces during the War of 1812. For ten points, name this city where Dolley Madison saved paintings that were hung in the White House.",
      "answer": "Washington, D.C. or the District of Columbia"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1962, this Prime Minister’s country lost the Aksai Chin region to China after a brief border war. After this man’s mentor was assassinated, this man gave an impromptu speech in which he said “the light has gone out of our lives.” On the eve of his nation’s independence, this leader described his people’s “tryst with destiny.” For ten points, name this prot´eg´e of Mahatma Gandhi and opponent of Muhammad Ali Jinnah, the first and longest-serving Prime Minister of India.",
      "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country established relations with Ethiopia’s Dawit II after settling the Swahili Coast. To defend against this country, the Sultanate of Oman built the Old Fort in Zanzibar. After the collapse of its Estado Novo, this country relinquished its colonies in Angola and Mozambique. For ten points, name this country whose caravel ships explored the world under Vasco de Gama and Henry the Navigator.",
      "answer": "Portugal"
    },
    {
      "question": "A palace in this region contained the Moorish Hall and Hall of the Singers, though neither of those were finished once the king mysteriously died in the waters of Lake Starnberg. In this region, a hill overlooking Hohenschwangau village was the site of a fortress that inspired the Sleeping Beauty castle, Neuschwanstein [noysh-van-stein]. The “Mad King” Ludwig II once ruled, for ten points, what German region whose capital is Munich?",
      "answer": "Bavaria"
    },
    {
      "question": "An aristocrat boards a train bound for this region to follow the woman he loves, a prostitute who was tricked into giving a womanizing merchant a lethal dose of arsenic. This region is the setting of the later parts of the novel Resurrection. Sonya Marmeladova travels to this region near the end of Crime and Punishment. For ten points, name this region to which Raskolnikov is exiled to complete a sentence of eight years of hard labor.",
      "answer": "Siberia"
    },
    {
      "question": "People who were not in one of these organizations revolted in Florence during the Ciompi [chomp-ee] Revolt. An alliance of these organizations formed a trading league in the Baltic Sea called the Hanseatic League. Some members of these organizations progressed from apprentices to journeymen to master craftsmen. For ten points, name these town-based medieval associations of merchants and skilled laborers.",
      "answer": "guilds"
    },
    {
      "question": "After this man’s first campaign, commemorative monuments were carved in rock at the Dog River north of modern-day Beirut. Early in this leader’s reign, he defeated the Sherden sea pirates. At the Orontes River, this ruler fought the Hittite King Muwatallis in the largest chariot battle in history. This successor of Seti I constructed the temple complex at Abu Simbel and inaugurated that temple alongside his wife, Nefertari. For ten points, name this pharaoh who won the Battle of Kadesh.",
      "answer": [
        "Ramesses II",
        "Ramesses the Great",
        "Ozymandias"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A leader of this religion named James Strang established a controversial “kingdom” on Beaver Island in Lake Michigan in the mid 19th Century. A leader of this religion founded the territorial capital of Fillmore after his plans to found the state of Deseret fell through. Members of this religion were led to Nauvoo, Illinois by Joseph Smith and then to Salt Lake City by Brigham Young. For ten points, name this religion whose members founded the Utah Territory.",
      "answer": [
        "Mormonism",
        "word forms",
        "the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints",
        "LDS"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A plaza in this city includes Cellini’s sculpture of Perseus and a copy of a statue now held in this city’s Academy of Fine Arts. Another museum in this city holds La Primavera and The Birth of Venus by Sandro Botticelli, who primarily worked in this city. A family of art patrons in this city included Lorenzo the Magnificent and Cosimo I, who commissioned this city’s Uffizi Gallery. For ten points, name this Italian city once controlled by the Medici family.",
      "answer": "Florence or Firenze"
    },
    {
      "question": "A 2003 court case ruled that Job Charnock was not the founder of this city. Lord Curzon created a monument in this city’s Dalhousie Square to commemorate an incident, of which John Zephaniah Howell wrote an account of brutalities committed in Fort William by the Nawab of Bengal. 146 prisoners were locked in a cell in this city, in which only 23 survived the conditions. British prisoners were kept in the “Black Hole” of, for ten points, what capital of West Bengal in eastern India?",
      "answer": [
        "Kolkata",
        "Calcutta",
        "additional information relating to the Black Hole of Calcutta",
        "Kolkata after “Curzon” is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "E´douard Drumont condemned the victim of this event in his newspaper La Libre Parole. This event concerned a document called the Bordereau, which had been forged by Major Henry. Ferdinand Ester´azy’s role in this event was discovered by Georges Picquart a year after its initial suspect was imprisoned on Devil’s Island. E´mile Zola wrote the letter J’accuse as a response to, for ten points, what 1890s affair in which a Jewish French army officer was falsely imprisoned for treason?",
      "answer": "Dreyfus Affair"
    },
    {
      "question": "Joseph Bazalgette designed this city’s sewer system, which reduced the frequency of cholera outbreaks and prevented a recurrence of the 1858 “Great Stink.” This city was one of first sites for rubber to be grown outside of South America, as part of a botanical research project at Kew. This city’s Crystal Palace stood in its Hyde Park until 1936 and was opened in 1851 by Queen Victoria. Sewage was once pumped into the River Thames in, for ten points, what capital city of England?",
      "answer": "London"
    },
    {
      "question": "A medieval philosopher from this country was the first Westerner to record the formula for gunpowder in his Opus Majus. Another medieval philosopher from this country developed a “law of parsimony” that seeks to solve problems by working with the hypothesis with the fewest assumptions; that “razor” was developed by William of Ockham. For ten points, name this home country of Roger Bacon where medieval scholars studied at the University of Oxford.",
      "answer": "England"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this country, independence leader and human rights activist Hannah Kudjoe created an anti-nudity campaign and distributed clothes. Operation Cold Chop deposed a ruler of this country who was part of the Big Six and founded the Convention People’s Party. The “Motion of Destiny” speech called for the independence of this nation, where the Akosombo dam was built on the Volta River by Kwame Nkrumah. The British colony of Gold Coast controlled what is now, for ten points, what West African country governed from Accra?",
      "answer": "Ghana"
    },
    {
      "question": "This state’s Barataria Nature Reserve and Chalmette Battlefield are administered together as part of the Jean Lafitte National Historical Park. A so-called “country” in this state, centered around the Atchafalaya River and the city of Lafayette, was settled by French speakers who were removed from present-day Nova Scotia in the Great Expulsion. Cajuns settled in, for ten points, what state that contains the Mississippi River Delta and was the site of the 1815 Battle of New Orleans?",
      "answer": "Louisiana"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country commemorates a deadly 1952 student protest on Language Movement Day. A university in this country was attacked by tanks to flush out Chhatra League leaders in 1971. Yahya Khan launched Operation Searchlight to suppress the independence-seeking Awami League in this country, which was known at the time as East Pakistan. For ten points, name this country that, after gaining its independence from Pakistan in 1971, established its capital at Dhaka.",
      "answer": "Bangladesh"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man confused the Lachine [la-sheen] Rapids as the Northwest Passage to China. This man brought Chief Donnacona with him on a return voyage to describe the riches of the northern Kingdom of Saguenay. This explorer was the first to describe the land that Iroquois inhabitants lived in as “Canada.” For ten points, name this Frenchman who discovered the mouth of the St. Lawrence River and mapped settlements at Quebec City and Montreal.",
      "answer": "Jacques Cartier"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city fell under the rule of the patron Ottone’s [oh-toh-nay’s] family after he won the Battle of Desio against Napo della Torre. Twelve “captains and defenders of liberty” were elected to write this city’s laws when it was briefly reorganized into the Golden Ambrosian Republic following the fall of the Visconti family. After that republic fell, this city was ruled by the Sforzas. For ten points, name this capital of Lombardy, a city in Northern Italy.",
      "answer": "Milan"
    },
    {
      "question": "A ruler of this country had, in his earlier military career, led a fleet against Alfredo Acton that tried to break the Otranto Barrage. This country, which faced the 1918 Aster Revolution, was the site of a very short-lived Soviet Republic led by Bela Kun. During World War II, Miklos Horthy was a regent of, for ten points, what European country that was ruled by the medieval Arpad dynasty and, until World War I, part of a dual monarchy with Austria?",
      "answer": "Kingdom of Hungary"
    },
    {
      "question": "In May 2015, this country became the first to pass a referendum legalizing same-sex marriage, and it is considering another referendum to repeal the abortion-forbidding Article 9 of its constitution. Leo Varadkar’s elevation as leader of this country made him the first biracial leader of a European country, and the first LGBT person to hold the title of Taoiseach [tee-shuck]. For ten points, name this country where Varadkar leads Fine Gael [finn-neh GALE], the rival party to Fianna F´ail [fee-uh-nuh FOIL] and Sinn F´ein [shin FAYN] in Dublin.",
      "answer": "Republic of Ireland"
    },
    {
      "question": "Genseric captured this city after his betrothal to Eudocia was broken, and Alaric was able to capture this city after the death of Stilicho. The Battle of the Allia led to the capture of this city, which was forced to measure out ransom money using weighted scales by Brennus. Romulus Augustulus was deposed after the capture of this city in 476 AD. For ten points, name this city that was sacked several times during the fall of its Italy-based empire.",
      "answer": "Rome"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what became known as this city’s “mile,” a group of troops including Randall Ramaglia walked through RPG fire to a rally point at National Street. William Garrison commanded troops in a battle in this city that was part of the larger Operation Gothic Serpent; in that battle, troops under Mohammad Farah Aidid shot down two Black Hawk helicopters. For ten points, name this site of a 1993 battle involving Delta Force, the capital of Somalia.",
      "answer": [
        "Mogadishu",
        "Hamar"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One leader of this country wanted to create a buffer state called “Intermarium” out of his country and its neighbors. This country, which lost a plebiscite awarding control of the Teschen district, defeated an invading force under Marshal Tukachevsky; the key battle of that campaign took place in this country’s capital and was nicknamed the “Miracle on the Vistula”. For ten points, name this country led by Jozef Pilsudski.",
      "answer": "Poland"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man violated the sovereignty of a neighboring country by recognizing the Act of Free Choice assemblies, and he turned the Golkar group into a personal political machine. The Santa Cruz Massacre occurredaspartofthisman’sattemptstocrackdownonFRETILIN,arevolutionarygroupinabreakaway region of his country. This man recruited the so-called “Berkeley Mafia” to create economic growth in a regime he called the “New Order.” For ten points, name this politician who succeeded Sukarno as leader of Indonesia.",
      "answer": "Suharto"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s St. Anne’s Church contains the tombs of three brothers of the Fugger family, whose banking enterprise operated here. The painter Hans Holbein the Younger was born in this city, where a 1555 peace treaty was signed to end a war between the Schmalkaldic League and Charles V. Charles had earlier convened a Diet in this city where Philip Melancthon helped draft a namesake Lutheran Confession. For ten points, name this Free Imperial City in Bavaria.",
      "answer": "Augsburg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Blackbeard died on this state’s island of Ocracoke. Virginia Dare’s birth on an island in this state made her the first person of English descent born in the Americas. A carving of the word “Croatoan” was found on an island in this state’s Outer Banks that was home to a “Lost Colony.” Roanoke was found in, for ten points, what state whose capital was named after Sir Walter Raleigh?",
      "answer": "North Carolina"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country is the setting of a novel in which a promise to watch Pinocchio is broken when Jalil refuses to see his estranged daughter. In a story set in this country, Rasheed is angered when his wife Miriam asks what a communist is at the start of a revolution against Daoud Khan. This setting of A Thousand Splendid Suns serves as Amir’s home in one novel before he was forced to flee from a Soviet invasion. For ten points, name this country where Khaled Hosseini’s The Kite Runner is set in Kabul.",
      "answer": "Afghanistan"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s sister Sophia once cut a hole in his throne to whisper advice during meetings. Until the death of his half-brother, this man jointly ruled with Ivan V. This man learned shipbuilding in the Netherlands during his “Grand Embassy” tour of Europe. Modernizations under this man included the creation of a new capital on the Neva river. For ten points, identify this “Great” Russian tsar who westernized the country.",
      "answer": [
        "Peter the Great or Peter I",
        "Peter alone after “Great” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A villa in Florence inspired the name of a map of this island known as the Castello Plan. Seyseys, the leader of the Canarsee, led a negotiation for this island. An artillery section built along the southern portion of this island was known as the Battery. Members of the Lenape tribe were supposedly given 60 guilders by Peter Minuit to transfer ownership of this island to the Dutch. For ten points, name this island of New York City that is home to Wall Street.",
      "answer": "Manhattan"
    },
    {
      "question": "Funding for this site was secured for Peter Norbeck, though it was supposed to originally be placed in the Needles region to honor Red Cloud and Lewis and Clark. After abandoning a similar commission at Stone Mountain venerating Stonewall Jackson and Robert E. Lee, Gutzon Borglum designed this monument in the Black Hills. For ten points, name this South Dakota monument featuring the faces of four presidents.",
      "answer": "Mount Rushmore"
    },
    {
      "question": "A golfer from this country is the only winner of the Masters to not have his jacket stored at Augusta, after he claimed to forget to bring it back; that golfer from this country became the first non-American to win a career Grand Slam in 1968. One of the earliest non-European golf clubs was founded in this country’s city of Durban. Gary Player is a golfer from this country who controversially supported Hendrik Verwoerd [feh-vert], though he later disavowed him. For ten points, name this country where the Cape Town Open is held.",
      "answer": "South Africa"
    },
    {
      "question": "A new religious movement from this country worships “God the Parent” and teaches about achieving the “Joyous Life.” Along with that religion, Tenrikyo, another new religious movement in this country became recognized as a terrorist group after it released sarin gas in a subway. A controversial shrine in this country honors war criminals, and many other shrines in this country honor spirits or deities called “kami.” For ten points, name this East Asian country home to Shintoism.",
      "answer": [
        "Japan or Nippon",
        "or Nihon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Cyclists traversing this island usually take about two weeks to go the over 800 miles from Land’s End to John o’ Groats, taking motorways like the M5, which opened in 1962. In a 1967 paper that predated his coining of the term “fractal,” Benoit Mandelbrot discussed the length of this island’s coast. The Antonine Wall and Hadrian’s Wall were built on, for ten points, what largest European island that is home to the countries of Scotland, Wales, and England?",
      "answer": "Great Britain"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1511, a force from this country led by Alfonso de Albuquerque captured the city of Malacca. Prior to 1975, this country controlled East Timor, and prior to 1961, it controlled the city of Goa. An explorer from this country was the first European to reach the Cape of Good Hope in South Africa. Explorers Vasco da Gama and Bartolomeu Dias were from, for ten points, what country where Prince Henry the Navigator sponsored explorations as a rival to its neighbor, Spain?",
      "answer": "Portugal"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. Planners decided to use this type of construction for Kansai International Airport to avoid noise complaints and the hassles of eminent domain. The Palm Jumeirah is this type of construction in the Persian Gulf, found near similar constructions in the shape of the countries of the world on the Dubai coastline. The Chinese “Great Wall of Sand” plans to use, for ten points, what process to build additional ports and runways in the South China Sea?",
      "answer": "artificial islands"
    },
    {
      "question": "Jesse Elliot was the second-in-command during this battle, whose combatants included the Queen Charlotte and the Caledonia. This battle was preceded by a ten day blockade of Presque Isle. One leader in this battle transferred his command to the Niagara after his original ship, the USS Lawrence, was destroyed by enemy fire. Upon his victory in this battle, that leader wrote to his superior that “We have met the enemy and they are ours.” For ten points, name this 1813 naval victory for Oliver Hazard Perry at a namesake Great Lake.",
      "answer": "Battle of Lake Erie"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city used a luxury tax to keep rents artificially low in public housing projects like the enormous Karl-Marx-Hof during a period from 1918-34 in which this city was nicknamed “Red.” Moritz Schlick organized an influential intellectual group in this city around 1918; that group, which included members like Godel and Carnap, advocated for logical empiricism and was called this city’s Circle. For ten points, name this home city of Sigmund Freud, the capital of Austria.",
      "answer": "Vienna or Wien"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was forced to begin his most famous campaign after his compatriots launched a drunken raid on settlements by the Salmon River. This leader was able to escape the clutches of Samuel Sturgis at the Battle of Canyon Creek, even though he was betrayed by the Crow tribe. After Oliver Howard captured this man at the Battle of Bear Paw Mountain, this leader said that he “will fight no more forever.” For ten points, name this chief of the Nez Perce who attempted to lead his tribe to Canada.",
      "answer": "Chief Joseph"
    },
    {
      "question": "A German territory in what is now this country was governed by Ambrosius Ehinger, who was employed by the Welser banking family. The British Legions under Miguel de la Torre lost to Jose Antonio Paez, who led this nation’s forces at the Battle of Carabobo. Simon Bolivar’s Decree of War to the Death primarily pertained to this country. For ten points, name this South American country that gained independence after the Battle of Lake Maracaibo.",
      "answer": "Venezuela"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this city, the Fortaleza do Monte overlooks the remains of a church whose facade was constructed by Japanese Christians under Carlo Spinola. Following a Dutch East India Company attack on this city in 1622, the Guia Fortress was built. The Bridge of Friendship is one of three bridges connecting parts of this city, where reclamation projects connected the islands of Coloane and Taipa. For ten points, name this special administrative region in the Pearl River Delta alongside Hong Kong, a city that was under Portuguese control until 1999.",
      "answer": "Macau"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thomas Merton wrote “The Seven-Story Mountain” about his life in one of these places. The site of the burning bush is supposedly located at one of these places on the Sinai Peninsula in Egypt. The most important Orthodox examples of these places are located on Mt. Athos in Greece. In the 1530s, Henry VIII closed many of these places down in the “Dissolution” of them. For ten points, name these institutions where religious devotees live in a community, including monks and nuns.",
      "answer": "monastery"
    },
    {
      "question": "Following a 2006 war, “The Right of Peace” advocated for residents of this territory to live in one neighboring country while holding citizenship in another. The Mukataa of a political leader of this territory was once found in its capital city of Ramallah until it was raided by the IDF in 2002. The founder of Fatah, Yasser Arafat, administered his main organization from this territory, which is named for its position relative to the Jordan River. For ten points, name this territory that makes up the State of Palestine along with the Gaza Strip.",
      "answer": "West Bank"
    },
    {
      "question": "This island’s Deltaterrasserne [“delta”-”terra”-sern] site was inhabited by the Independence I and II cultures. Archaeologists discovered the ruins of the Saqqaq culture around this island’s Disko Bay. The northernmost point of this island is named after philanthropist Morris Jesup. The US Air Force maintains Thule Base on this island, where over 30% of the population lives in the capital, Nuuk. For ten points, name this largest island in the world, an autonomous country within Denmark.",
      "answer": "Greenland or Kalaallit Nunaat"
    },
    {
      "question": "A portion of this modern-day state was organized into the self-governing Cimarron Territory by settlers who moved before the land was surveyed. Inhabitants of what became this state proposed the State of Sequoyah. Several Native American tribes were forced to move to Indian Territory in this state during the Trail of Tears. For ten points, name this state where “Sooners” founded cities like Tulsa.",
      "answer": "Oklahoma"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1603, an ice floe destroyed this city’s first permanent bridge, which connected it to the jurydyka of Praga. A shoemaker named Jan Kilinski led the armed peasantry of this city against the occupying Russian Empire in a 1794 uprising. Ju¨rgen Stroop suppressed an uprising in this city, eventually sending most of the rebels to Treblinka and other death camps. A 1943 ghetto uprising took place in, for ten points, what capital city of Poland?",
      "answer": "Warsaw"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Matoa sank in this lake in a 1913 storm that killed over 200 sailors across nearly a dozen ships. This lake’s town of Goderich has been a salt mining center since the 1800s. This lake contains the Georgian Bay, which is bounded by the largest freshwater island in the world. Manitoulin Island and Saginaw Bay are in this lake, which the Saint Marys River feeds from Lake Superior. For ten points, name this American Great Lake that forms the northeastern border of Michigan.",
      "answer": "Lake Huron"
    },
    {
      "question": "On February 3, 1977, a meeting of this country’s top military council ended in a shootout where fifty-eight people died. That event kicked off this country’s Red Terror in which up to 500,000 people died and the military council, known as the Derg, emerged supreme. In 1983, a massive famine in this country led to international attention, including the Live Aid concerts. For ten points, name this African country that once controlled Eritrea on the Red Sea and has capital Addis Ababa.",
      "answer": "Ethiopia"
    },
    {
      "question": "A Defense Minister of this country said “it is hard to search for a black cat in a dark room, especially if it’s not there” about the presence of soldiers in a neighboring country. The leader of that neighboring country, Viktor Yanukovych fled to this country after the Euromaidan protests. Soldiers from this country were termed “little green men” and dismissed as being militiamen despite taking Donbass for this country. For ten points, name this country that annexed Crimea in 2014 under Vladimir Putin.",
      "answer": "Russia"
    },
    {
      "question": "A thinker from this country wrote Dialectical and Historical Materialism, which laid the groundwork for this country’s political ideology. In the book Our Revolution, another thinker from this country argued against another thinker from here with the idea of a “permanent revolution.” One early leader of this country outlined his political philosophy in the “April Theses.” For ten points, name this former country, whose political thinkers included Leon Trotsky, Joseph Stalin, and Vladmir Lenin. ANSWER:SovietUnion(orUSSR;orUnionofSovietSocialistRepublics;acceptCCCPorSoyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik;promptonRussia;promptonGeorgia;promptonUkraine) (7) In a publicity stunt, Andrew Carnegie led an elephant across this city’s Eads Bridge to prove the stability of the steel used in its construction. This city’s Forest Park hosted the 1904 World’s Fair. A national park in this city, which was formerly called the Jefferson National Expansion Memorial, contains a massive steel catenary designed by Eero Saarinen. The Gateway Arch is in, for ten points, what large city in eastern Missouri?",
      "answer": "St. Louis"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country’s national dish consists of a mix of chili peppers and cheese called Ema datshi. In the Battle of the Five Lamas, invaders were blown up while trying to loot this country’s Simtokha Dzong. This country, which banned climbing its mountain Gangkhar Puensum, was led until 2006 by King Jigme Singye Wangchuck, who coined the term Gross National Happiness. Druk the Thunder Dragon is featured on the flag of, for ten points, what Himalayan nation ruled from Thimphu?",
      "answer": "Kingdom of Bhutan or Druk Yul"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country carried out Operation Cerberus to successfully extract its ships from the port of Brest. The Glorious was sunk by a 27,000 yard shot from one of this country’s Scharnhorst-class battleships. At the Battle of the Denmark Strait, the Prince of Wales and Hood were defeated by this country’s Prinz Eugen and Bismarck. For ten points, name this country whose navy attacked Allied shipping using wolf-packs of U-boat ships.",
      "answer": "Nazi Germany"
    },
    {
      "question": "Ameteorologicalagencymonitors59secretlocationsfortheinitialpresenceoftheseitems.Specimens of the Yoshino variety of these organisms have been proven to be genetically identical to each other, making disease a risk. Maps track a namesake “front” of these items, which are produced from trees in the genus Prunus and are appreciated in a custom called hanami. Springtime crowds flock to Japan to see, for ten points, what types of flowers, otherwise known as sakura?",
      "answer": [
        "cherry blossoms",
        "sakura before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The name of this state was inspired by the name of an island in a book by Garci Rodriguez de Montalvo. After landing near this state’s Point Reyes, an explorer gave the name “New Albion” to a region in this state. The Chumash were taken to pueblos to be taught Christianity after being transported from its Channel Islands. Vizcaino named several major cities in this state, including Monterey. El Camino Real passes between 21 missions in, for ten points, what western US state that underwent the Bear Flag Revolt?",
      "answer": "California"
    },
    {
      "question": "The heresy of Adoptionism was created by this city’s archbishop Elipandus. In one legend, this city’s Alcazar fortress refused to surrender, even after Jose Moscardo’s son was taken for ransom. This European city produced swords used by both Hannibal’s Carthaginians and the Roman legions; those swords were made of a steel alloy that was unmatched until the discovery of Damascus steel in the Middle Ages. For ten points, name this city in central Spain that was once called the “Imperial City” as the seat of Charles V’s court.",
      "answer": "Toledo"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s government lost the Supreme Court case Ricci v. DeStefano against a group of firefighters who were not promoted despite passing qualification tests. In this city, James Hillhouse established the first public tree planting project in America, leading it to be nicknamed “The Elm City.” This city was the birthplace of a group known as “Order 322” or “Skull and Bones,” whose collegiate members included John Kerry and George W. Bush. For ten points, name this Connecticut city that is home to Yale University.",
      "answer": "New Haven"
    },
    {
      "question": "Asettlement known as Keshetwas createdon the grounds where this region’s primary city of Quneitra had been burned to the ground. The southern portion of Mount Hermon extends into this region, where the Purple Line was created after a ceasefire during the 1973 Yom Kippur War. In the aftermath of a 1967 war, over 100,000 refugees fled this region. For ten points, name this plateau region of the Levant that Israel captured from Syria during the Six Day War.",
      "answer": "Golan Heights"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this city, the Albizzi family came to power as a result of the Ciompi [[CHOM-pee]] Revolt in 1378. Filippo Brunelleschi [[broo-nell-ESK-ee]] won a competition to complete the Santa Maria del Fiore [[fee-OR-ay]] Cathedral in this city in 1418. This guild republic rose to European prominence as a result of its banking prowess. Patrons of this city’s leader, Lorenzo, included Da Vinci and Michelangelo. For ten points, name this important Tuscan city ruled by the Medici family.",
      "answer": "Florence or Firenze"
    },
    {
      "question": "The basin of the Powder River separates this mountain range from the Bighorn Mountains to the west. This mountain range provides an alternate name for the Great Sioux War of 1876. The name of the tallest peak in this mountain range was changed from Harney Peak to Black Elk Peak in 2016. Gutzon Borglum designed a monument showing the faces of four presidents in this range. For ten points, what hills contain Mount Rushmore in South Dakota?",
      "answer": "Black Hills"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city's \"Maidens\" were transported to Mount Sinai Hospital in New York for treatment of keloid scars. The dome of the Industrial Promotion Hall in this city now serves as its namesake Peace Memorial. A Pulitzer Prize-winning book by John Hersey chronicles six survivors of an attack on this city, on which “Little Boy\" was dropped. For ten points, what Japanese city was devastated by an atomic bomb three days before a similar attack on Nagasaki?",
      "answer": "Hiroshima"
    },
    {
      "question": "Colonists in this state protested a British law in the Pine Tree Riot. Following the Antinomian Controversy, Puritan John Wheelwright founded this state's town of Exeter. Queen Anne's War was ended by a treaty named for this state's city of Portsmouth. Daniel Webster defended his alma mater located in this state in the case Dartmouth College v. Woodward. Franklin Pierce was born in, for ten points, what New England \"Granite State\" governed from Concord?",
      "answer": "New Hampshire"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a 1910 toast, John Collins Bossidy called this city “the land of the bean and the cod.” Abolitionist sentiment surged in this city when William Lloyd Garrison founded The Liberator newsletter there. Despite the anti-Catholic sentiment of its founders, this city became a center of Irish-Catholic politics. Oliver Wendell Holmes, Sr. wrote about this city’s so-called “Brahmin” elite. For ten points, name this major New England city, nicknamed “Beantown.”",
      "answer": "Boston, Massachusetts"
    },
    {
      "question": "An 1885 rebellion resulted in this polity’s reorganization under its first premier, Sir Frederick W.A.G. Haultain. Originally, this polity’s official language was French, though English became the official language in 1892 after a decisive vote by the Confederation Government in Ottawa. In 1999, this polity ceded land for the creation of its neighboring territory of Nunavut. For ten points, name this most-populous of the three Canadian federal territories, whose capital is Yellowknife.",
      "answer": "Northwest Territories"
    },
    {
      "question": "Jules Ferry blasted the 19th-century redesign of this city as “triumphant vulgarity,” while other critics noted that wider streets could be used in this city to more easily maneuver troops to counter uprisings. A series of glass and iron pavilions were built at this city’s central marketplace of Les Halles [[layz-ALL]]. Marc Chagall was hired to repaint the ceiling of a Charles Garnier-designed opera house in this city. Napoleon III hired Baron Haussman to renovate, for ten points, what city on the Seine River?",
      "answer": "Paris"
    },
    {
      "question": "Belief in this location may have been inspired by the healing of a paralyzed man at Bethesda, as recounted in the Gospel of John. The Arawak people believed this location to be in the mythical land of Bimini. One explorer, Juan de Solís, placed Bimini in the Gulf of Honduras, whereas the best known searcher of this location thought it to be in the Bahamas. For ten points, name this fabled body of water, for which Juan Ponce de León supposedly searched in Florida.",
      "answer": "Fountain of Youth"
    },
    {
      "question": "Nash Motors operated out of this city, where AMC also manufactured the Renault Alliance. Joseph Rosenbaum and Anthony Huber were killed in this city, while Gaige Grosskreutz was injured, leading to Dominick Black's arrest. A 17-year old from Antioch, Illinois, Kyle Rittenhouse, illegally used his rifle in this city. Officer Rusten Sheskey stopped an SUV in this city, then shot Jacob Blake seven times. For ten points, name this Wisconsin city, a center of racial unrest in the US in late 2020.",
      "answer": "Kenosha, Wisconsin 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 3"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thomas Chittenden was the first governor of this state, once known as The Republic of New Connecticut. At first, this state was governed from the town of Windsor, before its capital moved to its present location in 1805. This state was briefly an independent country from 1777 to 1791, and during the Revolutionary War, the Green Mountain Boys were considered part of the militia from this colony. For ten points, name this New England state, today led from Montpelier.",
      "answer": "Vermont"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1645, during this region’s Civil War, Françoise-Marie Jacquelin assumed command of the garrison at Fort la Tour while her husband, Governor Charles de Saint- Étienne de la Tour, was in Boston seeking support for their cause. The Wabanaki Confederacy maintained control of part of this region, northeast of the Kennebec River in Maine, during King Philip's War. For ten points, name this colony of New France which gives its name to a US National Park near Bar Harbor, Maine.",
      "answer": "Acadia"
    },
    {
      "question": "Chief Justice John Rutledge once served as governor of this state, where Patrick Ferguson was killed by Patriot militia at the Battle of Kings Mountain. Francis Marion, the “Swamp Fox,” led guerilla forces in this state. Horatio Gates was fired for losing the Battle of Camden in this state, though American forces later decisively defeated the British at the Battle of Cowpens. For ten points, name this Southern US state where the British captured the city of Charleston.",
      "answer": "South Carolina"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city was the site of the 1966 Compton's Cafeteria Riot, which involved members of the Vanguard organization. Bill Kraus and Cleve Jones were activists in this city's Castro District. This city's mayor, George Moscone, was assassinated by Dan White, whose lawyers used the \"Twinkie Defense.\" The White Night riots occurred in this city following the assassination of Harvey Milk. For ten points, name this California center of LGBTQ activism, situated on a namesake bay.",
      "answer": "San Francisco, California"
    },
    {
      "question": "The oldest of these structures still in use, located in A Coruña [[ah cor-OON-ya]], Spain, was built in the second century. An Oscar-nominated 2019 film directed by Robert Eggers is set in one of these places and stars Robert Pattinson and Willem Dafoe. The first of these built on the open ocean was built by Henry Winstanley at Eddystone Rocks. One of these buildings in Egypt was severely damaged by three earthquakes during the Middle Ages and was also known as the “Pharos.” For ten points, name these towers that aid ships in navigation.",
      "answer": "Lighthouses 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 5"
    },
    {
      "question": "A UN-supervised referendum led to this country’s formal independence in 1993, resulting in a nationalist one-party state. In 1994, then-US President Bill Clinton called this country’s president, Isaias Afwerki, “a renaissance African leader.” Reporters Without Borders rates this country lowest in the world on its Press Freedom Index, and until 2018 this country was at war with Ethiopia. For ten points, name this East African country, whose capital is Asmara.",
      "answer": "State of Eritrea"
    },
    {
      "question": "This remote territory was largely unaffected by the Protestant Reformation, although King Christian III established Lutheranism as the state religion. This country played host to the 1972 World Chess Championship between Boris Spassky and Bobby Fischer. This island nation, whose parliament is the oldest in the world, gained its independence from Denmark at the end of World War One. For ten points, what is this Nordic country, located just outside the Arctic Circle in the North Atlantic?",
      "answer": "Iceland"
    },
    {
      "question": "A rebellion on this island was led by the cacique [[kuh-SEE-kay]] Enriquillo [[en-ree- KEE-yo]] and began after his father and other leaders were killed by Nicolás de Ovando. The Spanish recognized French claims on this island through the Treaty of Ryswick. On this island, Christopher Columbus established the first European colony in the New World, La Navidad, though that colony was later destroyed by this island’s Taíno people. For ten points, name this island that is today shared by Haiti and the Dominican Republic.",
      "answer": "Hispaniola"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a Klickitat legend, this geographical feature was formed when the chief of the gods transformed the beautiful maiden Loowit into a mountain. The first Europeans to spot this mountain were sailors aboard the HMS Discovery, commanded by George Vancouver. The Grateful Dead played “Fire on the Mountain” at the Portland Memorial Coliseum as smoke poured from this nearby peak. For ten points, name this volcano in the Pacific Northwest, whose 1980 eruption killed 57 people.",
      "answer": "Mount St. Helens 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 1"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city hosted a 1992 UN convention on climate change. In 1864, Hamaguri rebels razed 28,000 houses in this city, resulting in a governmental reorganization, a decline of the local economy, and the construction of the Lake Biwa Canal. During World War Two, US Secretary of War Henry Stimson insisted that this city be removed from a list of bombing targets due to its cultural significance. For ten points, name this former imperial capital of Japan.",
      "answer": "Kyoto"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s boundaries, which are marked by stones placed a mile apart, were surveyed by a team including African-American Benjamin Banneker who was born in a county bordering this city. Andrew Ellicott revised the initial design for this city created by Pierre Charles L’Enfant. Legend has it that Dolley Madison rescued a portrait of this city’s namesake from an executive mansion before it was burned in the War of 1812. The White House can be found in, for ten points, what capital of the United States?",
      "answer": [
        "Washington, DC or District of Columbia,",
        "either Washington",
        "DC"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Only this island and the Faeroe Islands were in the band of totality of the total solar eclipse on March 20th, 2015. This island has no visa requirement and is officially designated a demilitarized zone by the Kingdom of Norway. Due to a lack of tectonic activity and extensive permafrost, the Norwegian government selected this island’s administrative center of Longyearbyen to host its Global Seed Vault. For ten points, name this Arctic island formerly known as Spitsbergen.",
      "answer": [
        "Svalbard",
        "Spitsbergen before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A \"monastery\" in this city contains inscriptions that refer to the cult of king Obodas I, who opposed the Hasmoneans. Johann Ludwig Burckhardt visited this city in 1812, believing it housed Aaron's Tomb. Local Bedouins supposedly tried to earn riches by shooting urns in this city's al-Khazneh, or Treasury, which is believed to be the mausoleum of Aretas IV. People entered this capital of the Nabateans through its narrow Siq entrance. For ten points, name this ancient rock-cut city in Jordan.",
      "answer": "Petra 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Finals"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler's armies forced the Truce of Ratisbon, which ceded Luxembourg to his country and concluded the War of the Reunions. This monarch survived the Fronde [[\"FROND\"]] Rebellion in his youth and employed the engineer Vauban [[VOH-BAHN]] to create star forts along his country's frontier. This king ordered his nobles to inhabit the massive Palace at Versailles. For ten points, name this \"Sun King\" of France, a long-lived absolutist monarch.",
      "answer": [
        "Louis XIV",
        "Louis the Great",
        "or Louis le Grand",
        "Louis, the Sun King",
        "Louis, le Roi Soleil before \"Sun King\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's skillful turning maneuvers resulted in a decisive victory at Kennesaw Mountain, which Liddell Hart cited in calling this man the first \"modern general.\" While leading the Division of the Mississippi, this man's Special Field Orders No. 15 resulted in the phrase \"forty acres and a mule.\" In the wake of the Battle of Atlanta, this man's forces undertook the \"March to the Sea\" to the Confederate port of Savannah. The \"scorched earth tactic\" was utilized by, for ten points, which Union general during the Civil War?",
      "answer": "William Tecumseh Sherman 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 1"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city was governed by a constitution known as the Great Rhetra, written by Lycurgus. Children in this city ate \"black soup\" and were forced into the Agoge [[ah-GOG- geh]] training system from the age of seven. Elected officials known as Ephors governed this city, which was ruled by two kings. Ritual killings of the Helot underclass occurred in, for ten points, what militaristic ancient city state which rivaled Athens?",
      "answer": [
        "Sparta",
        "Lacedaemon",
        "or Laconike 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 1"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The merger of the Sveno and the Bolshevik Workers Party into the Fatherland Front overthrew this nation's monarchy following a Soviet invasion. This European nation lost the Second Balkan War against its former allies of Serbia and Greece, losing territory in Macedonia and Thrace. Tsars such as Ferdinand I and Boris III led, for ten points, what member of the Axis governed from the city of Sofia?",
      "answer": [
        "Tsardom of Bulgaria or Tsarstvo Balgariya",
        "\"Kingdom\" in place of \"Tsardom\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "At Thalamae [[THAL-ah-mee]], a cult center dedicated to a queen of this island named Pasiphaë [[PASS-if-fee]] was a pilgrimage site for travelers seeking an oracle. A king of this realm named Deucalion [[doo-KAY-lee-on]] was slain by the departing Theseus outside the gates of Knossos [[kuh-NAH-sus]], which was a major site of a Bronze Age civilization on this island. The Minoans once ruled, for ten points, what Aegean Island?",
      "answer": "Crete or Kriti"
    },
    {
      "question": "Nominoe became the first king of this region after he and his local Vannetais tribe supported Louis the Pious in the fight against his sibling Lothair. A duchess of this region name Anne of Monfort commissioned the tapestry Hunt of the Unicorn to commemorate her marriage to Louis XII [[the twelfth]]. This region, known as Breizh [[BREHSH]] in its native Celtic tongue, was ruled by Henry II son's Geoffrey from the city of Rennes [[REN]].The Edict of Nantes was signed in, for ten points, what region of Northwestern France?",
      "answer": [
        "Brittany",
        "Breizh before mentioned",
        "Bretagne"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In the Neolithic period on this island, a group of standing stones likely meant to evoke fertility were rearranged by the Torrean [[toh-REH-ahn]] people at the Filitosa [[fee- lee-TOH-sah]] site. This island, which the launching point of the pro-De Gaulle Operation Resurrection, was ruled for nearly five hundred years by a republic in Liguria. The site of the Maison Bonaparte, the birthplace of Napoleon, for ten points, what is this French island department?",
      "answer": "Corsica or Corse 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 10"
    },
    {
      "question": "William Hogarth depicted a young merchant wasting his money in this city and eventually being placed in its Fleet Prison in A Rake's Progress. Waterloo Bridge and Charing Cross Bridge are included in Claude Monet's scenes from this city, which include a series on the Houses of Parliament. Canaletto painted The Thames and the City depicting, for ten points, which English capital city that contains the Tate Modern?",
      "answer": "London 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 3"
    },
    {
      "question": "Over 300 eunuchs and maids died in this city's Old Summer Palace following its intentional burning by the British under Lord Elgin. Prince Gong signed an 1860 treaty named for this city, ceding parts of Manchuria to Russia and leasing Kowloon to Britain. Following the Northern Expedition, central authority was moved south from this city to Nanjing. The Forbidden City is located in, for ten points, what modern capital of China?",
      "answer": [
        "Beijing or Beiping",
        "Peking"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Though Milton Obote [[oh-BOH-teh]] was restored to this country's presidency after a brief war with Tanzania, he did not restore its traditional kingdoms such as Ankole [[ahn- KOH-leh]]. Obote's predecessor proclaimed himself Conqueror of the British Empire and expelled this country's Asian population while declaring himself King of Scotland. During that dictator's rule, Israel rescued over 100 hostages from this country in Operation Entebbe [[en-TEH-beh]]. For ten points, name this country, once ruled by Idi Amin.",
      "answer": "Republic of Uganda 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 4"
    },
    {
      "question": "This \"people of the flint\" were the target of missionary efforts by Johannes Megapolensis [[yoh-HAH-ness meh-guh-poh-LEN-siss]] and earlier battled Hurons under the command of Samuel de Champlain. Due to claiming lands along a namesake river valley west of the Hudson River, this group was known as the Keepers of the Eastern Door. For ten points, name this member tribe of the Iroquois [[IH-roh-kwoy]] Confederacy, known in popular culture for an incorrectly attributed hairstyle in which the sides of the head are shaven.",
      "answer": [
        "Mohawks or Kanienʼkehá꞉ka",
        "Keepers of the Eastern Door before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In an effort to map this river in the 19th century, Breton explorer Auguste Pavie [[pah-VEE]] led a namesake mission with a convoy of elephants. During the first days of the Tet Offensive, the Vietcong attempted to seize all major towns in South Vietnam along this river. Cambodia, Laos, Thailand, and Vietnam formed a commission to maintain the natural integrity of, for ten points, what river of Southeast Asia?",
      "answer": [
        "Mekong River",
        "Mekong River Commission"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A contingent of this European people populated the Haitian city of Cazale [[kah- SAL]] after they betrayed Napoleon's troops. Over 20,000 officers and other intelligentsia of these people were murdered by the NKVD in the Katyn [[kah-TEEN]] Forest Massacre. With Hungarian Michael Kovats [[KOH-vach]], a nobleman of this nationality named Casimir Pulaski [[poo-WAH-skee]] reformed the American Cavalry Corps. For ten points, name these people who's country was invaded on September 1, 1939 to begin World War Two.",
      "answer": "Poles"
    },
    {
      "question": "Faina Vakhreva was the wife of the ruler of this island, whose adopted brother commanded a panzer division during the Anschluss of Austria. Before moving to this island, its leader created the \"Gannan New Deal,\" where civilians could talk to him at a \"public information desk.\" A ruler of this island arrested the \"Rommel of the East,\" Sun Li-jen, under conspiracy charges during the KMT's White Terror. For ten points, Chiang Ching Kuo and his father Chiang Kai Shek both controlled what East Asian island country?",
      "answer": [
        "Taiwan",
        "Republic of China",
        "or ROC"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A toxic pool labeled for this blight is shown in a political cartoon where men labelled \"Mr. Careless\" and \"Anti-Vaccinationist\" fall off a cliff titled \"Misinformation.\" During the Siege of Fort Pitt, Governor-General Jeffrey Amherst oversaw the gift of several blankets infected with this disease to opposing Native Americans. Edward Jenner inoculated people against, for ten points, what disease that was eradicated in the 1970s?",
      "answer": [
        "Smallpox",
        "Variola Major",
        "or Variola Minor"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The site of this city was purchased from the Mississauga by Lord Dorchester, though it remained unsettled until Governor John Graves Sicmoe established the town of York. John Strachan negotiated this town's surrender to the Americans in the War of 1812, after which it was the site of Government House on two occasions before it was moved to another location. William Lyons Mackenzie was the first mayor of this city until he abandoned it to lead the Upper Canada Rebellion. The Canadian National Railway built the CN Tower in, for ten points, which Ontario metropolis?",
      "answer": [
        "Toronto",
        "York before mentioned 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 6"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This country was governed by flight lieutenant Jerry Rawlings following a 1981 coup against the Convention People's Party. This country became the first colony in sub- Saharan Africa to achieve sovereignty under the regime of Kwame Nkrumah [[KWAH-meh en-KROO-muh]]. The only Black Secretary General of the United Nations, Kofi Annan [[KOH- fee ah-NAHN]], was originally from this country. The Ashanti once dominated, for ten points, what West African country ruled by Britain as the Gold Coast colony?",
      "answer": "Republic of Ghana"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Wadai Sultanate annexed a kingdom southeast of this body of water which was ruled by \"Mbang\" kings and was called Bagirmi. Ibn Furtu chronicled the military exploits of a Mai of an empire near this body of water named Idris Alooma. This lake shares its name with a country which with Libya fought the Toyota War over the Aouzu Strip. This lake in the Sahel has shrunk by 95% since 1960. For ten points, identify this lake that names a country governed from N’Djamena [[uhn-jah-MAY-nuh]].",
      "answer": "Lake Chad 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 7"
    },
    {
      "question": "A conflict in this region began in the Battle of the Bogside in 1969. The Sunningdale power-sharing agreement broke down after a general strike in this region, and a sectarian conflict in this region led to the fall of its parliament at Stormont. Protesters in this territory’s city of Derry were fired on by paratroopers in “Bloody Sunday.” For ten points, name this smallest constituent country of the United Kingdom in which the Troubles started in the late 1960s.",
      "answer": "Northern Ireland or Tuaisceart Éireann"
    },
    {
      "question": "Because Septimius Severus was born in Leptis Magna, a former colony of this city, he gave all of its people Roman citizenship at the end of the 2nd Century. Alexander the Great crucified 2,000 survivors in this city after he built an artificial causeway to subjugate its island portion. This city names a type of purple dye from the murex snail, most commonly associated with imperial power in antiquity. For ten points, name this Phoenician metropolis in modern-day Lebanon.",
      "answer": [
        "Tyre",
        "Tyros",
        "or Sur 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 9"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The short-lived Free State of Bottleneck was created in this region from a narrow gap in the Wisper Valley between Allied occupation zones. A brief \"Cis\" Republic in this region was a client state of Revolutionary France before being annexed. A pact recognizing this region's western borders was the principal portion of the Locarno Treaties in 1925. In direct violation of the Treaty of Versailles [[vehr-SYE]], Adolf Hitler ordered the remilitarization of, for ten points, what region in 1936?",
      "answer": "Rhineland"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city was the hub of the nahda cultural renaissance. Al-Fustat was absorbed into this city, where the Massacre at the Citadel was ordered by Muhammad Ali Pasha. In 969, this city became the Fatimids' capital, centuries before former slave soldiers called Mamelukes set up a sultanate here. For 10 points, name this pre-eminent city of Islamic Egypt which is the largest city by population in the Arab world today.",
        "answer": "Cairo, Egypt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A luxurious \"long-staple\" variant of what inedible crop has been grown in Egypt since Muhammad Ali Pasha's rule?",
        "answer": "cotton"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The \"flag-follower\" expeditions of miners departed from this city in the eighteenth century. The painting Independence or Death depicts events that took place in this city, which are also remembered at the Ipiranga (ee-pee-RON-guh) Monument. For 10 points, name this city where Pedro I declared the independence of Brazil, which is now the country's most populous.",
        "answer": "São Paulo"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which other Brazilian city has been the largest city entirely within the Amazon rain forest for decades, and hosted 2014 FIFA World Cup matches?",
        "answer": "Manaus NHBB B 2014-2015"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A state park named for these people contains the Pioneer Monument and the Emigrant Trail\nMuseum. This group of people suffered an early tragedy when John Snyder was murdered. This\ngroup's poor decision to attempt the Hastings Cutoff led to them being snowed in at Truckee\nLake. For 10 points, name these people who resorted to cannibalism in the 1840s.",
        "answer": [
          "Donner Party",
          "Donner"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Hastings Cutoff took the Donner Party south of what large body of water some\nmonths before they reached the Sierra Nevadas?",
        "answer": "Great Salt Lake"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was the destination of Operation Provide Relief and Operation Restore Hope. The U.S. intervened in this country following the fall of the Siad Barre (see-ODD bah-RAY) regime. A disastrous mission in this country's capital involved two Black Hawk helicopters being shot down. For 10 points, name this country where the U.S. fought the Battle of Mogadishu.",
        "answer": "Somalia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which two European countries colonized the territory that makes up present-day Somalia?",
        "answer": [
          "Italy and the United Kingdom",
          "England, Britain, UK,",
          "Great Britain too"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This territory controls the small Snake Island as well as the island of Vieques (vee-EY-case), which was the site of frequent protests prior to closing a naval training range in 2001. Activists from this territory attempted to assassinate Harry Truman in 1950. For 10 points, name this largest U.S. non-state commonwealth, found in the Caribbean.",
        "answer": "Puerto Rico"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which city in southern Puerto Rico shares its name with the first name of the explorer who searched for the Fountain of Youth in Florida?",
        "answer": "Ponce"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was where the Ogham script was invented and the Brehon laws were used. Thomas Cahill wrote a book about how this country’s people “saved civilization.” The Book of Kells was created in this country. According to legend, a saint drove the snakes off this island. For 10 points, name this island evangelized by St. Patrick.",
        "answer": "Ireland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "According to legend, what object did St. Patrick use to explain the trinity?",
        "answer": "clover"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, the Santa Fe was captured near King Edward Point. A year after losing this war, a military junta led by Jorge Videla lost power. A nuclear submarine sunk the General Belgrano during this war, which was sparked by the raising of a flag on South Georgia Island. For ten points, name this 1982 war won by the British over the Islas Malvinas, a small group of islands near Argentina.",
        "answer": "Falklands Islands War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Conservative British Prime Minister received a huge boost in popularity after winning the Falklands War.",
        "answer": "Margaret Thatcher"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country attempted to defend itself with the Metaxas Line, and this country’s seizure of Smyrna led to the War of Turkish Independence. Alexander Ypsilanti’s independence movement in this country was aided by a foreign fleet, which fought the Ottomans at the Battle of Navarino, and a painting by Eugene Delacroix depicts this country “Expiring on the Ruins of Missolonghi,” the same city where Lord Byron died fighting for this country. For ten points, name this country which won its independence from the Ottomans, and has its capital at Athens.",
        "answer": "Greece"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other Delacroix painting from the Greek War of Independence shows inhabitants of the title island being slaughtered or taken into slavery by Ottoman attackers.",
        "answer": "The Massacre at Chios"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The perioikoi were a class of freed people living in this city, and the mothakes were raised as citizens of this city. This city’s navy, led by Peisander, was destroyed at the Battle of Cnidus, part of the Corinthian War that this city fought alongside the Peloponnesian League. The Agiad and Eurypontid lines ruled this city, whose legendary founder and lawgiver was Lycurgus. For ten points, name this militaristic Greek city-state, the long-time rival to Athens.",
        "answer": [
          "Sparta",
          "Lacedaemon"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Sparta’s victory in the First Messanian War led to a large increase in the population of these people, subjugated slaves made to work for Spartans. They were killed at will during the crypteia.",
        "answer": "helots"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A coin struck in this city with a fleur de lis on one side and John the Baptist on the other became the most popular coin for transactions in Europe in the 14th century. The castato system was instituted in this city after a successful war against the Visconti of Milan, and this city was ruled by Piero the Unfortunate before being taken over by a Dominican friar in 1494. For ten points, name this Italian city, ruled for a brief time by Girolamo Savonarola and home to the Medici family.",
        "answer": "Florence"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Savonarola conducted one of these events on Mardi Gras in Florence to get rid of thousands of books, paintings, and cosmetics.",
        "answer": [
          "bonfire",
          "Bonfire of the Vanities"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country won the Battle of Hanko during a war where this country was led by Risto Ryi. Earlier this country was forced to give up the Karelian Isthmus that was protected by its unfinished Mannerheim line. This country fought the Continuation war with Nazi allies, but later turned on the Nazis in the Lapland war. For ten points, name this Scandinavian country that was invaded by the Soviets in the Winter War.",
        "answer": "Finland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Finnish Army indirectly participated in the 872 day Nazi siege of this city that is currently called Saint Petersburg.",
        "answer": "Leningrad"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Richard, the Earl of Cambridge, co-led the Southampton plot against this man. This man was wounded fighting Henry “Hotspur” Percy at the Battle of Shrewsbury, and this monarch, who signed the Treaty of Troyes during the Hundred Years War, led English forces to victory at the Battle of Agincourt. For ten points, name this Lancaster monarch who succeeded his father Henry IV, as king of England.",
        "answer": "Henry V"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Early in his youth Henry received military experience from fighting Owain Glyndwr, who was a prince of this region, whose current capital is Cardiff.",
        "answer": "Wales"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "P.G.T. Beauregard successfully repelled Union attacks on this state’s Bermuda Hundred. Joseph Hooker was forced to retreat from Banks’ Ford at the Battle of Chancellorsville in this state. This state’s secession from the Union was rewarded when the Confederacy moved its capital from Montgomery to this state. The final surrender of Robert E. Lee’s army of this state was conducted at Appomattox Court House in, for ten points, what Southern state with capital at Richmond?",
        "answer": "Virginia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This 1864 battle during the Siege of Petersburg near Richmond was a Confederate victory and is named for the result of a mine detonated by Ambrose Burnside.",
        "answer": "Battle of the Crater"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city’s Karakoy neighborhood is home to the Genoese-built Galata Tower. This city’s historic peninsula contains the Sarayburnu outcropping and lies south of the Golden Horn. The Marmaray Tunnel connects this city’s western and eastern halves. This city’s Topkapi Palace was built by Mehmed II, who also converted its Hagia Sophia into a mosque. For ten points, what city was known as Constantinople until it was conquered by the Ottoman Turks?",
        "answer": [
          "Istanbul",
          "Constantinople before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Istanbul lies on this strait connecting the Sea of Marmara to the Black Sea, making it an important historical stop for wheat shipments to the Mediterranean Sea.",
        "answer": "Bosporus or Bosphorus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A museum named for Tuol Sleng commemorates those who died at the hands of this party after it won a civil war against Lon Nol. This party called its state Democratic Kampuchea, and it created tens of thousands of mass graves in the Killing Fields. For ten points, name this communist movement led by Pol Pot which ruled Cambodia in the 1970s.",
        "answer": "Khmer Rouge"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Khmer Rouge lost power in Cambodia after a failed invasion of this neighbor country in 1978. This country’s village of Ba Chuc was the site of a Cambodian massacre in that invasion.",
        "answer": "Socialist Republic of Vietnam"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Willaq-Umu served as these peoples’ spiritual leader, and oracles venerated by these people included one at Pachacamac. Three “pachas” represented the three realms of deities in these peoples’ religion. Inti was the sun god of these people, and he was venerated at Cusco, the capital of these peoples’ empire. For ten points, name this South American people, conquered by Francisco Pizarro and centered on modern-day Peru.",
        "answer": "Incans"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Incan religion believed that Inti was born on this lake, which contains the Isla del Sol and the Isla de la Luna. This lake straddles the border between Peru and Bolivia and is the largest lake by volume in South America.",
        "answer": "Lake Titicaca"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At this city’s LEMD airport, Txeroki [”Cherokee”] used a van bomb to kill Carlos Palate. Another event in this city targeted four cercanias at its Atocha station and was wrongly blamed on the ETA by the outgoing Prime Minister, Jose Aznar, causing his party to lose his country’s general election. On March 11, 2004, Al-Qaeda bombed four trains in for ten points, what capital of Spain?",
        "answer": "Madrid"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The ETA terrorist group fights for the liberation of these people, who occupy an autonomous region in northern Spain.",
        "answer": "Basques"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man allowed volunteer troops from his country to fight against the Soviet Union as the Blue Division, despite maintaining official neutrality in World War II. The German Condor Legion assisted this leader of the Falange by bombing the Basque city of Guernica. This man defeated the Communist-backed Republicans in his country’s 1930’s civil war. For ten points, name this fascist dictator who led Spain from 1936 to 1975.",
        "answer": "Francisco Franco Bahamonde"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1969, Franco closed the border between Spain and this tiny peninsular territory to its south, which had been ceded to Great Britain in the Treaty of Utrecht.",
        "answer": "Gibraltar"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city’s most honored armed force was chosen by Gorgidas and included 150 pairs of men. Epaminondas led this city to victory at Leuctra, but was killed in victory at Mantinea. Twenty-seven years later, this city lost at the Battle of Chaeronea, where this army was defeated by Philip II of Macedon. For ten points, name this leader of the Boeotian Confederacy, a central Greek city legendarily founded by Cadmus.",
        "answer": "Thebes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This term names the elite force of 150 pairs of Theban soldiers. Plutarch’s account of this force notes that each pair of soldiers were lovers.",
        "answer": "Sacred Band"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One philosopher born in this nation was the lover of Alexander Berkman, the attempted assassin of Henry Clay Frick. The pamphlet “What Is To Be Done” supported the establishment of a “vanguard” to ferment revolution in this country. That pamphlet was written by an author from this country who traveled from Switzerland in a sealed boxcar and delivered the April Theses upon his return to Petrograd. For ten points, name this home country of Emma Goldman and Vladimir Lenin.",
        "answer": [
          "Russia",
          "USSR",
          "Soviet Union"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This assassin claimed inspiration from Emma Goldman to commit his most infamous deed; she was briefly arrested, then tried to prevent this man’s execution on October 29, 1901.",
        "answer": "Leon Czolgosz"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The zarzuela was invented in this country and named for its royal palace. In this country, Bach’s Chaconne was transcribed by Andres Segovia, a master of the classical guitar. Miles Davis’ Sketches of this country include a selection from Concierto de Aranjuez [con-thee-AIR-toe d’ar-ahn-WETH] by Joaquin [wah-KEEN] Rodrigo. For ten points, name this Iberian country where Isaac Alb´eniz wrote works like Cadiz, Granada, and Catalun˜a.",
        "answer": "Spain"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Flamenco music was developed in this Spanish region, an autonomous community where the Alhambra was built in Granada.",
        "answer": "Andalusia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Three brothers and a sister legendarily founded this city by two mountains and a river, and Hilarion was proclaimed as this city’s Metropolitan by one of its rulers, nicknamed “the Wise”. Nestor chronicled the history of this city in his Primary Chronicle, and this city was founded at the intersection of the Desna and the Dnieper Rivers. A Rurikid line that ruled this city was started by Vladimir the Great, whose son, Yaroslav the Wise, continued this city’s tradition of Christianity. For ten points, name this city, the medieval home of the Rus people and the modern capital of Ukraine.",
        "answer": [
          "Kiev",
          "Kievan Rus"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Prince Oleg moved the capital of the Rus from this city, his home, to Kiev. As Prince, Yaroslav the Wise briefly united Kiev with this city.",
        "answer": "Veliky Novgorod or Novgorod the Great"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Miguel Barbachano advocated for this state’s independence until a Caste War against Mayan forces, which included a sacking of its city of Valladolid [vay-yah-doh-leed]. Studies in the 1970s found shocked quartz in the northern area of this state, centered near the city of Chicxulub [chick-shu-lub] and dating to the K-Pg boundary. This Mexican state, with capital Merida, is the hypothesized site of the impact that killed the dinosaurs. For ten points, name this Mexican state on a namesake peninsula that juts into the Gulf of Mexico.",
        "answer": "Yucatan or Yucatan Peninsula"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This resort city on the northeastern tip of the Yucatan Peninsula, north of Playa del Carmen, remodeled its city grid after being significantly damaged by Hurricane Gilbert in 1988.",
        "answer": "Cancu´n"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was attacked by England and France during its Disaster Year, which resulted in the lynching of Cornelius and Jan de Witt. One general from this country emphasized combined arms to win the Battle of Nieuwpoort, although he avoided battle with the Duke of Parma during the 80 Years’ War. This home of Maurice of Nassau was formed from the 17 Provinces, and was led during its independence war by William the Silent. For ten points, name this country, which was ruled by the House of Orange from Amsterdam.",
        "answer": "The Netherlands"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "William the Silent was given this position, originally the representative of the Spanish king in the Netherlands. It evolved to essentially becoming the highest executive official in the Netherlands.",
        "answer": "Stadtholder"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this country, Ingrid Betancourt was kidnapped for over six years by the Revolutionary Armed Forces. The killing of Jorge Eliecer Gaitan sparked a ten-year civil war in this country known as La Violencia. Juan Manuel Santos currently leads this country, where possibly the richest criminal in history created a prolific cocaine cartel. Pablo Escobar operated in, for ten points, what South American country with capital Bogota?",
        "answer": "Colombia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Escobar’s cartel was based in this second largest Colombian city, where Escobar was killed in a firefight in 1993.",
        "answer": "Medellin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country memorializes the death of Syed Nazrul Islam on its Jail Killing day. This country’s first president, Sheikh Mujibur Rahman, created BAKSAL by merging the Krishak Sramik party with the Awami League. In 1971, Yahya Khan launched Operation Searchlight against leaders of what is now this country. Ravi Shankar and George Harrison held the world’s first benefit concert to support refugees from, for ten points, what country that borders India and Myanmar on the Bay of Bengal?",
        "answer": "Bangladesh"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Prior to its independence, Bangladesh was what province of a Muslim nation created by the Partition of India?",
        "answer": "East Pakistan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This nation’s economic ruin in the 1950s led to its genre of “scar” literature. One author from this country described his spiritual journey after learning of his survival from cancer. The protagonist of another novel set in this country was born with a jade piece in his mouth and is destined to marry his cousin despite his true love for another cousin. This country’s Four Great Classical Novels include the Romance of the Three Kingdoms and Water Margin. For ten points, name this country, the birthplace of Nobel laureates Gao Xingjian [sheeng-jee-ahn] and Mo Yan.",
        "answer": "People’s Republic of China"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This character’s 72 transformations and ability to jump 108,000 li with a single bound allow him to defend the monk Xuanzang on the Journey to the West. Depictions of this character as a monkey date to the Song Dynasty.",
        "answer": [
          "Sun Wukong",
          "either"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This virus’ env gene codes for the gp120 envelope glycoprotein. A disease caused by this virus was briefly, misleadingly called GRID. Using a molecular clock, scientists were able to trace back the origins of this virus to early twentieth century West Africa. This retrovirus infects and lowers the count of helper T cells. Infection by this virus took the lives of Freddie Mercury, Michel Foucault, and Rock Hudson during an explosive epidemic in the 1980s. For ten points, name this virus that causes AIDS.",
        "answer": "HIV or human immunodeficiency virus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A number of HIV and AIDS experts perished aboard this country’s national airline’s Flight 17 when it was shot down above Ukraine in 2014. Another of this country’s planes disappeared over the South China Sea in the same year.",
        "answer": [
          "Malaysia",
          "word forms",
          "Malaysian Airlines"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Massive protests in this country began after a speech in Qom during the 15 Khordad Movement. A series of land reforms and pro-Western measures led to further unrest, culminating in a massacre at Jaleh Square on Black Friday. The SAVAK secret police terrorized this nation and executed opponents of its ruler, Mohammed Reza Shah Pahlavi. For ten points, name this Middle Eastern country where a 1979 Islamic revolution was led by Ayatollah Khomeini and flooded the streets of Tehran.",
        "answer": "Islamic Republic of Iran"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Iranian Prime Minister Mohammed Mossadegh was overthrown in an operation backed by the CIA after he threatened to nationalize the assets of this oil company, which was responsible for the Deepwater Horizon spill.",
        "answer": "British Petroleum"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "When this man’s re-election hopes looked grim, he asked his cabinet to sign a pledge to end an ongoing war during his lame duck term. This man noted “Fondly do we hope, fervently do we pray, that this mighty scourge of war may speedily pass away” in his second inaugural address, having won a landslide re-election on the National Union ticket over George McClellan. For ten points, name this U.S. President who was assassinated a month into his second term by John Wilkes Booth in 1865.",
        "answer": "Abraham Lincoln"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Lincoln’s second inaugural address concludes with a foreshadowing of his leniency for the defeated Confederates; he calls on Americans to “bind up the nation’s wounds” with a pair of instructions for peaceful treatment. Give either instruction from Lincoln’s speech. ANSWER:”Withmalice toward none,withcharity for all”(accepteitherorbothunderlinedphrases) (3) This country was the last to approve the free trade agreement CETA, as Paul Magnette led an oppositiongroupinthiscountry’ssouth.ThiscountrywasthebirthplaceofSalahAbdeslam,anaccomplice of the November 2015 terrorist attack in Paris; four months later, Abdeslam was captured in this country. In March 2016, ISIS supporters bombed Maalbeek Metro Station and an airport in this country’s capital city. Prime Minister Charles Michel leads, for ten points, what country where French-speaking Walloons and Dutch-speaking Flemings meet in a Parliament in Brussels?",
        "answer": "Kingdom of Belgium BONUS: CETA is a free trade agreement between the European Union and this country. The TTIP is a proposed trade agreement between the EU and this country’s southern neighbor. ANSWER: Canada"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2015, this country’s president ended its transmigration program, which settled people from densely populated areas to sparsely populated islands. In September 2014, this was the last ASEAN country to ratify an agreement against haze pollution. In 2002, members of al-Qaeda killed over 200 people in nightclubs on this country’s island of Bali. Joko Widodo leads, for ten points, what Southeast Asian archipelagic country whose capital is Jakarta?",
        "answer": "Indonesia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The majority of the Bali Nightclub bombing fatalities were tourists from this country. In 2005, the Indonesian government charged the Bali Nine with smuggling heroin into Indonesia from this country, then controversially executed two of them in 2015.",
        "answer": "Australia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country lost a rubber-producing territory to its northern neighbor with the Treaty of Petropolis. This country’s highest point is the extinct volcano Nevado Sajama. This former owner of the State of Acre was the site of a Spanish colonial mint near the silver mines of Potosi, and it lost much of the Gran Chaco in a war with Paraguay. For ten points, name this “plurinational” country in South America that shares Lake Titicaca with Peru and whose two capitals are Sucre and La Paz.",
        "answer": "Plurinational State of Bolivia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bolivia lost its coastline, including the port city of Antofagasta, to Chile in what conflict, named for a body of water?",
        "answer": [
          "Pacific Ocean",
          "War of the Pacific"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This route was first conceived of in 1921 as a “project in regional planning” by Benton MacKaye. Its original route was completed near Mount Sugarloaf by the Civilian Conservation Corps in 1937, and the highest point of this route is Clingman’s Dome in the Great Smoky Mountains. This route runs over 2,000 miles from Springer Mountain in the south to Mount Katahdin in Maine. For ten points, name this long-distance hiking path from Georgia to Maine that follows a namesake mountain range.",
        "answer": "Appalachian National Scenic Trail"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The midpoint of the Appalachian Trail is usually considered to be this city, now in West Virginia. Its armory was raided by anti-slavery activists in 1859.",
        "answer": "Harpers Ferry"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country launched the Christmas Offensive in a war that began with a border skirmish at Wal Wal. One ruler of this country condemned the use of mustard gas in a speech at the League of Nations. The Derg overthrew a ruler of this country in a communist coup, and Italy annexed this African country prior to World War II. For ten points, name this country, once ruled by Menelik II and Haile [”highly”] Selassie, whose capital is Addis Ababa.",
        "answer": "Ethiopia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Menelik II and Haile Selassie both belonged to an Ethiopian dynasty named for this Biblical figure, due to his relationship with the Queen of Sheba. This man is credited with building the First Temple.",
        "answer": [
          "Solomon",
          "Solomonic Dynasty"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This mountain range was the target of Germany’s Operation Edelweiss in World War II, and its tallest peak was once known as Strobilus. The easternmost end of this mountain range is the Absheron Peninsula. Secessionist republics on the southern slope of this mountain range include Abkhazia and South Ossetia. Mount Elbrus is a part of, for ten points, what mountain chain that runs from the Black Sea to the Caspian Sea, shared by Azerbaijan, Georgia, and Russia?",
        "answer": "Caucasus Mountains"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This federal subject of Russia in the north Caucasus attempted to secede under the name of Ichkeria after the breakup of the USSR. It has its capital at Grozny.",
        "answer": "Chechnya or Chechen Republic"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A church in this city commemorates William Caxton with a stained glass window. According to legend, Brutus of Troy defeated giants with biblically inspired names, Gog and Magog, on the site of this city’s Guildhall. A namesake tower in this city once held two princes thought to be murdered by King Richard III. This city’s St. Paul’s Cathedral was rebuilt after a disaster in 1666. For ten points, name this city that was destroyed in a Great Fire, the capital of England.",
        "answer": "London"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This architect was responsible for much of the rebuilding following the Great Fire of London, including designing the new St. Paul’s Cathedral.",
        "answer": "Sir Christopher Wren"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this country, vassals pleged themselves to their lords through contracts called manrents. One leader of this kingdom lost the Battle of Falkirk after his schiltron formations proved useless against archers and joined with Andrew Moray to win the Battle of Stirling Bridge. Edward Longshanks executed this country’s national hero, William Wallace, in 1305 during its war for independence. For ten points, name this country that signed the 1706 Treaty of Union to join with its southern neighbor, England.",
        "answer": "Scotland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This king of Scotland defeated Edward II’s much larger army at the Battle of Bannockburn during the First War of Scottish Independence.",
        "answer": "Robert the Bruce or Robert I of Scotland"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city was ruled by a council of nine men called the Signoria, headed by a Gonfaloniere of Justice. In the Battle of Montaperti, Siena’s Ghibellines defeated this city’s Guelphs. Supporters of the Pope plotted the Pazzi Conspiracy to overthrow this city’s ruling family. Valuable objects were burned by a preacher from this city, Savonarola, during the Bonfire of the Vanities. This city’s rulers included Cosimo the Great, who used his banking wealth to sponsor artists like Donatello. For ten points, name this center of the Renaissance, an Italian city ruled by the Medici.",
        "answer": "Florence"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Florentine ruler, known as “the Magnificent,” survived the Pazzi Conspiracy and invited Savonarola to Florence.",
        "answer": "Lorenzo de’Medici or Lorenzo the Magnificent"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A former hotel in this state, the Royal Poinciana, was once the largest wooden building in the world. A city in this state became the largest by area in the contiguous USA when it consolidated with Duval County in 1968. A railroad along this state’s eastern coast was developed by Henry Flagler; that railway’s southernmost portion is now the Overseas Highway to Key West. For ten points, name this southern state, home to Jacksonville and Miami.",
        "answer": "Florida"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other Florida city, established by Spanish settlers in 1565, is the oldest continuously- occupied European settlement in the continental US.",
        "answer": "St. Augustine"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This kingdom’s first ruler was recognized by the papal bull Manifestis Probatum. This country is part of the oldest alliance still in effect, as it allied with England in 1373. A noble from this country created a school in Sagres and was head of the Order of Christ. It was ruled by the House of Braganza, and Henry the Navigator was part of its House of Aviz. For ten points, name this country that sponsored the first expeditions to India, which brought spices to its capital of Lisbon.",
        "answer": "Kingdom of Portugal"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Order of Christ in Portugal grew out of the remnants of this crusading order. Clement V disbanded this order after Philip IV nearly destroyed it, and it feuded with the Knights Hospitaller.",
        "answer": "Knights Templar"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The largest city in this region hosts a yearly ice sculpture festival and was once home to the Jurchens. The “outer” portion of this region, beyond the Amur and Ussuri Rivers, was ceded to Russia in a pair of Unequal Treaties. Harbin is the largest city of this region, where the Mukden Incident was used by Japan to establish the puppet state of Manchukuo. The Qing Dynasty was founded by people from, for ten points, what region in the northeast of China?",
        "answer": [
          "Manchuria",
          "Manchukuo after “Mukden” is said and before it itself is mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This river, the site of the largest naval battle in the First Sino-Japanese War, is Manchu for “the boundary between two countries” and marks the northern border of North Korea.",
        "answer": "Yalu River"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After it was revealed that this country’s former president gave money to Paul Manafort, Manafort was dismissed as manager of the Trump presidential campaign. This country’s president is known as the “Chocolate King” since he controls the chocolate manufacturing group Roshen. The Minsk II agreement was signed in an attempt to de-escalate the war in the Donbass Region of this country. The Euromaidan protests led to the ousting of this country’s president, Viktor Yanukovych. For ten points, name this country led by Petro Poroshenko whose Crimean Peninsula was annexed by Russia in 2014.",
        "answer": "Ukraine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The two separatist groups in eastern Ukraine are based around the Donetsk Oblast and this city’s oblast. The Merheleva Ridge is a prehistoric burial complex found in 2006 in its namesake oblast.",
        "answer": "Luhansk or Lugansk"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was targeted by the Aberdeen Act, which authorized the Royal Navy to board its ships. A period of regency in this country led to a series of independence revolts, such as the Ragamuffin War. During the Peninsular War, Prince Regent Joao moved his monarchy to this country. It fought the Platine War against Argentina and was part of the Triple Alliance that defeated Paraguay. For ten points, name this country that gained its independence from Portugal after the Treaty of Rio de Janeiro.",
        "answer": "Empire of Brazil"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Brazil abolished slavery with the passage of this 1888 law, thus becoming the last Western country to do so.",
        "answer": "Golden Law or Lei A´urea"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was the site of the 1909 Goudi coup, which forced its King George I to bring in a reformist prime minister. The London Conference of 1832 established this country and made the Bavarian prince Otto its king. This country and Serbia fought Bulgaria over the occupation of Macedonia in the Second Balkan War. Andreas and Georgios Papandreou served as Prime Minister of, for ten points, what country that, in 1896, hosted the first modern Summer Olympics in Athens?",
        "answer": "Kingdom of Greece"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man was born as a prince of Greece and Denmark. He is now the royal consort of another country, having served in its Royal Navy during World War II.",
        "answer": [
          "Prince Philip, Duke of Edinburgh",
          "either portion"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Projects along this river include the Elephant Butte and Amistad Dams. The mouth of this river was once home to the port of Bagdad, which was heavily used by the Confederacy. A swing bridge spanning this river connects the cities of Matomoros and Brownsville, and it was claimed as the southern border of a republic that gained its independence after the Battle of San Jacinto. For ten points, name this river that serves as the boundary between Mexico and the State of Texas.",
        "answer": "Rio Grande"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the Texas Revolution, Mexico claimed that this other river, not the Rio Grande, was the southern border of Texas.",
        "answer": "Nueces River"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This river became the site of Fort Brown after a military buildup by Zachary Taylor, whose men were ambushed near this river in the Thornton Affair. A dispute over the deaths of federal troops during the “Spot Resolutions” was prompted by the United States’ use of this river, not the Nueces, as a southern boundary; that territorial dispute prompted President Polk to begin the Mexican-American War. For ten points, name this river that forms the south Texan border.",
        "answer": "Rio Grande or Rio Bravo del Norte"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Far from what is now the US-Mexico border, Texas attempted to expand east of the Rio Grande to capture what lucrative trail that connected Independence, Missouri with the capital city of New Mexico?",
        "answer": "Santa Fe Trail"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was wounded and captured at the Battle of Aspromonte, after which he retired to Caprera. During the Franco-Prussian War, this general led the Army of the Vosges. After a handshake at Teano, this leader declared his loyalty to King Victor Emanuel II. This ex-member of the Carbonari led his redshirts on the Expedition of the Thousand to conquer the Kingdom of Two Sicilies. For ten points, name this general who led the military campaigns that unified Italy.",
        "answer": "Giuseppe Garibaldi"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After fleeing a death sentence, Garibaldi joined the Colorados during the Ragamuffin War to liberate this country, then known as Rio Grande do Sul. Garibaldi made his home in this country’s capital, Montevideo.",
        "answer": "Oriental Republic of Uruguay"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Architecture students at this university annually build a dragon and parade it through campus, though the dragon is no longer set ablaze. The namesake founder of this university founded the telegraph company Western Union. This private land grant university is located near Cayuga Lake, which is the longest of its state’s Finger Lakes. This school was founded 96 years after Dartmouth, making it the youngest Ivy League school. For ten points, name this prestigious university in Ithaca, New York.",
        "answer": "Cornell University"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This astronomer served as a professor at Cornell for almost three decades, during which time he compiled the Voyager Golden Record and wrote the book Cosmos.",
        "answer": "Carl Sagan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This history of this disease was examined by Randy Shilts in his book And The Band Played On. Teenager Ryan White’s expulsion from school after contracting this disease inspired a 1990 law providing healthcare funding to people living with this disease. Critics of the Reagan administration have blamed homophobic policy makers for ignoring the crisis of, for ten points, what disease that is caused by the HIV virus?",
        "answer": "Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome or HIV/AIDS"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ryan White was from this state, which suffered its largest AIDS outbreak in 2015. Mike Pence, while serving as this state’s governor, reluctantly backed some needle exchange programs in an attempt to stop the outbreak.",
        "answer": "Indiana"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man rented the Kennedy Farm in Maryland under the alias of Isaac Smith. Forces under this man defeated a contingent under Henry Pate in the Battle of Black Jack and killed several members of the Doyle family in the Pottawatomie Massacre. This man cut off telegraph cables and railroad lines as part of his raid on a Virginia arsenal. For ten points, name this abolitionist who was executed in 1859 for leading a raid on Harpers Ferry.",
        "answer": "John Brown"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The 1856 Pottawatomie massacre left five people dead in this territory, which Horace Greeley described as “Bleeding” during the violent debate over whether it would enter the Union as a free or slave state.",
        "answer": [
          "Kansas Territory",
          "Bleeding Kansas"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An 1864 raid on this city failed to relieve prisoners at Irving Block Prison. One of this city’s parks was hastily renamed Health Sciences Park in 2013; that park was the site of a Charles Niehaus equestrian statue overlooking a pair of graves. In December 2017, to avoid a state law banning war memorial changes on public property, this city sold two of its parks to a non-profit that then took down the aforementioned Confederate memorial and a statue of Jefferson Davis. Jim Strickland is the mayor of, for ten points, what Tennessee city on the Mississippi River?",
        "answer": "Memphis"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Prior to the 2013 signing of the aforementioned Tennessee law, Health Sciences Park was named for this Civil War general and early leader of the KKK, a Memphis native whose equestrian statue was removed from the park.",
        "answer": "Nathan Bedford Forrest"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country’s Keroman peninsula is the site of three submarine pens, two of which required subs to be taken out of the water completely. The success of Operation Cobra in this country led to the creation of the Falaise Pocket. Canadian soldiers launched the failed Dieppe Raid into this country, where hedgerows later hindered tanks during attempts to take Caen. For ten points, name this country, the site of the Normandy landings during World War II.",
        "answer": [
          "France",
          "Vichy France"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ground troops during the Normandy campaign were under the command of this British general, who had earlier defeated Rommel in the North African campaign.",
        "answer": "Bernard Montgomery"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This site includes the Torreon tower, which was once used as an observatory, and a Popular District where commoners lived. The Huatana stone and the Room of the Three Windows at this site were dedicated to a sun god, Inti. This site is situated above the Urubamba River and was constructed as an estate for Pachacuti. Hiram Bingham studied, for ten points, what “lost city of the Incas?”",
        "answer": "Machu Picchu"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hiram Bingham’s excavation of Machu Picchu was supported by this Ivy League university, where Bingham lectured.",
        "answer": "Yale University"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Hedonistic white settlers settled this country’s Happy Valley. This country subsidized possibly non-existent gold in the Goldenberg Scandal. This country’s Kalenjin people came to power under Daniel Arap Moi, who discriminated against its Kikuyu ethnic group. This country’s Westgate shopping mall was attacked in 2013 by Al-Shabaab, a terrorist group based in neighboring Somalia. For ten points, name this east African country led by Uhuru Kenyatta.",
        "answer": "Kenya"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Dedan Kimathi led the Kikuyu people in this 1950s uprising against British colonial power in Kenya.",
        "answer": "Mau Mau Rebellion"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Demilitarization along this border was planned by the Rush-Bagot Treaty. Confusion over this border led to a bloodless war after a pig was shot on San Juan Island. Lumberjack infighting along this border led to the Aroostook War, which was ended by a treaty negotiated by Daniel Webster. This border was initially demarcated by the 1783 Treaty of Paris following the American Revolution. For ten points, name this border whose eastern end lies between Maine and New Brunswick.",
        "answer": [
          "the border between Canada and the United States of America",
          "USA",
          "America for United States"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned Aroostook War was ended by a treaty signed by, and named for, Daniel Webster and this British baron.",
        "answer": "Alexander Baring, 1st Baron Ashburton"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was divided into a grid by Raoul Salan’s quadrillage system during its war of independence. The Oran Massacre began in this country on its independence day, and was used as justification by Jean Bastien-Thiry to attempt the assassination of Charles de Gaulle. Ahmed Ben Bella led the FLN in this country, which signed the Evian Accords to gain independence. For ten points, name this former French colony in North Africa.",
        "answer": "Algeria"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This term, from the French for “black foot,” was used to describe Algerians of European descent, most of whom emigrated back to Europe after Algerian independence.",
        "answer": "pied-noirs"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country’s city of List is one of four “compass communities” that host Unity Day celebrations to symbolize this country’s modern borders. Brocken Peak in this country’s Harz Mountains is said to be the site of witches’ meetings on Walpurgisnacht. An annual festival in the Theresienwiese celebrates this country’s consumption of bratwurst and beer. For ten points, name this country where Oktoberfest celebrations are the world’s largest annual festival.",
        "answer": "Federal Republic of Germany"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "All beer served at Oktoberfest must adhere to the standards set in this 1516 Bavarian law, which dictates that the only ingredients used in beer brewing are water, barley, and hops.",
        "answer": [
          "Reinheitsgebot",
          "German Beer Purity Law"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This speech calls for an “insurance-in” and a “bank-in” to strengthen black financial institutions, shortly after calling for boycotts of Wonder Bread and Coca-Cola. This speech opens with praise for “the best friend that I have in the world,” Ralph Abernathy, and ends with an ultimately foreboding note that “[he’s] seen the Promised Land,” though he “may not get there with you.” For ten points, name this April 3, 1968 speech, delivered in Memphis by Martin Luther King, Jr. the day before his assassination.",
        "answer": "I’ve Been to the Mountaintop"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The “I’ve Been to the Mountaintop” speech was given in response to a strike of these workers in Memphis.",
        "answer": [
          "sanitation workers",
          "equivalents related to garbage collection, waste collection, etc."
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this region, the nymph Arethusa surfaced from beneath the sea into a freshwater spring. This region’s city of Kamikos was ruled by the legendary Cocalus, who sheltered Daedalus after Daedalus fled from Crete. Most accounts hold that either Tartarus or this region was the final resting place of Typhon after he was vanquished by Zeus; both Typhon’s burial and the forge of Vulcan in this region were held to cause the volcanic tremors around Mount Etna. For ten points, name this island where Arethusa’s spring was found in Syracuse.",
        "answer": "Sicily"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "According to an ancient anecdote, this courtier to Dionysus II of Syracuse begged to switch places with his ruler for a day, but he quickly asked for his old position back when he realized the dangers of being in power.",
        "answer": [
          "Damocles",
          "Sword of Damocles"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This location’s fall was allegedly watched by celebrating drinkers gathered on “the battery.” Inhabitants of this location under Robert Anderson were starved out by guns placed in the nearby military college, the Citadel. Sullivan’s Island, the site of nearby Fort Moultrie, was abandoned in favor of this location, which the Star of the West failed to re-supply in Charleston Harbor. For ten points, name this South Carolina fort that Confederates seized at the start of the Civil War.",
        "answer": "Fort Sumter"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Fort Sumter lies just off the western tip of this island at the opening to Charleston Harbor. This island, which is cut off from downtown Charleston by the Ashley River, was the site of the last armed action of the Revolutionary War in 1782.",
        "answer": "James Island"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Greer County eventually was ruled to be part of this state after a dispute over the Adams-Onis Treaty with its southern neighbor. This state was assigned the Cimarron Territory in 1890 but was considered No Man’s Land beforehand. The Unassigned Areas in this state were allocated by an 1889 land rush in which the “Sooners” rushed across the border. For ten points, name this US state who has had several territorial disputes with its southern neighbor, Texas.",
        "answer": "Oklahoma"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Cimarron Territory became Oklahoma’s Cimarron, Texas, and Beaver counties, forming this region in northwest Oklahoma that is exactly half a degree of latitude wide.",
        "answer": "Oklahoma Panhandle"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man declared that “love to my country actuates... my conduct, however it may appear inconsistent” in defending himself in a letter addressed “To the Inhabitants of America.” This man was forced to flee on the Vulture after his associate, John Andre, was captured. For ten points, name this traitorous Continental Army general who attempted to turn West Point over to the British.",
        "answer": "Benedict Arnold"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Arnold helped sabotage West Point by weakening its defenses, including by failing to maintain a protective chain that spanned this river, on which West Point is located.",
        "answer": "Hudson River"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Elections in this country were held after the June Struggle led to the establishment of the Sixth Republic. A student uprising in 1960 led to the overthrow of this country’s first ruler, Syngman Rhee. This country signed an armistice at Panmunjom, establishing its northern border as a demilitarized zone at the 38th parallel. For ten points, name this country bordered to the north by a dictatorship ruled by the Kim family.",
        "answer": [
          "South Korea or the Republic of Korea",
          "ROK"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This first female President of South Korea was impeached in 2016 on corruption charges.",
        "answer": "Park Geun-hye"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This field of study was founded during the Dartmouth Conference. The failure of initiatives like Japan’s fifth generation project was due to financial setbacks in this field during its namesake “winters.” John Searle dissented against the main argument of a paper in this field beginning “Can Machines Think?” The Turing Test uses questions to discern between the cognitive abilities of humans and computers in, for ten points, what area of computer science?",
        "answer": "artificial intelligence or AI"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "John Searle’s 1980 paper about the Chinese Room Argument divided artificial intelligence into these two types, named for a machine’s ability to perform general and specific actions.",
        "answer": "strong and weak AI"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event’s leader stumbled upon Pompey’s Pillar, where his etched signature remains to this day. Fort Mandan was constructed by participants of this event, who included a slave named York. After setting out from St. Louis, this event’s leaders were joined by Toussaint Charbonneau and his Shoshone wife, Sacagawea. For ten points, name this early 19th century expedition that Thomas Jefferson deployed to scout the Louisiana territory.",
        "answer": [
          "Lewis and Clark Expedition",
          "Corps of Discovery"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Much of the expedition took place along this river, which flows from Montana to the Mississippi River near St. Louis.",
        "answer": "Missouri River"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After this city fell to France, Napoleon ordered the destruction of the Bucentaur, a ship that was used by this city’s leader each Ascension Day to perform the “Marriage of the Sea” ceremony. This city maintained the fortress city of Famagusta on its island colony of Cyprus. A maritime empire in the Adriatic was ruled by, for ten points, what Italian city-state that is famed for its canals?",
        "answer": "The Most Serene Republic of Venice"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the original tradition of the Marriage of the Sea ceremony, the holder of this position dropped a ring into the water. The name of this position is related to the English term “duke.”",
        "answer": "Doge of Venice"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Alberto Granado and this man were given a raft to sail on the Amazon River after treating lepers. This man supported Jacobo Arbenz, but when his wife Hilda Gadea was arrested, he moved to Mexico. This man journeyed for nine months on a motorcycle across South America. This revolutionary fought in a revolution that deposed Fulgencio Batista after sailing on the Granma. For ten points, name this Argentine Marxist revolutionary who helped Fidel Castro in Cuba.",
        "answer": "Ernesto “Che” Guevara"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Che supported Jacobo Arbenz in this Central American country. Like Panama City and Mexico City, this country’s capital city shares the name of the country.",
        "answer": "Guatemala City"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This location was transferred to the Pitjantjatjara in exchange for a ninety-nine year lease. This location shares a national park with Mount Olga, which is part of the Kata Tjuta formations. This feature is notably never climbed by the Anangu, who believe that it is the site of a Dreamtime trail. In 1873, William Gosse named this feature in honor of Chief Secretary Henry Ayers. For ten points, name this sandstone formation sacred to Australian Aborigines.",
        "answer": [
          "Uluru",
          "Ayers Rock before “Ayers” is mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Uluru is found in the southwestern region of this Australian territory, whose capital city was bombed in 1942 by the Japanese.",
        "answer": "Northern Territory"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A kingdom once located on this island drove out Dutch foreigners in the Siege of Fort Zeelandia. This island, where the Kingdom of Tungning ruled, suffered a forty-year period of martial law called the White Terror. This island was ceded to Japan in 1895 per the Treaty of Shimonoseki, and Chiang Kai-shek fled to this island after his defeat in the Chinese Civil War. For ten points, name this island controlled by the Republic of China, whose capital is Taipei.",
        "answer": [
          "Taiwan",
          "Republic of China",
          "ROC before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After fleeing to Taiwan, Chiang Kai-shek continued the rule of this political party.",
        "answer": [
          "Kuomintang or KMT",
          "Nationalist Party of China"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle’s result was investigated by the Catroux Commission, which reported that its greatest effect was upon public morale. Charles Piroth committed suicide after discovering he could do no more in this battle, whose sides fought to control hills codenamed Beatrice and Gabrielle. During this battle, artillery pieces placed in the mountains were used by great effect by Vo Nguyen Giap, who had surrounded his European enemy. For ten points, name this 1954 battle that led France to withdraw from Vietnam.",
        "answer": "Battle of Dien Bien Phu"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The result at Dien Bien Phu significantly altered the proceedings at a 1954 conference held in this Swiss city. A set of Conventions signed in this city discuss the rights of civilians and prisoners of war.",
        "answer": "Geneva Conference and/or Conventions"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "George Barnard collected a set of 61 prints in his Photographic Views of this campaign. A telegram in which a president said “go as you propose” gave its leader permission to carry out this campaign, during which Orlando Poe was tasked with dismantling bridges. Special Field Orders Number 15 was issued after this campaign concluded with the capture of thousands of bales of cotton and a crucial port city. An estimated $100 million dollars in damage was caused by, for ten points, what campaign through Georgia led by William Tecumseh Sherman?",
        "answer": [
          "Sherman’s March to the Sea",
          "Savannah Campaign"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the March to the Sea, Sherman ordered scorched earth tactics like foraging, as well as destroying these specific items, which then became known as “Sherman’s neckties.”",
        "answer": "rails"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Ingvar Kamprad, the founder of IKEA, drew controversy by moving his production facilities to this country. This country liberalized under the leadership of Wladyslaw Gomulka [vlad-ee-slav go-moo-ka]. The wave of protests that eventually overthrew this country’s Communist government began at the Lenin Shipyard. For ten points, name this Eastern European country where Lech Walesa [lek vah-wen-sah] led the Solidarity movement.",
        "answer": "Poland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Lenin Shipyard is found in, and now named for, this Polish city on the coast of the Baltic Sea.",
        "answer": "Gdansk or Danzig"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A particularly hazardous season in this region in 1988 is sometimes referred to as the “Summer of Fire.” The establishment of the Lamar Buffalo Ranch in this region helped boost its population of bison. The “capture and destruction [of wildlife] for the purposes of merchandise or profit” were banned in an 1872 act that made this region the first of its type. For ten points, name this national park containing Old Faithful, the first national park in the US.",
        "answer": "Yellowstone National Park"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Much of Yellowstone’s roads, trails, and facilities were built or repaired by workers with this New Deal agency, which employed young men in manual labor on governmental land to maintain America’s natural resources.",
        "answer": "Civilian Conservation Corps or CCC"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader embarked on a political purge in a “Corrective Revolution,” and he liberalized his country’s economy through his policy of intifah. With Hafez al-Assad, this leader launched Operation Badr against a neighboring country. This politician was assassinated in 1981 by radical forces inside his country, largely because he had signed the Camp David Accords three years earlier. For ten points, name this man who succeeded Gamal Abdel Nasser as President of Egypt.",
        "answer": "Muhammad Anwar el-Sadat"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Anwar Sadat shared the Nobel Peace Prize for signing the Camp David Accords with this prime minister of Israel, who later invaded Lebanon in 1982 in an attempt to combat the PLO.",
        "answer": "Menachem Begin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Soldiers from this former nation plotted to assassinate a losing candidate in Operation Quartz, but his victory meant the operation wasn’t necessary. Abel Muzorewa briefly led a successor state to this entity, and the Lancaster House Agreement ended a longstanding conflict in this country. Forces loyal to this country fought ZANU and ZAPU guerrillas in a civil war known as its namesake “Bush War.” Robert Mugabe gained power after the 1979 dissolution of, for ten points, what former African country now known as Zimbabwe?",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of Rhodesia",
          "Colony of Southern Rhodesia"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This racist Prime Minister of Rhodesia signed the Internal Settlement with Abel Muzorewa in 1978 and was one of the signatories of the Lancaster House Agreement.",
        "answer": "Ian Smith"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the 1500s, this city’s House of Trade handled a 20 percent tax on all precious metals passing into its country. Christopher Columbus is buried underneath a cathedral in this city, which is located on the Guadalquivir River. Legends claim that Heracles founded this inland city and a nearby port city as he passed through the Strait of Gibraltar. Twelve years after the fall of Cordoba, this city was captured by Ferdinand III of Castile in 1248. For ten points, name this largest city in Andalusia.",
        "answer": [
          "Seville",
          "Sevilla"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Seville lost its economic importance in the late 16th century to this port city on the mouth of the Guadalquivir River, which empties into a gulf named for this city.",
        "answer": "Gulf of Cadiz"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was the adopted home of Hugh Cholmondeley [chum-lee], the man who first coined the term “white hunter” for safari hunting westerners; he belonged to this country’s scandalous white Happy Valley Set. A dispute over this country’s north caused the Shifta War. Dedan Kimathi was killed in this country while leading a rebellion that led to the jailing of the Kapenguria Six. The Mau Mau Rebellion occurred in, for ten points, what country first led by Jomo Kenyatta?",
        "answer": "Kenya"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Dedan Kimathi was a member of this ethnic group, the largest in Kenya. Members of this group, as well as the Meru, Maasai, and Embu peoples, joined together in the Mau Mau Rebellion.",
        "answer": "Kikuyu people or Gikuyu"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city was briefly ruled by the Thirty Tyrants, a client government of their rival. Citizens of this city could vote to expel others by depositing pottery shards in urns, a process known as ostracism that was used against statesmen like Themistocles. During this city’s Golden Age under Pericles, the Parthenon was built. For ten points, name this “birthplace of democracy,” a powerful city-state of ancient Greece.",
        "answer": "Athens"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Themistocles persuaded the Athenians to create a “wooden wall” by improving this military force with the construction of dozens of triremes, which were later used at the Battle of Salamis.",
        "answer": "Athenian navy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country’s independence fighters included the La Trinitaria society, led by Juan Pablo Duarte. A leader of this country ordered his secret police, the SIM, to murder three of the Mirabal sisters. Many citizens of a neighboring country were murdered by this country’s troops for their pronunciation of the word “perejil” [per-eh-HEEL] in the 1937 Parsley Massacre. For ten points, name this Caribbean country where a dictator known as “El Jefe” [hay-fay] attacked the people of its neighbor, Haiti.",
        "answer": [
          "Dominican Republic",
          "D.R.",
          "Republica Dominicana"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This dictator, known as “El Jefe,” ruled the Dominican Republic for over three decades. The Mirabal sisters were activists against this ruler, who ordered the Parsley Massacre.",
        "answer": "Rafael Trujillo"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This speech warns dictators that “those who foolishly sought power by riding the back of the tiger ended up inside.” Ted Sorensen helped draft this speech, whose speaker notes that America “shall pay any price [...] to assure the survival and success of liberty.” The challenge to “ask not what your country can do for you; ask what you can do for your country” was delivered in, for ten points, what January 1961 address?",
        "answer": "John Fitzgerald Kennedy’s inaugural address"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Kennedy’s inaugural ceremonies were the first in which a poet took part; this New Englander recited “The Gift Outright” from memory after sunlight prevented him from reading his intended text.",
        "answer": "Robert Frost"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A diplomat from this country became known as “Mr. No” because of his frequent vetoes in the United Nations. Another diplomat from this country promulgated the “Sinatra Doctrine” that encouraged countries to settle their own internal affairs. This country invaded Afghanistan in accordance with its Brezhnev Doctrine. Eduard Shevardnadze represented Georgia within, for ten points, what country that led the Warsaw Pact in opposition to NATO during the Cold War?",
        "answer": [
          "Soviet Union",
          "USSR",
          "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
          "CCCP",
          "Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Brezhnev Doctrine was first described in an article in this Soviet newspaper, whose name means “Truth.”",
        "answer": "Pravda"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Robert Livingston and Peter Schuyler [sky-ler] led a convention in this city to oppose Leisler’s Rebellion. Another organization in this city grew out of the Bucktails and lost power after governor William Marcy was defeated in 1838 by William Seward. Thurlow Weed coined the name of that organization led by Martin Van Buren, this city’s “Regency.” The “Join or Die” cartoon was produced at a 1754 meeting in this city that discussed the early goings of the French and Indian War. A 1754 “Congress” met in, for ten points, what capital city of New York?",
        "answer": "Albany"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another member of Albany’s Schuyler family, Philip, was one of the first senators from New York until he was defeated in a 1791 election by this man, who later killed his son-in-law in a duel in Weehawken, New Jersey.",
        "answer": "Aaron Burr"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These people left artifacts behind in the Ukraine’s largest burial mound, the “Black Grave.” These people allegedly executed their enemies with the “blood eagle” method and were employed by the Byzantine Empire as the Varangian Guard. These people sacked Lindisfarne and sailed up the Seine River in longships to attack Paris in 845. The colony of Vinland was founded by, for ten points, what seafaring marauders from Scandinavia?",
        "answer": "Vikings"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The 793 Viking raid on the island of Lindisfarne destroyed one of these facilities, which was founded by Aidan in 634.",
        "answer": [
          "monastery",
          "priory",
          "abbey",
          "church"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An inscription found at Jarrow claims that this structure’s namesake built it due to “divine instruction.” The Stanegate was a road that followed a similar path to this structure, which contains a ditch once named after Agricola. Along the North Sea, this structure terminates at Solway Firth. This 73 mile long structure was intended to keep the Picts and other Celtic groups out of Roman territory. A cousin of Trajan names, for ten points, what wall in northern England?",
        "answer": [
          "Hadrian’s Wall",
          "Vallum Aelium"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Antonine Wall was built 100 miles north of Hadrian’s Wall, but it was abandoned by this last of the Five Good Emperors in 164 AD.",
        "answer": "Marcus Aurelius Antoninus Augustus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A decade of turmoil in this country was ushered in with the July Apostasy by king Constantine II. After several weak civilian governments, the Regime of the Colonels took over and ruled this country from 1967 to 1974; when civilian rule was restored, PASOK and New Democracy dominated this country’s politics until the rise of Syriza in the wake of the debt crisis of the early 2010s. For ten points, name this country where Alexis Tsipras was replaced as Prime Minister in 2019.",
        "answer": "Greece"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The rule of the colonels was ended by the failure of enosis, a Greek word meaning “union” that described the goal of uniting Greece with what other country?",
        "answer": "Cyprus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Earl van Dorn’s defeat in this state while trying to retake the railroad junction at Corinth was a major loss for the South. Another Union victory in this state, where John C. Pemberton surrendered to the Union, cut off Texas and Arkansas from the rest of the Confederacy. Ulysses Grant led a successful siege of Vicksburg, a fortress town on this state’s namesake river. For ten points, name this Confederate state where, in 1863, Union forces seized the capital of Jackson.",
        "answer": "Mississippi"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Confederates surrendered Vicksburg on this day in 1863, one day after the last day of Gettysburg.",
        "answer": "July 4th"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1999, this country sought to isolate Ladakh and force its enemies to withdraw from the Siachen Glacier by launching Operation Badr, even though it had committed to the peaceful Lahore Declaration in the same year. This country’s troops crossed the Line of Control to instigate the Kargil War against a rival with whom it often contests the region of Kashmir. For ten points, name this rival and western neighbor of India.",
        "answer": "Pakistan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Fourteen years before Pakistan’s Operation Badr, Iran launched an Operation Badr that captured a highway connecting Baghdad and this city, Iraq’s main port on the Shatt al-Arab.",
        "answer": "Basra"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "ThissubstancewasrecklesslyhandledbyfactoryownersincitieslikeWaterbury,Connecticut,Orange, New Jersey, and Ottawa, Illinois, where workers were given the instructions “lip, dip, paint.” In 1921, President Harding presented Marie Curie with a vial holding one gram of this substance, which names an institute she led at the University of Paris. After polonium, this was the second element discovered by the Curies. For ten points, name this highly toxic radioactive element with chemical symbol Ra [spell it].",
        "answer": "radium"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Many of the “Radium Girls,” who were falsely told that working with radium was safe, had their medical claims denied on grounds that their symptoms of radiation sickness were actually caused by this scandalous disease. The US government carried out an unethical study of this disease at Tuskegee from 1932 to 1972.",
        "answer": "syphilis"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was nearly assassinated by Anteo Zamboni, prompting him to establish a secret police known as the OVRA. He soldified power by changing parliamentary thresholds through the Acerbo Law. The Republic of Sal´o was led by this man, who signed a treaty with Pius IX in 1929 to recognize an independent Vatican City within his country’s borders. For ten points, name this leader who seized power after his Blackshirts marched on Rome in 1922 and led Italy during World War II.",
        "answer": "Benito Mussolini"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This 1929 treaty recognized the independence of the Vatican City. It is named for the papal residence, a palace that also hosted numerous medieval ecumenical councils.",
        "answer": [
          "Lateran Treaty",
          "Lateran Palace",
          "Apostolic Palace of the Lateran",
          "Lateran Councils"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader authorized the use of deadly force over an internal dispute for the cargo ship Altalena. This leader formed the Rafi party, which lost to the Alignment faction of his successor Levi Eshkol. This leader authorized Operation Magic Carpet in order to transport Jews to his country. This leader consolidated the Haganah and Irgun militias to form the IDF in an 1948 war with the Arabs following independence from Britain. For ten points, name this first prime minister of Israel.",
        "answer": "David Ben-Gurion"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Operation Magic Carpet targeted Jews living in, or with heritages from, this country on the Arabian Peninsula. Today, there may be fewer than 100 Jews living in this country, subject to death threats from Houthis.",
        "answer": "Yemen"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These people offered a peace deal in which they gave up lands south of the Tugela River to lure in and massacre Piet Retief’s dignitaries. That incident was avenged when these people failed to breach a laager fort set up by Andries Pretorius at the Battle of the Blood River. These people were led by Dingane [din-GAH-nay] and Cetshwayo [key-SHWY-oh], whose armies fought the battles of Rorke’s Drift and Isandlwana against the British. For ten points, name this southern African empire that was led by Shaka.",
        "answer": "amaZulu people"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Anglo-Zulu War effectively ended at this July 4, 1879 battle over the Zulu capital city, fought seven months after the British lost at Isandlwana.",
        "answer": "Battle of Ulundi"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Ga¨etan Dugas, a flight attendant who was nicknamed this disease’s Patient O [oh], was erroneously accused of being a North American originator of this disease. Traces of this disease’s type 1 strain have been found in preserved lymph and blood samples from citizens of 1960 L´eopoldville. This disease attacks CD4+ helper T cells, weakening its host’s immune system. For ten points, name this retrovirus that can cause AIDS.",
        "answer": "HIV"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the early 1980s, HIV was known by this name, due to the mistaken understanding that it was endemic to homosexual populations.",
        "answer": "GRID"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city’s mayor Ron Norick created a massive municipal improvement project known as MAPS that was funded without debt. The Field of Empty Chairs are part of a memorial in this city that was authorized by Bill Clinton; that memorial commemorates an event that was carried out by a Gulf War veteran who opposed the handling of the Ruby Ridge and Waco standoffs. For ten points, name this city where over 160 people were killed in a 1995 bombing by Timothy McVeigh.",
        "answer": "Oklahoma City"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Timothy McVeigh’s execution in 2001 marked the first execution carried out by the federal government since the decision in this 1972 Supreme Court case, which temporarily ended the death penalty in the US.",
        "answer": "Furman v. Georgia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A temple sculpture at this location consists of a pair of water mirrors intended to view the sky. The Condor Stone is located in a cave in this city where boys underwent a rite of passage during the Royal Feast of the Sun. Advanced irrigation systems in this city rely on water from the Urubamba River. This city was falsely thought to be Vilcabamba Viejo by a Yale lecturer who led an expedition here. Hiram Bingham “re-discovered,” for ten points, what citadel sometimes referred to as the “Lost City of the Incas?”",
        "answer": "Machu Picchu"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Machu Picchu is believed to have been built as an estate for this ruler, the ninth Sapa Inca. This grandfather of Huayna Capac ruled until 1471.",
        "answer": "Pachacuti"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A king of this country had a vision of a cross in the sky before winning the Battle of Ourique. The bull Manifestis Probatum recognized Afonso I as the first king of this country. The Battle of Aljubarrota was fought in this country, after which it was ruled by the Aviz dynasty. A prince of this country sponsored voyages to West Africa, sparking the Age of Discovery. For ten points, name this Iberian country that was home to Prince Henry the Navigator.",
        "answer": "Kingdom of Portugal"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The House of Aviz ruled Portugal for two centuries until the Habsburgs created the Iberian Union; that union lasted until 1640 when this final Portuguese ruling dynasty rose to power.",
        "answer": "House of Braganza"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this state, Frank Canton led a band of Texans known as Wolcott’s Regulators in Powder River Country during the Johnston County War. Thomas J. Walsh led an investigation of a scandal named for a location in this state; as a result, Albert Fall was imprisoned for accepting bribes. The Teapot Dome oil field is in this state, where the Great Western Cattle Trail passed by Fort Laramie. The first state to grant suffrage to women was, for ten points, what state that is governed from Cheyenne?",
        "answer": "Wyoming"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Johnston County War ended after this President called in the cavalry. This man was elected in the last Presidential election in which Wyoming was a territory, not a state, and when he lost his re-election in the year of the Johnston County War, Populist candidate James Weaver carried four western states.",
        "answer": "Benjamin Harrison"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these events that affected the Selk’nam in the Tierra del Fuego was led by Romanian-Argentine engineer Julius Popper, who designed the city of Havana. Dmitry Milyutin carried out one of these events, forcing many Circassians to be quarantined in lazarettos in the Ottoman Empire. Lothar von Trotha committed one of these actions in Namibia after the Herero and the Nama rebelled against German rule, and another of these events occurred in modern Sudan in the Darfur region. For ten points, give this term for an atrocity against an entire racial group, such as the Holocaust.",
        "answer": "genocides"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Polish-Jewish lawyer coined the word genocide and described the Holodomor as “the destruction of the Ukrainian nation,” a “classic example of Soviet genocide”.",
        "answer": "Raphael Lemkin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "William Gilpin was the first governor of this territory, where Lewis Ralston found gold at a creek now named for him. George Custer won the Battle of Washita River in this territory where, in 1864, volunteers under John Chivington massacred members of the Cheyenne and Arapaho tribes. President Grant made this territory a state in 1876. For ten points, name this territory to which the “Fifty-Niners” migrated during the Pike’s Peak Gold Rush.",
        "answer": "Colorado Territory"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "John Chivington’s men killed hundreds of Cheyenne and Arapaho people, mostly women and children, in this November 1864 massacre.",
        "answer": "Sand Creek Massacre"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was once led by \"The Madman Who Loves,” Abdalá Bucaram. With a neighbor, this country's president of Lebanese descent, Jamil Mahuad, signed the Brasilia Presidential Act. After a 1972 coup, this country implemented a \"Return to the Constitution Plan.” One party in this country was named \"Alfaro Lives, Dammit!” In 2017, this country's president, Lenín Moreno, succeeded Rafael Correa. For ten points, name this South American nation, the first to call for independence in 1809.",
        "answer": "Republic of Ecuador"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "These islands are part of Ecuador and the location of Charles Darwin's studies of animals on an 1835 expedition that led to the theory of evolution.",
        "answer": [
          "Galápagos Islands",
          "Archipelago de Colón"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Zero-tolerance on this border was implemented in Operation Streamline. This border was changed in the Chamizal Dispute due to river shifts. The Big Bend National Park lies on this border, and the International Boundary and Water Commission deals with water rights on this border. This border was first fixed in the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo, and, more recently, Donald Trump proposed enhancing a wall on this border. For ten points, name this border that includes a portion of the Rio Grande.",
        "answer": [
          "United States-Mexico border",
          "US",
          "USA for United States",
          "United Mexican States",
          "EUM for Mexico"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "While Donald Trump claimed during his 2016 presidential campaign that Mexico would pay for his planned border wall, this president of Mexico, in office from 2012 to 2018, denied that his country would pay for the construction of such a wall.",
        "answer": "Enrique Peña Nieto"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Guy Hopkins attempted to implicate this man as a member of the Knights of the Golden Circle, and James Dobbin's speech for this man aided his nomination. Shortly after his election, this man's son, Benjamin, was killed in a train crash, causing the First Lady to avoid public events for two years. This man purchased part of Mexico with the Gadsden Purchase and his diplomats authored the Ostend Manifesto. For ten points, name this 14th US president.",
        "answer": "Franklin Pierce"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Knights of the Golden Circle would have had their headquarters on this island, and the Ostend Manifesto described the US rationale for purchasing this island from Spain.",
        "answer": "Cuba"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This plant is damaged by microscopic cyst nematodes as well as the ten-striped spearman in the Rocky Mountains. Copper pesticide can control the Phytophthora infestans disease from damaging this plant. Monsanto genetically engineered the New Leaf form of this plant of which Chuno is a freeze fried version. These plants were first domesticated in Peru and Bolivia and widely replaced turnip and rutabaga production. For ten points, name this crop, the subject of a Great Famine in Ireland in the mid-19th century.",
        "answer": "Potato"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the Potato Blight returned again in 1879, an agrarian movement had begun fighting for this resource. A series of acts over this resource occurred after an 1879 war named for it in which tenants tried to take this resource.",
        "answer": "Land 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 3"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These two countries engaged over the Chumbi Valley in the Nathu La and Cho La Clashes over the Kingdom of Sikkim. These two countries disputed borders along the McMahon Line and the Line of Actual Control. In order to avoid war over Tibet, these two countries codified the Five principles of Peaceful Coexistence. Fighting over the Aksai Chin, these two countries clashed over the Forward Policy on the Himalayan border in a 1962 war. Led by Nehru and Mao, for ten points, name these two most populous countries in the world.",
        "answer": "People's Republic of China and the Republic of India"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "China and India have disputed water rights on the Brahmaputra River that flows from high in the Himalayas into this river, the third largest in the world in terms of total discharge.",
        "answer": [
          "Ganges River",
          "Ganga River"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this country, an association called Honest People reported thousands of election violations. In 2006, this country's OMON police tried to stop one candidate from campaigning. This country's current president won 80% of all votes in the 2020 election, defeating Sviatlana Tsikhanouskaya [[tsik-on-oo-SKY-ah]]. The Coordination Council attempted to take power away from this country's leader, nicknamed \"Europe's Last Dictator.\" For ten points, name this Eastern European country in which people protested against Alexander Lukashenko in Minsk.",
        "answer": "Republic of Belarus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2006, the democratic opposition in Belarus led this revolution against the election of Lukashenko, named for a blue-colored clothing.",
        "answer": [
          "Jeans Revolution",
          "Denim Revolution",
          "or Cornflower Revolution"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Derry Coburn often accompanied this man in his later life, and William Russell and this man led an expedition during which they had a meeting at Sycamore Shoals with Richard Henderson. Blackfish took this man to Chillicothe after he was forced to run the gauntlet. This man is often depicted atop Pilot Knob looking at the Bluegrass Region. This longhunter served under Hugh Waddell to suppress the Cherokee uprising. For ten points, name this folk hero who blazed the Wilderness Road into Kentucky.",
        "answer": "Daniel Boone"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Daniel Boone was elected three times to this state's General Assembly and was captured near Charlottesville on his way to the state capital in 1781.",
        "answer": "Virginia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This structure was criticized in a leaflet titled \"Public Necessity or Just Plain Pork\". Luther Ely Smith proposed this structure to Mayor Bernard Dickmann, which led to the creation of the non-profit \"Jenny May.” In 1934, John Cochran and Bennett Champ Clark introduced an appropriation bill to create this structure which is situated near the Old Courthouse where the Dred Scott decision took place. Eero Saarinen designed this stainless steel monument that overlooks the Mississippi River. For ten points, name this St. Louis arch.",
        "answer": [
          "Gateway Arch or Gateway to the West",
          "St. Louis Arch before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Eero Saarinen's father, Gottlieb Eliel Saarinen, was runner up to Walter Burley Griffin in a contest to design this city, Australia's capital.",
        "answer": "Canberra, Australia 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 4"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Sufi Abdul Hamid targeted Jews as well as people of this ethnicity. Governor John M. Parker organized an 1891 lynch mob against people of this ethnicity. Germans and prisoners of war of this ethnicity were housed at Camp Albuquerque. Joe Ettor organized these people in labor movements, and eleven men of this ethnicity were lynched in 1891 in New Orleans after Police Chief David Hennessy was murdered. Often Roman Catholic, for ten points, name this ethnicity that included people like Sacco and Vanzetti.",
        "answer": "Italian-American"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1977, this Massachusetts governor and 1988 Democratic nominee officially declared that Sacco and Vanzetti had been unfairly tried and convicted.",
        "answer": "Michael Dukakis"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Maurice Francis Egan tried to trade for this region in exchange for Mindanao. Expeditions to Sabine and Shannon Islands near this region were part of the North Atlantic weather war. Charles Francis Hall saw much of the northwest of this region, and its northern part was claimed by the Polaris expedition. Part of this island was claimed by Norway as “Erik the Red's Land,” and Project Icework attempted to construct hundreds of minuteman missiles on this island. For ten points, name this large island within the Kingdom of Denmark.",
        "answer": "Greenland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of these bombers crashed with thermonuclear weapons at Thule [[THOO-lee]] Air Base in Greenland. The US was forced to end Chrome Dome operations after that incident.",
        "answer": "Boeing B-52 Stratofortress"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this city, Roscoe Conkling Simmons worked as a columnist and politician. This city’s second African-American alderman, Louis B. Anderson, succeeded the first, Oscar Stanton De Priest, who was defended from graft by Clarence Darrow. Robert S. Abbott started this city’s Bud Billiken Parade and Picnic and founded the Defender newspaper. In 1993, this city's Hyde Park neighborhood supported Carol Moseley Braun for US senator. For ten points, name this Midwest city where Barack Obama served as a voter organizer.",
        "answer": "Chicago, Illinois"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This US president was scolded by Southern politicians in 1929 after Oscar De Priest's wife, Jessie, was invited to the White House for tea with his First Lady, Lou.",
        "answer": "Herbert Clark Hoover 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 5"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this city in 2019, white-shirted mobsters attacked MTR passengers with steel rods until police arrived 39 minutes later. Relations between this city's residents and police worsened after an attack at Prince Edward subway station. In this city, protestors wore black while trying to \"be water\" per Bruce Lee's philosophy. This city faced 2019-20 protests over an extradition bill authored by the CCP. For ten points, name this Southern Chinese city governed by Carrie Lam, where protests broke out over Mainland China's control over civil liberties.",
        "answer": [
          "Hong Kong Special Administrative Region of the People's Republic of China",
          "HKSAR"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hong Kong Protestors like Agnes Chow and Joshua Wong participated in these 2014 protests against changes to the electoral system, named for an item opened by Paul Zimmerman at an indoor reception.",
        "answer": [
          "Umbrella Revolution",
          "Umbrella Movement",
          "or Occupy Movement"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Waldo Evans landed at this island's city of Piti. This island was captured by the USS Charleston under Henry Glass, and Spanish merchant Francisco Portusach helped surrender this island to the US. Masashi Ito and Soichi Yokoi hid on this island until the 1970s, long after this island was retaken from the Japanese in 1944. The Chamorro live on this island, part of the Mariana Islands, which was taken from Spain in the Spanish-American War. For ten points, name this US territory in the Pacific.",
        "answer": "Guam"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Guam was transferred to US Navy control in December, 1898 by this US president.",
        "answer": "William McKinley"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A Jewish tribe identified as the Banu Qurayza betrayed this city during the Battle of the Trench. One document signed in this city defines a community identified with the term ummah. This city is home to the Green Dome, which is part of the last mosque built by Muhammad, the Prophet's Mosque. This city was the destination of a group of early Muslims fleeing their hometown in a trip known as the hegira. For ten points, name this second- holiest city in Islam, the location to which Muhammad fled from Mecca.",
        "answer": "Medina or Al Madinah Al Munawwarah"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Medina is home to the tombs of Mohammed, Umar, and this other caliph, a father in-law of Muhammad, considered the first Caliph by Sunnis.",
        "answer": "Abu Bakr al Siddiq or Abu Bakr Abdullah ibn Uthman 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 3"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "China gave this country 15 thousand military advisers and a $20 million gift to help its communists. This country invaded its neighbor in the Ba Chúc massacre, causing the collapse of a regime. Both GRUNK and FUNK operated in this country, and supporting Operation Freedom Deal in this country led the US to adopt the War Powers Resolution. In this country, the “new people” were eliminated by the “base people,” and its government operated the Santebal in its Killing Fields. For ten points, the Khmer Rouge and Pol Pot governed which country?",
        "answer": [
          "Kingdom of Cambodia",
          "Democratic Kampuchea",
          "Khmer Republic",
          "People's Republic of Kampuchea"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man ruled Cambodia as its king twice, from 1941 to 1955 and from 1993 until he abdicated in favor of his son in 2004.",
        "answer": "Norodom Sihanouk Both names required"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's decision on stare decisis led to a split into strong and weak forms after Burnet v. Coronado Oil & Gas Co. In Gilbert v. Minnesota, this man defended Freedom of Speech, and he aided Thomas Masayrk's Washington Declaration. The Judiciary Committee held its first ever public hearing for this man, and this man's pioneering legal brief style featured expert witness testimony and scientific information which was used in Muller v. Oregon. For ten points, name this first Jewish Supreme Court Justice.",
        "answer": "Louis Brandeis"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Brandeis was born in Louisville, Kentucky to parents who came to the US from Bohemia, a region that is now part of this modern-day country.",
        "answer": "Czech Republic or Czechia 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 3"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The so-called “second generation” of this art movement included three founders of the Metropolitan Museum of Art: John Frederick Kensett, Sanford Robinson Gifford, and Frederic Edwin Church. The towns of Skaneateles and Catskill both host historic landmarks dedicated to this art movement, which is named after a nearby location. For ten points, name this mid-19th century American art “school” exemplified by the landscape art of Thomas Cole and Asher Durand.",
        "answer": "Hudson River School"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Perhaps the best known Hudson River School painting is this Asher Durand work that depicts Thomas Cole and his friend, William Cullen Bryant in the Catskills.",
        "answer": "Kindred Spirits"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country's ruling party fractured in 2015 with Amama Mbabazi forming the GO FORWARD group. The National Resistance Movement has been in power in this country since 1986. This country's military arrested politician Bobi Wine days after he announced his nomination for president in 2021. In January, 2021, Yoweri Museveni was reelected to a 6th term to govern this country. Milton Obote was removed from power in this country by a man who faced the Entebbe Raid. For ten points, name this African country that was led by Idi Amin.",
        "answer": "Republic of Uganda"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Museveni has faced a 34 year insurgency by this guerilla group. Its leader, Joseph Kony, believes he is inhabited by a Chinese phantom and has abducted children to be soldiers.",
        "answer": [
          "Lord's Resistance Army",
          "LRA 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Finals"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A party in this state included \"Dragons of Death\" and FICO groups and that party uses \"zebra lists\" in which every third person must be a woman. Eduardo Montane, a history professor at Syracuse University, led a party in this country that Samora Machel would soon govern. Joaquim Chissano helped this country sign the Lusaka Accord. FRELIMO brought independence to this country from Portugal. For ten points, name this country with capital at Maputo, which names a strait that separates it and Madagascar.",
        "answer": "Republic of Mozambique"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mozambique came under the control of Portugal in the years following this explorer's 1498 voyage around the Cape of Good Hope.",
        "answer": "Vasco da Gama"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This river is the site of the Gariep Dam, which has been used for irrigation by the local Khoekhoe [[KO-KO]] people. This river enters the ocean near Alexander Bay and descends at Augrabies [[aw-GRAH-beez]] Falls. This river was named by Robert Gordon, who introduced Merino sheep to the Cape Colony. This river passes through only one city, Upington, and flows on the border of Lesotho [[luh-SOO-too]] and Namibia from the Drakensberg Mountains. For ten points, name this longest river within South Africa, named for the Dutch ruling family.",
        "answer": [
          "Orange River",
          "Gariep River, Groote River,",
          "Senqu River"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Orange River flows south of this South African city, the capital of Northern Cape Province. This city, which contains a notable \"Big Hole,\" was where the De Beers family established its diamond company.",
        "answer": "Kimberley, South Africa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country fought a month-long conflict with Ecuador in 1995 known as the Cenepa War. Beginning in 1996, the Japanese embassy in this country was the scene of a hostage crisis that lasted for four months. In this nation, Chilean Bernardo O'Higgins and Argentine general José de San Martín [[mar-TEEN]] crossed the Andes to help liberate this country from Spanish control. For ten points, name this South American country that was once the heartland of the Inca.",
        "answer": [
          "Peru",
          "Republic of Peru",
          "or República del Perú",
          "Piruw Ripuwlika",
          "Piruw Suyu"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Spanish conquistador conquered the Inca people of Peru in 1532 after winning the Battle of Cajamarca [[KAH-hah-MAR-kuh]].",
        "answer": "Francisco Pizarro or Francisco Pizarro González"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This river contains Margaret Island, formerly a base for the Knights of Saint John. The mouth of this river, which was known as Okeanos Potamos in antiquity, contains Apollo's sacred island of Alba. This river's basin was the site of the Vinča [[VEEN-tsuh]] culture, and was crossed by Darius the Great in order to invade the Scythian [[SKIHTH-yen]] realm. The Dacians were separated from the Roman Empire by, for ten points, what river that now runs through European capitals like Budapest and Vienna?",
        "answer": [
          "Danube River or Donau",
          "Donaj",
          "Duna",
          "Istros"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Danube also runs through this city, formerly known as Pressburg, which is now the capital of Slovakia.",
        "answer": [
          "Bratislava",
          "Pozsony"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "To advertise this city at the 1904 World's Fair, Giuseppe Moretti created the tallest cast-iron statue in the world depicting Vulcan wielding a hammer. This city's mining significance gave the local KKK chapter easy access to dynamite, allowing them to terrorize Black citizens in the 16th Street Baptist Church bombing. In a call for direct action against segregation, Martin Luther King, Jr. wrote the treatise \"Letters from [this city's] Jail.\" For ten points, name this industrial Alabama city.",
        "answer": "Birmingham"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This fellow Alabama city was the starting point of a Civil Rights march to Montgomery which crossed the Edmund Pettus Bridge.",
        "answer": [
          "Selma",
          "Selma to Montgomery Marches"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This island attempted to secede from one country after the \"Grito de Lares\" [[GREE- toh deh LAH-rehs]]. This non-Cuban island was controlled by the Spanish since the defeat of the native Taíno [[tah-EE-noh]] by Juan Ponce de León, who became this island's first governor. This island became a \"Commonwealth\" in 1952, and movements for full integration and independence have competed since then. For ten points, name this Caribbean territory of the United States, a potential 51st state.",
        "answer": [
          "Commonwealth of Puerto Rico",
          "Estado Libre Asociado de Puerto Rico",
          "or Boriken",
          "or Borinquen"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This island west of Puerto Rico was the site of the first European settlement in the New World, La Navidad, as well as the first permanent settlement, Santo Domingo.",
        "answer": [
          "Hispaniola or La Española",
          "or Ispayola",
          "or Ayiti"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This region's eastern part was split off as the Union Territory of Ladakh, and its northernmost frontiers, far from its capital Srinagar, are governed as Gilgit-Baltistan [[GIL- git BAHL-tee-stahn]]. This region's inhabitants were separated after a 1947 war that reflected tensions between its Maharaja Hari Singh and this region's majority-Muslim population. With a Line of Control between two parts of this region ending at the Siachen [[see-AH-chen]] Glacier, for ten points, what is this region which is disputed by India and Pakistan?",
        "answer": [
          "Kashmir",
          "Jammu and Kashmir Valley"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This province to the south of Kashmir was similarly divided by India and Pakistan, albeit peacefully, and is home to the world's largest population of Sikhs, as well as the cities of Amritsar [[AM-rit-sar]] and Lahore [[lah-HOR]].",
        "answer": [
          "Punjab",
          "Panjāb"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A peasant rebellion in this nation led by Skipper Clement was put down by the noble Johan Rantzau [[RAHNT-zow]] during the Count's Feud. Håkon VI [[HAH-kohn the SIXTH]] of Norway married this kingdom's Queen Margaret, leading to the formation of the Kalmar Union. The German Empire seized this country's province of Schleswig [[SHLESS-vig]] in a brief 19th century conflict. For ten points, name this Scandinavian nation that once governed Sweden and Norway from its capital, Copenhagen.",
        "answer": [
          "Kingdom of Denmark or Kongeriget Danmark",
          "the Danish Realm",
          "or Danmarks Rige"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the 1970s, Denmark awarded home rule to what largest non-continental island on Earth?",
        "answer": [
          "Greenland",
          "Kalaallit Nunaat",
          "or Grønland 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 5"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "US army officer Henry Schneider revealed that this company provided a third of all trucks in the Wehrmacht through their Cologne plant which was confiscated in 1941. In the 1920s, this company attempted to set up a free state in Brazil in order to dodge the British monopoly on rubber. While not invented by this company's leader, the assembly line was popularized in the car factories of this company. For ten points, name this American based car company famous for its production of Model T's.",
        "answer": "Ford Motor Company"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "While Detroit is known as the \"Motor City\", Ford's headquarters and the Henry Ford museum are located in what Michigan city, which was exposed in James M. Loewen's Sundown Towns for aggressively excluding Black migrants?",
        "answer": "Dearborn, Michigan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This modern country was the heartland of the medieval Mutapa Empire. This country's predecessor state was governed briefly by Bishop Muzorewa [[moo-zoh-REH- wah]] following the Lancaster House Agreement. A \"Bush War\" in this country ended with the rise of the ZANU-PF and its leader Robert Mugabe. Mugabe's thirty-year presidency occurred in, for ten points, what southeast African country that succeeded Rhodesia?",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of Zimbabwe",
          "Republic of Rhodesia",
          "Southern Rhodesia until mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Rhodesia was named for Cecil Rhodes, a British politician who, through his company De Beers, established a monopoly on this good.",
        "answer": "Diamonds"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The ancient city of Zadracarta sat on this body of water and was the seat of power of Hyrcania. This body of water marked the western extent of the Chinese Empire during the Tang Dynasty, and it was primarily explored by Fedor Soimonov [[SOY-mon-off]] during the reign of Peter the Great. The city of Derbent, which lies on this body of water, was handed over in the Treaty of Gulistan from Persia to Russia. For ten points, name this largest inland body of water, named for an ancient Caucasian tribe.",
        "answer": [
          "Caspian Sea",
          "Mazandaran Sea",
          "or Hyrcania Sea",
          "or Khazar Sea",
          "Kaspiyskoye more",
          "Hazar denizi"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This central Asian country, which was governed for nearly three decades by Nursultan Nazarbayev [[nah-zar-BYE-yev]], lies northeast of the Caspian Sea and has the longest coastline of any country on it.",
        "answer": "Republic of Kazakhstan or Qazaqstan Respublikasy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2013, rapper Killah P was murdered in this country by a member of the Golden Dawn, which lost its last Parliamentary seat in 2019. This country's New Democracy party was founded in 1974 after the fall of the Regime of the Colonels. Syriza [[sih-REE-zah]] party leader Alexis Tsipras [[TSIP-rahss]] led this country through a period of austerity bookended by its third E.U. bailout. For ten points, name this country whose Prime Minister Kyriakos Mitsotakis [[kee-ree-AH-kohss mit-so-TAH-kiss]] came to power in 2019.",
        "answer": [
          "Greece or Hellenic Republic",
          "or Elliniki Dimokratia",
          "or Hellas",
          "or Ellas",
          "or Ellada"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Greek debt crisis occurred under the governance of the PASOK [[PASS-ock]] party, which espouses this political and economic ideology, often represented by a red rose.",
        "answer": "Social-Democracy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Taney [[TAW-nee]]-era case Strader v. Graham held that this law's prohibition of slavery did not extend to states created from the territory it covered. Little Turtle's War was fought in the territory created by this act, which mandated appointments for governors and population thresholds for future statehood. For ten points, name this organic act that established a namesake territory between the Mississippi and Ohio rivers.",
        "answer": "Northwest Ordinance"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Northwest Territory is considered the first example of this kind of land in U.S. history, which has yet to be dedicated to a specific use. The Homestead Act allowed applicants to settle this kind of land and convert it to private property.",
        "answer": "Public Domain"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country's 1960 independence was established by the London and Zürich Agreements. One leader of this country survived four assassination attempts and was given the title \"Ethnarch.\" This country, whose first president was Makarios III [[mah-KAHR- yohss the THIRD]], pursued a union with a larger country in a process called Enosis [[ee- NOH-siss]]. This country's north has been occupied since 1973 by Turkey and is divided by the Green Line. For ten points, name this island nation, controlled successively by the Ottomans and Great Britain, in the eastern Mediterranean.",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of Cyprus or Kypriaki Dimokratia",
          "or Kibris Cumhuriyeti",
          "Kypros"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "It has been suggested that the word \"Cyprus\" derives from the Sumerian word for this metal, which was found in abundance on the island.",
        "answer": "Copper or Cu"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "COLONIAL VIRGINIA",
      "prompt": "In pre-Revolutionary Virginia, who or what was the…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country which chartered the Virginia Colony?",
          "answer": "England"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fort on a namesake river which was the first European settlement?",
          "answer": "Jamestown"
        },
        {
          "question": "Powhatan princess who saved John Smith's life?",
          "answer": "Pocahontas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of a 1676 \"rebellion\" which burned the capital?",
          "answer": "Nathaniel Bacon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Governor targeted in that rebellion, who shares his name with the hometown of the University of California's oldest campus?",
          "answer": "William Berkeley"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ancestor of the Virginia General Assembly which functioned as the colonial legislature?",
          "answer": "House of Burgesses"
        },
        {
          "question": "College chartered in 1693, America's second-oldest after Harvard?",
          "answer": "College of William & Mary"
        },
        {
          "question": "Second governor of Virginia and namesake of another state?",
          "answer": "Baron De La Warr \"Delaware\""
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "LEWIS AND CLARK",
      "prompt": "The Lewis and Clark expedition...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was intended to explore what large acquisition of land made in 1803?",
          "answer": [
            "Louisiana Purchase",
            "Louisiana territory",
            "Louisiana"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was dispatched by what President who made that acquisition?",
          "answer": [
            "Thomas Jefferson",
            "Jefferson"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Departed from what city, which commemorates the event with the Gateway Arch?",
          "answer": "St. Louis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was aided by what Shosone (shuh-SHOW-nee) woman?",
          "answer": "Sacajawea"
        },
        {
          "question": "Followed what river of modern-day Washington and Oregon to the Pacific?",
          "answer": [
            "Columbia River",
            "Columbia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Formally had what name?",
          "answer": [
            "Corps of Discovery Expedition",
            "Corps of Discovery"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Suffered its first death near what is now Sioux City in what state?",
          "answer": "Iowa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the subject of a two-volume history by what future head of the Second Bank of the\nUnited States?",
          "answer": [
            "Nicholas Biddle",
            "Biddle"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Islands",
      "prompt": "Which island...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "is a former Danish colony and - not counting Australia - the world’s largest?",
          "answer": "Greenland"
        },
        {
          "question": "has been ruled by either Fidel or Raul Castro since its 1959 revolution?",
          "answer": "Cuba"
        },
        {
          "question": "is the world’s second largest, and is home to the Indonesian province of Papua and a former Australian colony?",
          "answer": "New Guinea"
        },
        {
          "question": "is shared by the Dominican Republic and Haiti and is where Columbus lost the Santa Maria?",
          "answer": "Hispaniola"
        },
        {
          "question": "lost its Minoan civilization after a volcanic eruption on Thera?",
          "answer": "Crete"
        },
        {
          "question": "is the northernmost of Japan’s four main islands and home to many indigenous Ainu people in Hidaku?",
          "answer": "Hokkaido"
        },
        {
          "question": "was the site of the Great Kanto Earthquake of 1923?",
          "answer": "Honshu"
        },
        {
          "question": "was flown over by Korean Air 007, which was then shot down by Soviets in 1983?",
          "answer": "Sakhalin"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Port Explosions",
      "prompt": "In the history of mishaps near the water, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "U.S. Navy ship that sunk in Havana Harbor in 1898?",
          "answer": "USS Maine"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Nova Scotia capital city where a fire on the SS Mont Blanc detonated its explosive cargo, killing 2,000 people?",
          "answer": "Halifax"
        },
        {
          "question": "State where the SS Grandcamp exploded 10 miles from Galveston?",
          "answer": "Texas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Middle Eastern country where the USS Cole was attacked by al-Qaeda while in the port of Aden?",
          "answer": "Yemen"
        },
        {
          "question": "State where the Port Neal fertilizer plant, near Sioux City on its Missouri River border with Nebraska, exploded in 1994?",
          "answer": "Iowa"
        },
        {
          "question": "River that forms the Georgia-South Carolina border, on which a sugar refinery exploded in 2008?",
          "answer": "Savannah River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Northeastern Chinese city near Beijing where August 2015 explosions killed 173 people?",
          "answer": "Tianjin"
        },
        {
          "question": "3 storage caused three of those disasters?",
          "answer": "Ammonium nitrate words must be exact"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Louisiana",
      "prompt": "In Louisiana, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "most populous city, which was struck by Hurricane Katrina.",
          "answer": "New Orleans"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who signed the Louisiana Purchase.",
          "answer": "Thomas Jefferson"
        },
        {
          "question": "administrative districts that Louisiana uses in lieu of counties.",
          "answer": "parishes"
        },
        {
          "question": "city in Louisiana named for the “Hero of Two Worlds,” a French general who fought in the Revolutionary War.",
          "answer": [
            "Lafayette",
            "Marquis de Lafayette"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Governor, nicknamed the “Kingfish,” who was assassinated in 1935.",
          "answer": "Huey Pierce Long Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "man who was arrested in 1892 for sitting in a train car that was for whites only?",
          "answer": "Homer Plessy"
        },
        {
          "question": "world’s longest bridge over water, which was controversially closed during Katrina?",
          "answer": [
            "Lake Pontchartrain Causeway",
            "any description of a bridge spanning Lake Pontchartrain"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "treaty that ceded control of Louisiana from Spain back to France in 1800.",
          "answer": "Third Treaty of San Ildefonso"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The New Year",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that celebrates New Year with the dragon dance in cities like Beijing?",
          "answer": "People’s Republic of China"
        },
        {
          "question": "New York City intersection where a Waterford crystal ball is dropped on New Year’s Eve?",
          "answer": "Times Square"
        },
        {
          "question": "Roman god of doorways and gates celebrated on New Year’s, and for whom the first month of the western calendar is named?",
          "answer": "Janus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Robert Burns poem traditionally sung on New Year’s Eve?",
          "answer": "Auld Lang Syne"
        },
        {
          "question": "Jewish New Year holiday, on which the shofar is traditionally blown?",
          "answer": "Rosh Hashanah or Yom Teruah"
        },
        {
          "question": "Vietnamese New Year holiday, on which the North Vietnamese launched a surprise attack in 1968?",
          "answer": [
            "Tet Nguyen Dan",
            "Tet Offensive"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Calendar that began the New Year on 1 Vendemiaire [one ven-demi-air]?",
          "answer": [
            "French Republican Calendar",
            "French Revolutionary Calendar",
            "any description of the calendar instituted during the French Revolution",
            "the Paris Commune"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Pacific island country whose Line Islands are the first land west of the International Date Line?",
          "answer": [
            "Kiribati , but",
            "phonetic pronunciations"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "South America",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "nation whose capital city, Montevideo, hosted the first FIFA World Cup.",
          "answer": "Uruguay"
        },
        {
          "question": "President of Argentina who was married to Evita.",
          "answer": "Juan Domingo Peron"
        },
        {
          "question": "man, known as “El Libertador,” who founded Gran Colombia and conquered Ecuador.",
          "answer": "Sim´on Jos´e Antonio de la Santisima Trinidad Bolivar y Palacios"
        },
        {
          "question": "country currently led by Nicolas Maduro, chosen by a socialist who died in 2013.",
          "answer": "Venezuela"
        },
        {
          "question": "country whose Golden Law outlawed slavery in 1888.",
          "answer": "Brazil"
        },
        {
          "question": "man who overthrew Salvador Allende [eye-EN-day] in 1973.",
          "answer": "Augusto Jose Ramon Pinochet Ugarte"
        },
        {
          "question": "country with whom the U.S. wanted to sign the Hay-Herran Treaty regarding ownership of Panama.",
          "answer": "Colombia"
        },
        {
          "question": "nation where members of the Peoples Temple Agricultural Project committed mass suicide in 1978.",
          "answer": "Guyana"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Great Lakes",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "state that once sued its southern neighbor, Illinois, over lowering Lake Michigan’s water level.",
          "answer": "Wisconsin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ohio city on Lake Erie and the once-aflame Cuyahoga River.",
          "answer": "Cleveland"
        },
        {
          "question": "river the drains Lake Erie into Lake Ontario, on which three massive waterfalls lie?",
          "answer": "Niagara River or Niagara Falls"
        },
        {
          "question": "river, once invaded by German U-boats, that connects Lake Ontario to the Atlantic.",
          "answer": "Saint Lawrence River"
        },
        {
          "question": "American naval commander who said “we have met the enemy, and they are ours” at the Battle of Lake Erie.",
          "answer": "Oliver Hazard Perry"
        },
        {
          "question": "lake on the Vermont-New York border that Bill Clinton briefly made the “sixth” Great Lake.",
          "answer": "Lake Champlain"
        },
        {
          "question": "freighter that sank on Lake Superior in 1975, killing 29.",
          "answer": "SS Edmund Fitzgerald"
        },
        {
          "question": "1818 treaty that limited naval forces on the Great Lakes.",
          "answer": "Rush-Bagot Treaty"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Il Risorgimento",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "capital city whose 1871 capture finished the Italian unification.",
          "answer": "Rome"
        },
        {
          "question": "city, home to the Uffizi gallery, which replaced Turin as a temporary capital.",
          "answer": "Florence"
        },
        {
          "question": "first king of the unified Italy.",
          "answer": "Victor Emmanuel II"
        },
        {
          "question": "country that controlled Lombardy-Venetia until 1866 and was ruled by Emperor Franz Joseph I.",
          "answer": "Austrian Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "leader of the Redshirts and the Expedition of a Thousand.",
          "answer": "Giuseppe Garibaldi"
        },
        {
          "question": "noble Prime Minister of Piedmont-Sardinia, who arranged for French intervention.",
          "answer": "Camillo Benso, Count di Cavour"
        },
        {
          "question": "journalist and founder of the secret, pro-unification Young Italy society.",
          "answer": "Giuseppe Mazzini"
        },
        {
          "question": "southern kingdom whose independence was lost at the Siege of Gaeta.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of the Two Sicilies"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Simon Bolivar",
      "prompt": "Name...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "either capital city of the country which was named in his honor in 1825.",
          "answer": [
            "Sucre",
            "La Paz"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "the self-appointed position Bolivar took with his Organic Decree, also taken by Roman republic rulers during emergencies.",
          "answer": "dictator"
        },
        {
          "question": "the Caribbean capital city, from where he wrote the “Letter from Jamaica.”",
          "answer": "Kingston"
        },
        {
          "question": "the “great” country that gained its independence from Spain in 1819 at Boyaca but broke apart in 1831",
          "answer": "Gran Colombia"
        },
        {
          "question": "the July 1822 conference where Bolivar discussed the future of Peru.",
          "answer": "Guayaquil Conference"
        },
        {
          "question": "the Argentinian general who resigned as protector of Peru at that conference.",
          "answer": "Jose de San Martin"
        },
        {
          "question": "the 1813 decree that ordered the murder of Spanish-born civilians in Venezuela.",
          "answer": "Decree of War to the Death"
        },
        {
          "question": "the 1824 battle in Peru that ended Spanish rule in South America.",
          "answer": "Battle of Ayacucho"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Health Care",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Viral disease spread by animal bites, for which Louis Pasteur created a vaccine?",
          "answer": "rabies"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mystic healer employed by Tsar Nicholas II to treat his son’s hemophilia.",
          "answer": "Grigori Yefimovich Rasputin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Research clinic based in Rochester, Minnesota, where Lou Gehrig’s ALS was diagnosed.",
          "answer": "Mayo Clinic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Medical research university in Baltimore, whose hospital employed Ben Carson.",
          "answer": [
            "Johns Hopkins Hospital, University,",
            "School of Medicine"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Physician’s oath to do no harm, based on the writings of a Greek physician.",
          "answer": [
            "Hippocratic Oath",
            "Hippocrates"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Disease spread in New York by the cooking of Mary Mallon.",
          "answer": "typhoid fever"
        },
        {
          "question": "Greek god of medicine, whose snake-entwined rod now symbolizes the practice.",
          "answer": [
            "Asclepius",
            "Rod of Asclepius"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Hungarian doctor whose suggestion that doctors wash their hands led to lowered mortality rates for new mothers.",
          "answer": "Ignaz Semmelweis"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "James Cook",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Continent in Oceania whose eastern edge he discovered.",
          "answer": "Australia"
        },
        {
          "question": "British scientific organization that sent him to map the transit of Venus.",
          "answer": "Royal Society or the President, Council and Fellows of the Royal Society of London for Improving Natural Knowledge"
        },
        {
          "question": "Research vessel on which he sailed for his first voyage, making the aforementioned discoveries.",
          "answer": "HMS Endeavour"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pacific island chain he discovered and died on, two centuries before it became a U.S. state.",
          "answer": "Hawaii"
        },
        {
          "question": "Disease he prevented in his crew by providing them with Vitamin C.",
          "answer": "scurvy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island mapped by Cook that later merged with Labrador as a Canadian province.",
          "answer": "Newfoundland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Canadian river he mapped during the French and Indian War.",
          "answer": "Saint Lawrence River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island where Cook observed the transit of Venus in 1769.",
          "answer": "Tahiti"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Decolonization",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "International organization that oversees the process, increasing the size of its General Assembly as countries become independent.",
          "answer": "United Nations"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term sometimes used to describe countries freed as a result of decolonization, and often used to describe less-affluent countries.",
          "answer": "Third World"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that became independent from Egypt and Britain in 1956, and whose southern portion declared its own independence in 2011.",
          "answer": [
            "Sudan",
            "South Sudan"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that formed in a merger between former British colonies like Singapore, North Borneo, and Sarawak.",
          "answer": "Malaysia"
        },
        {
          "question": "African country that gained its independence after the Mau Mau uprising.",
          "answer": "Kenya"
        },
        {
          "question": "French territory that split into Vietnam, Laos, and Cambodia upon decolonization.",
          "answer": "French Indochina"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that unilaterally declared independence from Britain as a white-governed state under the rule of Ian Smith.",
          "answer": "Southern Rhodesia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colony that, after gaining independence, spiraled into a civil war between the MPLA and UNITA.",
          "answer": "Angola"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Canada",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "French-speaking province, home to a movement seeking independence from Canada.",
          "answer": "Qu´ebec"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city where the 2014 Parliament Hill shooting took place.",
          "answer": "Ottawa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Most populous city, once governed by mayor Rob Ford.",
          "answer": "Toronto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Surname of Prime Ministers Pierre and Justin.",
          "answer": "Trudeau"
        },
        {
          "question": "1917 disaster that destroyed a Nova Scotian port and killed thousands.",
          "answer": "Halifax explosion or equivalents"
        },
        {
          "question": "Western oil-producing province that suffered the Fort McMurray wildfire in 2016.",
          "answer": "Alberta"
        },
        {
          "question": "Flat terrace overlooking the St. Lawrence River where opposing generals, Wolfe and Montcalm, died in a 1759 battle.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Plains of Abraham"
        },
        {
          "question": "Canadian Prime Minister who won a Nobel for negotiating an end to the Suez Canal crisis.",
          "answer": "Lester Pearson"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Assassination of Franz Ferdinand",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Global war it sparked.",
          "answer": [
            "World War I or the Great War",
            "the War to End All Wars"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Twenty-year-old Serbian assassin.",
          "answer": "Gavrilo Princip"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern-day Bosnian city in which it took place.",
          "answer": "Sarajevo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colorfully named Serbian secret society that organized the attack.",
          "answer": [
            "Black Hand",
            "Unification",
            "Death"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country from which Franz Ferdinand was heir apparent, and which controlled the Serbian territory.",
          "answer": "Austria-Hungary"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wife of Franz Ferdinand who was also killed in the attack.",
          "answer": [
            "Sophie von Chotkow, Duchess of Hohenberg",
            "either underlined portion"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Poison that failed to kill bomber Nedejlko Cabrinovic [neh-dyell-koh cah-brin-oh-vitch] after he jumped into a shallow river.",
          "answer": "cyanide pill"
        },
        {
          "question": "Serbian teacher who recruited the assassins and was hanged in 1915.",
          "answer": "Danilo Ili´c"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Battle of Stalingrad",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "War in which the battle took place.",
          "answer": "World War II"
        },
        {
          "question": "River on which Stalingrad lies, and which took the Germans three months to reach after starting the battle.",
          "answer": "Volga River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mountain range crossed by the German Army Group A to attack Baku, while Army Group B secured that river.",
          "answer": "Caucasus Mountains"
        },
        {
          "question": "Strategic resource sought by the Nazis in Case Blue, which attacked that mountain range.",
          "answer": "oil"
        },
        {
          "question": "Codename of the Soviet operation to encircle the enemy in Stalingrad, launched in November.",
          "answer": "Operation Uranus"
        },
        {
          "question": "German commander of the Sixth Army who surrendered to the Soviets, despite Hitler’s expectation.",
          "answer": "Friedrich von Paulus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Apartment building in central Stalingrad held by the Soviets for two grueling months.",
          "answer": "Pavlov’s House"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tallest statue in Europe, built in 1967 to commemorate the battle.",
          "answer": "The Motherland Calls"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ottoman Empire",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country with capital Ankara that was borne out of the fallen empire.",
          "answer": "Turkey"
        },
        {
          "question": "Secular founder of that country who fought in World War I.",
          "answer": [
            "Mustafa Kemal Ataturk",
            "either",
            "both names"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle where that founder defended the Dardanelles against a British amphibious attack, a major Ottoman victory.",
          "answer": "Battle of Gallipoli"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that gained its independence from the Ottomans in 1832 after fighting in Athens.",
          "answer": "Greece"
        },
        {
          "question": "Elite Ottoman infantrymen who were kidnapped as young boys and forcibly converted to Islam.",
          "answer": "janissary"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ethnic group subjected to a genocide by the Ottomans during World War I.",
          "answer": "Armenians"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian tsar who fought the Pruth River Campaign against the Ottomans.",
          "answer": [
            "Peter the Great",
            "Peter I"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Mayans",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "European country whose conquistadors fought the Mayans on the Yucatan Peninsula.",
          "answer": [
            "Spain",
            "Spanish Empire"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Concept that the Mayans represented with dots and lines in a base 20 system.",
          "answer": [
            "numbers",
            "Mayan numerals",
            "anything related to mathematics"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of system represented by the Mayan Long Count, which assigned slightly over 394 years to a Baktun.",
          "answer": "Mayan calendar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country home to the classical Mayan city of Tikal where modern Mayan peoples were involved in a decades-long civil war.",
          "answer": "Guatemala"
        },
        {
          "question": "Large Mayan city that is home to the step pyramid of El Castillo and the Temple of Kukulcan.",
          "answer": "Chichen Itza"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mayan text in the Quiche [kee-chay] language that tells of the mythological Hero Twins.",
          "answer": "Popul Vuh or Popul Wuj"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mayan ruler of Palenque [pah-len-kay] for 68 years, known as the Great.",
          "answer": [
            "Pacal the Great or K’inich Janaab Pakal I",
            "8 Ahau",
            "Sun Shield"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mayan city, ruled by 18 Rabbit and Smoke Imix, that was the chief rival of Quirigua.",
          "answer": "Copan"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Spanish Civil War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Fascist generalissimo who won the war.",
          "answer": "Francisco Franco"
        },
        {
          "question": "Basque town whose 1937 bombing was depicted by Pablo Picasso.",
          "answer": "Guernica"
        },
        {
          "question": "Arm of the Luftwaffe that was sent to aid the fascists.",
          "answer": "Condor Legion"
        },
        {
          "question": "US President who named an International Brigade that fought in the war.",
          "answer": "Abraham Lincoln Brigade"
        },
        {
          "question": "North African protectorate where an uprising began the war, and where the Rif War was also fought.",
          "answer": "Spanish Morocco"
        },
        {
          "question": "Force of sympathizers that Emile Mola claimed would help him undermine Madrid’s defenses.",
          "answer": "Fifth Column or Quinta Columna"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nationalist leader of the Falange whose execution sparked great outrage during the war.",
          "answer": "Jose Antonio Primo de Rivera"
        },
        {
          "question": "River east of Madrid that was crossed by Nationalists in February 1937, though the heavy fighting failed to break the Republican lines.",
          "answer": "Battle of Jarama"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Erie Canal",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital of New York that was one of the endpoints of the canal.",
          "answer": "Albany"
        },
        {
          "question": "Other endpoint of the canal, the city where President McKinley was shot.",
          "answer": "Buffalo"
        },
        {
          "question": "River that connects the canal to New York harbor.",
          "answer": "Hudson River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Escarpment where construction was briefly slowed; it is home to a massive waterfall of the same name on the Canada/US border.",
          "answer": "Niagara Escarpment and/or Falls"
        },
        {
          "question": "Aztec leader who names a marsh in the Finger Lakes where canal workers often caught “swamp fever.”",
          "answer": "Montezuma Marsh"
        },
        {
          "question": "New York governor who oversaw construction of the canal, which became known as his “ditch.”",
          "answer": "DeWitt Clinton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Author of the preamble to the Constitution who chaired the Erie Canal Commission.",
          "answer": "Gouverneur Morris"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ceremonial action taken at the completion of the canal to mark the “Wedding of the Waters;” description acceptable.",
          "answer": [
            "water taken from Lake Erie was poured into New York Harbor",
            "the reverse order"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Worldly Landmarks",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "13,000-mile-long fortification, mostly built during the Ming Dynasty to keep out the Mongols.",
          "answer": "Great Wall of China"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mausoleum built in the 17th century for the wife of Shah Jahan.",
          "answer": "Taj Mahal"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where slave labor was used to build the Burj Khalifa, the tallest building in the world.",
          "answer": "Dubai"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where the first shinkansen, or bullet train, opened in 1964.",
          "answer": "Japan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Railroad that connects Moscow and Vladivostok and was finished in 1916.",
          "answer": "Trans-Siberian Railway"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dam on the Yangtze River that was planned for much of the 20th century, the largest dam in China.",
          "answer": "Three Gorges Dam"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where foreign banks were built in the early 20th century in the International Settlement, a region now known as the Bund.",
          "answer": "Shanghai"
        },
        {
          "question": "City whose tallest buildings include a tower at One Raffles Place.",
          "answer": "Singapore"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Apartheid",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "African country where white politicians created apartheid.",
          "answer": "South Africa"
        },
        {
          "question": "First black president of that country, being elected after years in prison fighting apartheid.",
          "answer": "Nelson Mandela"
        },
        {
          "question": "Trial in which that man was sentenced to life in prison in 1964.",
          "answer": "Rivonia Trial"
        },
        {
          "question": "Largest city in which apartheid was carried out; the aforementioned trial was named for a suburb of this city.",
          "answer": "Johannesburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Language from which the word “apartheid” is derived; it and English were required to be taught in schools.",
          "answer": "Afrikaans"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sport played by the Springboks, whose 1981 Test tour of New Zealand was heavily protested.",
          "answer": "rugby union"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last apartheid-era President, a white politician who also ended his country’s nuclear weapons program.",
          "answer": "Frederik Willem de Klerk"
        },
        {
          "question": "1960 massacre in which 69 protesters against the pass laws were killed by police.",
          "answer": "Sharpeville Massacre"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Revolutionary calendar month in which it occurred.",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country she led as Prime Minister.",
          "answer": "India"
        },
        {
          "question": "Father of Indira Gandhi, the first Prime Minister of their country.",
          "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru"
        },
        {
          "question": "Military operation that Gandhi authorized in Smiling Buddha; American examples took place at Bikini Atoll.",
          "answer": [
            "nuclear weapons test",
            "equivalents"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion followed by the bodyguards who assassinated her in 1984.",
          "answer": "Sikhism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Holy site in Amritsar where she ordered a deadly raid, enraging those bodyguards.",
          "answer": "Golden Temple of Amritsar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name for the 21-month period in the mid-70s when Gandhi suspended elections and violated civil liberties.",
          "answer": "The Emergency"
        },
        {
          "question": "Medical procedure forced on millions of people during that time period, meant to curb population growth.",
          "answer": [
            "forced sterilization",
            "word forms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Period of agricultural change, championed by Norman Borlaug, that Gandhi fostered during the fourth Five Year Plan.",
          "answer": "Green Revolution"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Aztecs",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern country where the Aztec Empire was located.",
          "answer": "Mexico"
        },
        {
          "question": "Spanish conquistador whose expedition to the Americas led to the collapse of the Aztec Empire.",
          "answer": "Hernan Cortes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital of the Aztec Empire from 1325 until its 1521 capture by the Spanish.",
          "answer": "Tenochtitlan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Aztec ruler who first made contact with Europeans, but was killed when Spanish invaders took over the capital.",
          "answer": "Montezuma II or Moctezuma II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Agricultural method that used interwoven reeds beneath the surface of lakes to create artificial “fences.”",
          "answer": [
            "floating gardens",
            "chinampas"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Language historically spoken by the Aztecs, which is still spoken by some of their descendants today.",
          "answer": "Nahuatl , but be lenient"
        },
        {
          "question": "Aztec slave who acted as an interpreter; she has historically been seen as a traitor to the Aztecs.",
          "answer": "La Malinche"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ritual wars fought between the Aztec Triple Alliance and its enemies from the mid-1450s until the arrival of the Spanish.",
          "answer": "Flowery wars"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Colonial Virginia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Pre-1699 capital of Virginia, the first permanent English settlement in the Americas.",
          "answer": "Jamestown"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crop that was introduced to Virginia by John Rolfe and popularized in England by Sir Walter Raleigh.",
          "answer": "tobacco"
        },
        {
          "question": "First representative assembly in America, formed in 1642 in Virginia.",
          "answer": "House of Burgesses"
        },
        {
          "question": "Native group that met the first English colonists in Virginia; the leader of this group, as with Pocahontas’ father, shares the same name.",
          "answer": "Powhatan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Englishman who was legendarily saved by Pocahontas and declared “He who will not work, shall not eat.”",
          "answer": "John Smith"
        },
        {
          "question": "Armed rebellion by settlers against Governor William Berkeley in 1676; it included the burning of the capital.",
          "answer": "Bacon’s Rebellion"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nearby Virginia city that became capital of the colony after a burning of the previous capital in 1698.",
          "answer": "Williamsburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colonial governor who names a 1774 war and a 1775 proclamation that freed slaves who joined the British army.",
          "answer": [
            "John Murray, Lord Dunmore",
            "either",
            "both",
            "Lord Dunmore’s War",
            "Dunmore’s Proclamation"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Joan of Arc",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Home country of Joan, for whom she opposed England in the Hundred Years’ War.",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "City whose siege she helped lift, earning her the nickname “Maid of” this place.",
          "answer": "Orleans"
        },
        {
          "question": "Method by which she was executed for heresy.",
          "answer": "burning at the stake"
        },
        {
          "question": "Additional charge added to Joan’s crimes, as heresy alone was not punishable by death.",
          "answer": [
            "cross-dressing",
            "equivalents, such as wearing male clothing"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City to which she brought the Dauphin Charles to be crowned King in 1429.",
          "answer": "Reims , but be lenient"
        },
        {
          "question": "Either the pope who cleared Joan’s name in 1455 or the pope who named her a saint in 1920.",
          "answer": [
            "Callixtus III",
            "Benedict XV"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Any one of the three saints who appeared to Joan in her vision; one was a 4th century AD martyr from Alexandria.",
          "answer": "Saints Catherine of Alexandria, Michael, and/or Margaret of Antioch"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where Joan was captured in 1430 by the English.",
          "answer": "Compiegne"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Revolutionaries",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country where Yukio Mishima committed seppuku in 1970 after a failed coup d’etat.",
          "answer": "Japan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose National Army was joined by Lakshmi Sahgal, who fought for independence from Britain.",
          "answer": "India"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where Metis leader and revolutionary Louis Riel fought in the Red River Rebellion.",
          "answer": "Canada"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose 1791-1804 revolution was led by ex-slave Toussaint L’Ouverture.",
          "answer": "Haiti"
        },
        {
          "question": "African country where Ahmed Ben Bella fought for independence from the French.",
          "answer": "Algeria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who led Philippine forces against Spain and the US; in 1899, he became the first President of the Philippines.",
          "answer": "Emilio Aguinaldo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Non-violent group in Nazi Germany that included the executed student Sophie Scholl.",
          "answer": "White Rose or Die Weisse Rose"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rvolutionary who called for land reforms in Mexico under the Plan de Ayala.",
          "answer": "Emiliano Zapata"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Oil",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Body of water that names a 1991 war triggered by Saddam Hussein’s invasion of oil-rich Kuwait.",
          "answer": "Persian Gulf War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country led by Hussein that began that war.",
          "answer": "Iraq"
        },
        {
          "question": "Only charter member of OPEC from South America, led from Caracas.",
          "answer": "Venezuela"
        },
        {
          "question": "SouthAmericancountrywherethestate-ownedoilcompany,Petrobras,wasfoundtobecontroversially corrupt in Operation Car Wash.",
          "answer": "Brazil"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where oil money fueled the development of Dubai.",
          "answer": "United Arab Emirates or UAE"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose Baku oil fields were targeted by Joseph Stalin.",
          "answer": "Azerbaijan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Libyan colonel and dictator who may have hired Carlos “the Jackal” to kidnap OPEC ministers in 1975.",
          "answer": "Muammar al-Gaddafi"
        },
        {
          "question": "South American country where the Stabroek oil field marked its first production in December 2019.",
          "answer": "Guyana"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "League of Nations",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "War whose bloodshed inspired a US President to recommend the League.",
          "answer": "World War I"
        },
        {
          "question": "US President who pushed for the League in his Fourteen Points.",
          "answer": "Woodrow Wilson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Swiss city where the League was headquartered and where Conventions against war crimes were signed.",
          "answer": "Geneva"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region re-militarized by Nazi Germany in March 1936, an action essentially ignored by the League.",
          "answer": [
            "Rhineland",
            "descriptions of the land along the Rhine River"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country led by Haile [“highly”] Selassie, who spoke at the League after Italy invaded this country in 1936.",
          "answer": [
            "Ethiopia",
            "Abyssinia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that retained the Aland Islands in 1921, despite Sweden’s claims.",
          "answer": "Finland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Massachusetts Senator who kept the US out of the League as Chair of the Senate Committee on Foreign Relations.",
          "answer": "Henry Cabot Lodge"
        },
        {
          "question": "Greek island in the Ionian Sea that was bombed by the Italians in 1923, an early example of the League’s weakness.",
          "answer": "Corfu incident"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Jamestown",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Colony and future state of which it was the capital.",
          "answer": "Virginia"
        },
        {
          "question": "City, originally called the Middle Plantation, that replaced it as capital in 1699.",
          "answer": "Williamsburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cash crop, cultivated by John Rolfe, that helped save the colony.",
          "answer": "tobacco"
        },
        {
          "question": "Explorer and governor who told the first settlers “he that will not work, shall not eat.”",
          "answer": "John Smith"
        },
        {
          "question": "1676 rebellion against William Berkeley in which Jamestown was burned.",
          "answer": "Bacon’s Rebellion"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name given to the harsh winter of 1609 that resulted in the death of 90% of Jamestown’s population.",
          "answer": "Starving Time"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nearby native confederacy that clashed with Jamestown; Pocahontas was a member of these people.",
          "answer": "Powhatan Confederacy"
        },
        {
          "question": "English naval officer who kidnapped Pocahontas and later used Jamestown as his base of operations for raids against Acadia.",
          "answer": "Samuel Argall"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Italian Unification",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Century in which the Risorgimento was conducted.",
          "answer": [
            "19th century",
            "1800s"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City that became the capital of unified Italy.",
          "answer": "Rome"
        },
        {
          "question": "Position held by Pius IX [ninth], who opposed the efforts.",
          "answer": [
            "Pope",
            "Bishop of Rome"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Kingdom, based on an island off the Italian coast, where Francis II was deposed in the Expedition of the Thousand.",
          "answer": [
            "Kingdom of Sicily",
            "Kingdom of the Two Sicilies"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "General who led the Expedition of the Thousand and whose followers wore red shirts.",
          "answer": "Giuseppe Garibaldi"
        },
        {
          "question": "First king of unified Italy, who maintained the regnal number “the Second” despite leading a new country.",
          "answer": "Victor Emmanuel II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kingdom ruled by that man prior to unification, explaining why he kept “the Second” in his title.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Piedmont-Sardinia"
        },
        {
          "question": "River where the redshirts of the Matese Legion prevented Francis II’s troops from reaching Naples.",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Volturno",
            "Volturnus"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Genghis Khan",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Animal whose Mongol riders used a special compound bow to decimate Genghis’ enemies.",
          "answer": "horse"
        },
        {
          "question": "Portable, round-tent his army used on campaigns.",
          "answer": [
            "yurts",
            "gers"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Indian river where he defeated Jalal al-Din and where a Bronze Age civilization flourished 4,000 years ago.",
          "answer": [
            "Indus River",
            "Indus River Valley Civilization"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Script he adopted for his empire, an old version of a script currently used by a namesake minority Muslim ethnicity in Xinjiang [shin-jee’ahng].",
          "answer": "Uyghur script"
        },
        {
          "question": "Slavic confederation ruled by the Ruriks that he invaded in 1223.",
          "answer": "Kievan Rus’"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who succeeded him as Great Khan, his third son.",
          "answer": "Ogedei Khan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Secret law code he issued to control his empire.",
          "answer": "Yassa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Grand Empress, his first wife, whose kidnapping by the Three Merkits may have started his military campaigns.",
          "answer": "Borte"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Irish Republican Army",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country from which the IRA believes Ireland should be independent.",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland or U.K.",
            "Great Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Irish political party whose name means “We ourselves” that often associated with the IRA.",
          "answer": "Sinn F´ein"
        },
        {
          "question": "Northernmost of the four provinces of Ireland, a Protestant-majority region where loyalists have fought the IRA.",
          "answer": "Ulster"
        },
        {
          "question": "Northern Irish city where the IRA fought the Battle of St. Matthews, and where the Good Friday Agreement was signed.",
          "answer": "Belfast"
        },
        {
          "question": "IRA member who led and died in a 1981 hunger strike in the Maze prison.",
          "answer": "Bobby Gerald Sands"
        },
        {
          "question": "IRA attempt by Patrick Magee to kill Margaret Thatcher.",
          "answer": "Brighton Hotel bombing"
        },
        {
          "question": "Guerrilla warfare strategist for the IRA who, with Arthur Griffith, signed the Anglo-Irish Treaty.",
          "answer": "Michael Collins"
        },
        {
          "question": "Unit, founded by that strategist and commanded by Mick McDonnell, that assassinated members of the Cairo Gang.",
          "answer": [
            "the Squad",
            "the Twelve Apostles"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Peter the Great",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country he led as tsar.",
          "answer": "Russian Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "European sea that he sought to control by building the city of Saint Petersburg.",
          "answer": "Baltic Sea"
        },
        {
          "question": "Members of the aristocracy who were forced to pay taxes on their beards.",
          "answer": "boyars"
        },
        {
          "question": "1698 uprising of infantrymen that was brutally put down by Peter.",
          "answer": "Streltsy uprising"
        },
        {
          "question": "Civil service hierarchy introduced by Peter in 1722 to create a bureaucracy devoted to him.",
          "answer": "Table of Ranks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Iranian dynasty that Peter fought in 1722-23; it collapsed a decade later.",
          "answer": "Safavid dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Anti-Ottoman alliance he strengthened with his Grand Embassy; it dissolved with the Treaty of Karlowitz in 1699.",
          "answer": "Holy League"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cossack commander whose rebellion against Peter, the supposed Antichrist, sputtered after his 1708 death.",
          "answer": [
            "Kondraty Bulavin",
            "Bulavin Rebellion"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "20th Century Brazil",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Planned city built to be Brazil’s new capital in the 1950s.",
          "answer": "Brasilia"
        },
        {
          "question": "City replaced as capital in 1960.",
          "answer": "Rio de Janeiro"
        },
        {
          "question": "revolution.",
          "answer": [
            "coffee and milk",
            "caf´e com leite"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "State, named for Brazil’s most populous city, that dominated that two-state political system.",
          "answer": "Sao Paulo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Other, larger state in that two-state political system.",
          "answer": "Minas Gerais"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dictator who committed suicide in 1954 after ordering a hit on Carlos Lacerda.",
          "answer": "Getulio Vargas"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who authorized the new capital and led Brazil from 1956 to 1961.",
          "answer": "Juscelino Kubitschek"
        },
        {
          "question": "President ousted in the coup of 1930, which also prevented President-elect Ju´lio Prestes from taking power.",
          "answer": "Washington Luiz"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Candle Making",
      "prompt": "Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "English capital where the Tallow Chandlers Company was located.",
          "answer": "London, England, United Kingdom"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who is celebrated on Candlemas as well as December 25th, his birthday.",
          "answer": "Jesus Christ"
        },
        {
          "question": "Natural material used for candles that comes from honey making insects.",
          "answer": "Beeswax"
        },
        {
          "question": "Aquatic mammal hunted to near extinction for the candle-making material harvested from its head cavity.",
          "answer": "Sperm whale"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of wax made from the material that James Young distilled from coal and oil shales.",
          "answer": "Paraffin Wax"
        },
        {
          "question": "1840 London event involving a woman wearing a William Dyce-designed dress, during which loyal households burned candles.",
          "answer": [
            "Wedding of Queen Victoria and Prince Albert",
            "Marriage in place of \"Wedding\""
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Upstate New York city named for a Sicilian city known for candle manufacturing.",
          "answer": "Syracuse"
        },
        {
          "question": "Largest candle-maker in the UK who pioneered steam distillation in manufacturing.",
          "answer": "Price's Patent Candles 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 1"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Great Smoky Mountains",
      "prompt": "Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Long hiking trail completed in 1937, 70 miles of which are in the Great Smoky Mountains National Park.",
          "answer": "Appalachian Trail"
        },
        {
          "question": "UN organization that designated the region a World Heritage site in 1983.",
          "answer": "UNESCO or United Nations Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization"
        },
        {
          "question": "New Deal president who opened the park in 1934.",
          "answer": [
            "Franklin Delano Roosevelt",
            "FDR,"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Side most Great Smoky Mountains residents supported in the Civil War despite being in the South.",
          "answer": [
            "Union",
            "answers indicating the U.S. Federal government"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Forced relocation march that Great Smoky Mountain Cherokee residents underwent.",
          "answer": "Trail of Tears"
        },
        {
          "question": "Conquistador, the first European to cross the Mississippi, who spent time in the Chiaha village.",
          "answer": "Hernando de Soto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Culture which lived in the Mountains and built mound cities like Cahokia.",
          "answer": "Mississippian Culture"
        },
        {
          "question": "Highest point in the Mountains nicknamed for North Carolina's \"Prince of Politicians.\"",
          "answer": "Clingmans Dome 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 3"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Bolivia",
      "prompt": "Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Co-capital with Sucre since 1898.",
          "answer": "La Paz"
        },
        {
          "question": "Bordering Andean nation with which Bolivia united in 1836, angering Chile and Argentina.",
          "answer": "Peru"
        },
        {
          "question": "War which led to Bolivia losing access to the title ocean.",
          "answer": "War of the Pacific"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who fled in 2019 at the request of the military due to electoral irregularities.",
          "answer": "Evo Morales"
        },
        {
          "question": "Oil company owned by Brazil which had its facilities occupied by government forces.",
          "answer": [
            "Petrobras",
            "Petróleo Brasiliero S.A.",
            "Brazilian Petroleum Corporation"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Silver mining hub of Colonial Spain, an Andean city in Central Bolivia.",
          "answer": "Potosí"
        },
        {
          "question": "Left-wing politician who was elected president in 2020.",
          "answer": "Luis \"Lucho\" Arce"
        },
        {
          "question": "Aymara peasant who led a 1781 revolt and remains a hero for many indigenous people.",
          "answer": "Tupac Katari 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 4"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "20th Century Finland",
      "prompt": "Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Season which names a war between Finland and the USSR, stalemated in part due to cold weather.",
          "answer": "Winter War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Finnish capital which hosted the 1952 Winter Olympics.",
          "answer": "Helsinki"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian tsar who lost control of Finland after the Bolshevik Revolution destabilized his regime.",
          "answer": "Nicholas II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nearby Baltic nation that was invaded by Finnish forces in the Kinship Wars.",
          "answer": "Estonia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Historical region of southeastern Finland that it was forced to cede to the USSR in 1940.",
          "answer": "Karelia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Red Army nickname for Finnish soldier Simo Häyhä [[HIGH-hah]] for his success as a sniper.",
          "answer": "The White Death"
        },
        {
          "question": "War fought by the Finns and Nazis in an effort to regain Finnish territory from the Soviets during World War Two.",
          "answer": "Continuation War"
        },
        {
          "question": "President of Finland during the Interim Peace, who was sentenced to ten years in prison for his involvement with the Axis.",
          "answer": "Risto Ryti ] 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 2"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Árpád Dynasty",
      "prompt": "Name the…...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country the Árpád Dynasty ruled with its modern capital at Budapest.",
          "answer": "Hungary"
        },
        {
          "question": "Along with the Tisza, Sava and Drava, this “Blue” river is one of the four Árpád stripes.",
          "answer": "Danube River"
        },
        {
          "question": "This king of the Premyslids succeeded the final Árpád ruler and shares his name with a “good” king in a Christmas carol.",
          "answer": [
            "Wenceslaus III",
            "Ladislaus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Saintly first king of the Árpáds who shares his name with the first Christian martyr.",
          "answer": "Saint Stephen I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group that devastated Árpád rule, including at Mohi, led by Subutai.",
          "answer": [
            "Mongols",
            "Golden Horde"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "955 Battle before the dynasty began in which Otto the Great defeated Lel and Sur.",
          "answer": "Battle of Lechfeld"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last king of the Árpáds, a man called “the Venetian.”",
          "answer": "Andrew III"
        },
        {
          "question": "Scottish clan in the parish of Dryman that claims descent from George, the son of an Árpád king.",
          "answer": "Drummond 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 3"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Uruguayan Independence",
      "prompt": "Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital of Uruguay, occupied by Britain in 1807.",
          "answer": "Montevideo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Portuguese-speaking country, ruled by Pedro I, that claimed the Cisplatine Province, now Uruguay.",
          "answer": "Empire of Brazil"
        },
        {
          "question": "Estuary of the Uruguay and Paraná Rivers, on the border of Argentina and Uruguay.",
          "answer": "Rio de la Plata"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the Italian legion, a \"Hero of the Two Worlds\" who helped Uruguay and helped unify Italy.",
          "answer": "Giuseppe Maria Garibaldi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Opponent party of the Colorados, headed by President Manuel Oribe.",
          "answer": [
            "Blancos",
            "Whites"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "War in which Uruguay teamed up with Argentina to beat Francisco Solano López.",
          "answer": [
            "Paraguayan War",
            "War of the Triple Alliance"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Argentine dictator who was attacked in the Great War and operated the Mazorca secret police.",
          "answer": "Juan Manuel de Rosas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Father of Uruguay, who beat the Spanish at Las Piedras and formed the League of the Free Peoples.",
          "answer": "José Gervasio Artigas 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 3"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Over the course of Abercrombie & Fitch's history, name the......",
      "prompt": "Name the over the course of abercrombie & fitch's history, name the.........",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Densely populated core borough of New York City in which it first started.",
          "answer": "Manhattan"
        },
        {
          "question": "American aviator whom they outfitted for his flight on the Spirit of St. Louis.",
          "answer": "Charles Lindbergh"
        },
        {
          "question": "NYC Avenue on which the store was located, today identified with the advertising industry.",
          "answer": "Madison Avenue"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sales method pioneered by Sears that they used to expand their market beyond stores.",
          "answer": [
            "Mail order",
            "Catalogue,",
            "descriptive answers indicating receiving deliveries by mail"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Chinese rummy-like tile game it introduced to US audiences.",
          "answer": "Mahjong"
        },
        {
          "question": "Northern Mariana Island where they were accused of having sweatshops.",
          "answer": "Saipan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Star of Man’s Favorite Sport, one of the first product placement films, nominated for an Oscar for Giant.",
          "answer": "Rock Hudson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Oldest department store in the US which William Humphreys headed before coming to Abercrombie & Fitch.",
          "answer": "Lord & Taylor 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Finals"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Rivers",
      "prompt": "Given the clue, name the river which...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Is the largest in the world by discharge volume, and was opened to steamboat travel by Pedro II of Brazil.",
          "answer": "Amazon River or Rio Amazonas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is considered the flowing hair of the god Shiva and was involved in a 1951 water sharing dispute between India and Bangladesh.",
          "answer": [
            "Ganges River or Ganga",
            "Padma"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Is a colorfully-named river of China that was strategically flooded by rival nations during the Warring States period.",
          "answer": "Yellow River or Huáng hé"
        },
        {
          "question": "Turned black due to the ink from texts once contained in Baghdad's House of Wisdom.",
          "answer": "Tigris River or Dijlah"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was explored by Henry Morton Stanley and now names two African countries whose capitals sit across the river from each other.",
          "answer": "Congo River or Zaire River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site where Peter the Great determined to build his western-facing capital of St. Petersburg.",
          "answer": "Neva River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of a 20th century economic miracle in Seoul, South Korea.",
          "answer": "Han River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Caused a blackout in Southern Brazil and Paraguay after transmission lines at its Itaipu Dam failed.",
          "answer": "Paraná River 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 1"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Reign of Suleiman the Magnificent",
      "prompt": "Concerning the reign of Suleiman the Magnificent, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire which he ruled.",
          "answer": [
            "Ottoman Empire or Ottomans",
            "Ottoman Turks"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Austrian capital city he besieged in 1529.",
          "answer": "Vienna or Wien"
        },
        {
          "question": "Serbian capital he razed in 1521.",
          "answer": [
            "Belgrade",
            "Beograd"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Island off the coast of Anatolia ruled by the Knights of St. John which he captured.",
          "answer": [
            "Rhodes",
            "Rodos"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Persian dynasty against which he conducted a prolonged campaign and later negotiated the Peace of Amasya [[ah-MAH-syah]].",
          "answer": "Safavid ] Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "European kingdom which entered an \"unholy\" alliance with Suleiman.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of France or Royaume de France"
        },
        {
          "question": "1526 battle in which Suleiman's forces devastated the armies of Hungary, Bohemia, and Bavaria.",
          "answer": "Battle of Mohács ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Father of Suleiman known as \"the Grim\" who annexed the Mamluk sultanate.",
          "answer": [
            "Selim I or Selim the Grim",
            "or Selim the Resolute",
            "or Selim the Mean 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 6"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This modern-day country was the birthplace of an order founded by Stephen Hunting and spread by St. Bernard, the Cistercians. During a massacre of heretics in this country, the order \"kill them (20 pts)",
        "all- God will know his own\" was given. After the death of Peter of Castelnau in this country, Innocent III ordered a campaign against the gnostic (10 pts)",
        "Cathars of this country, the Albigensian crusade. For 10 points, name this country, home to the Cluny Abbey in its Aquitaine region."
      ],
      "answer": "France"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A popular hippie song said to \"wear a flower in your hair\" when travelling to this city. This city suffered the \"White Night (20 pts)",
        "riots\" following the acquittal of a former supervisor who used the \"twinkie defense\" after killing George Moscone and (10 pts)",
        "Harvey Milk. In 1989, this city was hit by an earthquake while hosting a World Series game. For 10 points, name this city where historic districts such as The Mission and Haight-Ashbury are located."
      ],
      "answer": "San Francisco"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This editor of the newspaper Iskra wrote about the “burning questions of our movement” in a pamphlet titled What Is to Be Done? As leader, he instituted the moderate New Economic Policy. He issued a series of (20 pts)",
        "“April Theses” after riding through Germany on a sealed train. This man, for whom (10 pts)",
        "St. Petersburg was renamed in 1924, brought his country out of World War I with the Treaty of Brest-Litovsk. For 10 points, name this leader of the Bolsheviks."
      ],
      "answer": "Vladimir Lenin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Police in this city fought with demonstrators at Admiralty, Causeway Bay, and Mong Kok during protests that were centered at the Connaught and Harcourt Road area. Those protests in this city, grew out of the (20 pts)",
        "Occupy Central movement founded by Joshua Wong and Lester Shum. (10 pts)",
        "For 10 points, name this city where the \"Umbrella Revolution\" movement seeks to accelerate democratization following a 2014 decision on electoral reforms from China, which has governed this city since 1997."
      ],
      "answer": "Hong Kong"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This westward-facing building is the largest in a similarly-named city that also houses\nthe Bayon, the Ta Prohm, and artificial lakes called baray. Its cross-shaped Grand Terrace\nstands in front of five towers laid out like the dots on a die. (20 pts) ",
        "Suryavarman II began\nconstruction on this site, which was first dedicated to (10 pts) ",
        "Vishnu before it became Buddhist.\nFor 10 points, name this tallest temple built by the Khmer empire, which appears in white on the\nnational flag of Cambodia."
      ],
      "answer": "Angkor Wat"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country celebrates the two-week-long Dashain (DAH-shayn) festival every fall. In the 1980s, this country took in over a hundred thousand Lhotshampa (LOTE-sahm-pa) refugees. This country has been subject to unrest in the (20 pts)",
        "Terai (teh-RYE) region, which it shares with India, and it was the only officially (10 pts)",
        "Hindu country in the world until its monarchy was abolished in 2008. For 10 points, name this Himalayan country governed from Kathmandu."
      ],
      "answer": "Nepal"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country suffered through a succession crisis when Sebastian I disappeared at the Battle of the Three Kings. For much of its history, this country was led by rulers from the House of (20 pts)",
        "Aviz. Under leaders like Prince Henry the Navigator, this country patronized expeditions that discovered the Madeira Islands, found (10 pts)",
        "Brazil, and circumnavigated the earth for the first time. For 10 points, name this Iberian home of Pedro Cabral and Ferdinand Magellan."
      ],
      "answer": "Portugal"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A society along this non-European river made seals showing a seated horned god surrounded by animals and a bitumen-lined Great Bath. Sites along this river include the early port of (20 pts)",
        "Lothal, a site whose name means \"mound of death,\" Mohenjo-Daro, and the mudbrick city of (10 pts)",
        "Harappa, built around 2000 BCE before Aryan peoples arrived in the area. Alexander the Great turned back shortly after crossing, for 10 points, what river that flows south through Pakistan?"
      ],
      "answer": "Indus river"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country’s leaders received a dead dog from Henry the Fowler before the Battle of Riade. This country’s Black Army was founded by the son of John Hunyadi, Matthias Corvinus. Otto the Great stopped this country’s westward expansion at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Lechfield. A member of the Arpad dynasty, (10 pts)",
        "Stephen I, converted this country to Christianity, and it was formed by the Magyar tribe. For 10 points, name this country with capital at Budapest."
      ],
      "answer": "Hungary"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The world’s largest rubber plantation is in this country’s city of Harbel. Samuel Doe was overthrown and executed by the rebel group National Patriotic Front, led by Charles (20 pts)",
        "Taylor. The American Colonization Society founded this country as a home for freed slaves; with Ethiopia, it was one of two (10 pts)",
        "African countries never to be colonized by European powers. For ten points, name this African country that honored a U.S. President with the name of its capital, Monrovia."
      ],
      "answer": "Liberia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country defeated Count von Bennigsen at the Battle of Friedland, leading to a treaty signed on a raft in the Neman River, the Treaty of (20 pts)",
        "Tilsit. This country burned down a capital city after the Battle of Borodino, then retreated from “General Winter” and the (10 pts)",
        "Cossacks when it couldn’t defeat Alexander I’s Russia. For ten points, name this country whose Grande Arm´ee was led by Napoleon Bonaparte."
      ],
      "answer": "France"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city’s Iberville Projects were built on the site of its red-light district, which was shut down in 1917. This city’s oldest neighborhood, just east of Storyville, features buildings with distinctive (20 pts)",
        "ironwork galleries and balconies. Another neighborhood in this city, which lies downriver of the Industrial Canal, suffered (10 pts)",
        "catastrophic damage in a 2005 storm that breached the levees of the Mississippi River. The Lower Ninth Ward and the French Quarter are in, for ten points, what Louisiana city?"
      ],
      "answer": "New Orleans, Louisiana"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A U.N. Secretary General from this country died in a 1961 plane crash en route to peace talks over conflict in the Congo Crisis. Another leader from this country was a prime minister (20 pts)",
        "assassinated in 1986 whose main suspect was Christer Pettersson. A king and military general from this nation died at the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Lutzen and was known as the “Lion of the North”. For ten points, name this Scandinavian country whose leaders included Dag Hammarskjold, Olof Palme, and Gustavus Adolphus."
      ],
      "answer": "Sweden"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Winston Churchill proposed that this country be given Eastern Galicia, including the city of Lvov, in a “Plan B” regarding its proposed border. A line formed by two rivers and ending at (20 pts)",
        "Stettin now forms this country’s western border. The postwar Curzon and (10 pts)",
        "Oder-Neisse [NICE-uh] lines were drawn on either side of, for ten points, what European country which, on September 1, 1939, was invaded by Nazi troops to begin World War II?"
      ],
      "answer": "Poland"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country repelled the forces of Eleftherios Venizelos after they landed at Smyrna, in accordance with the Treaty of (20 pts)",
        "Sevres that divided this country’s immediate predecessor. This country’s independence was guaranteed by the Treaty of Lausanne, and it saw reforms based on the Six Arrows of its first leader, who adopted Latin script, banned (10 pts)",
        "fezzes, and deposed the Sultan. For ten points, name this country, formed from the remnants of the Ottoman Empire by Kemal Ataturk, which has its capital at Ankara."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Turkey"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This nation’s southern border was established by the Treaty of Taif. One city here is completely off-limits to non-practitioners of its state religion, the most influential sect of which in this country is (20 pts)",
        "Wahhabism. Concerns have recently arisen over the spread of the MERS virus among pilgrims in this country during the annual (10 pts)",
        "Hajj. For ten points, name this Middle Eastern kingdom whose capital is Riyadh, home to the two holiest cities of Islam, Medina and Mecca."
      ],
      "answer": "Kingdom of Saudi Arabia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A king of this country formed the International African Association and sent Henry Morton Stanley to explore land for him. This country’s independence movement started after a riot at a performance of the (20 pts)",
        "opera The Mute Girl of Portici. This country signed the Treaty of London, which was dismissed as a “scrap of paper,” leading Britain to enter a war started by the (10 pts)",
        "assassination of Franz Ferdinand after this country’s neutrality was violated. For ten points, name this country that split from the Netherlands with capital at Brussels."
      ],
      "answer": "Belgium"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Gatun Lake was formed during the building of this structure, where William C. Gorgas worked to prevent the spread of yellow fever. Omar (20 pts)",
        "Torrijos negotiated a treaty with Jimmy Carter that transferred this structure to Torrijos’ nation in 1999. This structure, built between (10 pts)",
        "1907 and 1914, includes six locks and is crossed by the Bridge of the Americas. For ten points, name this artificial waterway in Central America that connects the Caribbean Sea to the Pacific Ocean."
      ],
      "answer": "Panama Canal"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Representatives of this city declared “the weak suffer what they must” before destroying the town of Melos. This city won the Battle of Sphacteria, but it was later subjected to the rule of the (20 pts)",
        "Thirty Tyrants after losing the Battle of Aegospotami. This city, which was connected to its port at (10 pts)",
        "Piraeus by the Long Walls, lost its maritime empire after it led a disastrous offensive against Syracuse. For ten points, name this city that launched the Sicilian Expedition during the Second Peloponnesian War against Sparta."
      ],
      "answer": "Athens"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An 1883 Convention for the protection of intellectual property was signed in this city and is still in effect. The Confederation of the Rhine was initially convened in this city. A series of post-World War I treaties reinforcing the (20 pts)",
        "boundaries of defeated nations including the Treaties of Sevres, Trianon, and (10 pts)",
        "Neuilly-sur-Seine were signed in this city, which was also the site of treaties ending the Spanish-American War and the Revolutionary War. For ten points, name this city, the namesake of many treaties and the capital of France."
      ],
      "answer": "Paris"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1624, Fyodor Kotov described the dismantling of this group’s capital, Sarai. One ruler of this group defeated Mamai at the battle of Kalka River; that man, Tokhtamysh, united the (20 pts)",
        "White and Blue sections of this group into a single force. Uzbek Khan was the longest-reigning ruler of this army, which split off from the (10 pts)",
        "Mongol empire after the death of Genghis Khan. For ten points, name this Mongol army, either named for their wealth or for the color of their tents."
      ],
      "answer": "Golden Horde"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One country launched the Mega Rice Project on this island, resulting in the mass drainage of its peat swamps. The southern portion of this island is referred to as (20 pts)",
        "Kalimantan, and the Wallace line separates this island from Sulawesi. The Crocker Range is home to Mount (10 pts)",
        "Kinabalu, its highest point. The Philippines once claimed the province of Sabah on, for ten points, what island divided between Indonesia, Brunei and Malaysia?"
      ],
      "answer": "Borneo"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Hans and Sophie Scholl, part of the White Rose group, were based in this city and executedfortheiranti-NazileafletsduringWorldWarII. (20 pts)",
        "Dachau, thefirstconcentration camp, was located close to this city, and the Nazi Party’s national headquarters, the Brown house, was located at the center of this city. This city was targeted by (10 pts)",
        "Black September in a 1972 incident that occurred while it was hosting the Summer Olympics. For ten points, name this German city, the site of a namesake “Massacre” of Israeli athletes."
      ],
      "answer": "Munich"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) On this island, Venetian settlers built a still-standing series of fortifications in Famagusta. A political movement on this island known as enosis sought to (20 pts)",
        "unite it with another country. In 1960, this island gained its independence from the UK, who still controls a military bases at Akrotiri here. A 1974 invasion of this island led to its partition along the (10 pts)",
        "Green Line. For ten points, name this Mediterranean island, divided into a Greek-speaking southern majority and a self-proclaimed “Turkish Republic” in the north."
      ],
      "answer": "Cyprus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This waterway is named after a kingdom that was absorbed by Portugal in 1914. Upstream of the Boyoma Falls, this river is known as the Lualaba, and a planned dam along its (20 pts)",
        "Inga Falls would be the largest hydroelectric project in the world. A widening of this waterway known as the Malebo Pool has two national capitals along its banks. A set of rapids along this river is named after an explorer who was sought by Henry Morton (10 pts)",
        "Stanley, David Livingstone. The national capitals of Kinshasa and Brazzaville are on the banks of, for ten points, what second-longest river in Africa?"
      ],
      "answer": "Congo River"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One leader of this country created a secret police called the Securitate and was overthrown after protests in Timisoara led to full scale revolution. The Allies bombed this country’s oil fields at (20 pts)",
        "Ploesti to deny Nazi Germany vital fuel. A right-wing group known as the Iron Guard was put down by Conducator Ion (10 pts)",
        "Antonescu in this country, which was forced in 1940 to cede Transylvania to Hungary. For ten points, name this country, ruled during the Cold War by Nicolae Ceausescu [chow-chess-coo] from Bucharest."
      ],
      "answer": "Romania"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city was home to the original terminus of the Western and Atlantic Railroad in its Five Points neighborhood. A military campaign for this city included the Battles of Kennesaw Mountain and (20 pts)",
        "Peachtree Creek. Security guard Richard Jewell was falsely accused of a bombing carried out in this city by Eric Robert Rudolph, which killed one person in Centennial (10 pts)",
        "Olympic Park. For ten points, name this city that hosted the 1996 Summer Olympics and was burned during Sherman’s March to the Sea, the capital of Georgia."
      ],
      "answer": "Atlanta"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this city, an author hired massive crowds to attend the premiere of his play Hernani to avoid censorship. An 1862 novel contains a lengthy digression on this city’s (20 pts)",
        "sewer system. In two scenes set in this city, Javert [zha-vair] commits suicide by jumping into a river, and Marius is dragged from the (10 pts)",
        "barricades during the 1830 July Revolution by Jean Valjean. Several scenes in Les Mis´erables [lay miz-er-ahb] are set in, for ten points, what capital city of France?"
      ],
      "answer": "Paris"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Part of this territory was placed under Amos Stoddard’s military rule after it was transferred on Three Flags Day. After the discovery of the secret Treaty of (20 pts)",
        "San Ildefonso, John Livingston was sent to purchase part of this territory. The rebellion of Toussaint [too-sahn] Louverture in Haiti, as well as a desire to raise (10 pts)",
        "funds for war against England, prompted Napol´eon to sell this territory for only fifteen million dollars. For ten points, name this large Midwestern territory purchased by the government of Thomas Jefferson in 1803."
      ],
      "answer": "Louisiana Purchase"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler’s empire was visited on a diplomatic mission by Ruy Gonzalez de Clavijo. This man’s forces defeated Bayezid the Thunderbolt at the Battle of Ankara, and he emerged victorious at the Battles of the Kondrucha River and the Terek River against the (20 pts)",
        "Golden Horde under Tokhtamysh. Mikhail Gerasimov exhumed this man’s body in 1941, supposedly triggering Hitler’s invasion of Russia. This ruler, whose capital was (10 pts)",
        "Samarkand, supposedly got his nickname due to an arrow wound on his leg. For ten points, name this crippled Mongol ruler."
      ],
      "answer": "Timur the Lame"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city’s Mill Pond, once part of an Atlantic harbor, was filled in in the 19th century to create Bullfinch Triangle and a Haymarket Square. Other land reclamation projects in this city created the Back Bay neighborhood and lowered (20 pts)",
        "Beacon Hill. The 15-year-long “Big Dig” constructed the Central Artery of I-93 through this city and brought I-90 past (10 pts)",
        "Logan International Airport. The Freedom Trail passes by the Old North Church and Fanueil Hall in, for ten points, what capital city of Massachusetts?"
      ],
      "answer": "Boston"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country was blamed for the shelling of Mainila, a false flag operation that ended a non-aggression pact. Less than a year after that war ended, aggression against this country resumed in the (20 pts)",
        "Continuation War. This country was defended by the Mannerheim line, from which soldiers tossed Molotov cocktails at the Red Army. The (10 pts)",
        "Soviet Union was expelled from the League of Nations in December 1939 after it invaded, for ten points, what Scandinavian country in the Winter War?"
      ],
      "answer": "Finland"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) To avoid paying damages, the orchestra for this event was relocated from the Hotel Biltmore to the Park Plaza. Reporter Carl Phillips was killed early in this event, which included Ray Collins’ panicked report of people jumping into the (20 pts)",
        "East River to escape black smoke. This event is memorialized with a three-legged statue in Woking, England and a ground-zero marker in Grovers Mill, (10 pts)",
        "New Jersey. Mercury Theater on the Air produced, for ten points, what 1938 radioplay by Orson Welles, based on a novel by H.G. Wells, which caused a mass panic of people who thought the Martian invasion was real?"
      ],
      "answer": "War of the Worlds radio broadcast"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A farm owned by this city’s first leader was turned into the Royal Botanic Garden by Lachlan Macquarie, who appointed “emancipists” to its government. Early in this city’s history, it was moved north to (20 pts)",
        "Port Jackson from the landing site of the HMS Endeavour, Botany Bay. This city’s harbor is home to a Jorn Utzon-designed building with sail-like (10 pts)",
        "shells, and it was founded as the capital of the British penal colony of New South Wales. For ten points, name this city with a notable opera house, the most populous in Australia."
      ],
      "answer": "Sydney"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This region was conquered after the Battle of Chuvash Cape and the defeat of Kuchum Khan. Tyumen was the first European settlement in this region. The Stroganov family financed the conquest of this region by a group led by (20 pts)",
        "Yermak, leading to an explosion in the fur trade. This region’s culture was driven by participants in the failed Decembrist revolt, who were (10 pts)",
        "sent here. The port of Vladivostok was selected as the eastern terminus of a railroad that crosses, for ten points, what enormous, desolate eastern region of Russia?"
      ],
      "answer": "Siberia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In Beijing in April 2013, this non-Asian country’s leader insisted he would send troops to back a hypothetical US invasion of North Korea. This country’s recently-resigned Prime Minister, John Key, had been elected in 2008 over long time Labour leader (20 pts)",
        "Helen Clark. Kyle Lockwood designed the proposed “Silver Fern” flag for this country, an option in a failed March 2016 referendum to replace this country’s current flag, which features the (10 pts)",
        "Union Jack and Southern Cross. For ten points, name this country in Oceania whose cities include Wellington and Auckland."
      ],
      "answer": "New Zealand"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An abandoned proposal to dam this river near Tocks Island led to the creation of a “water gap” National Recreation Area. Tributaries of this river, whose valley was home to the colony of New Sweden, include the Christina and the (20 pts)",
        "Schuylkill [skool-kul]. Ice on this river was a major obstacle to carrying out a successful attack on Johann Rall’s (10 pts)",
        "Hessians, who were quartered along its banks in Trenton during the American Revolution. For ten points, name this river which was crossed on the night of Christmas, December 1776 by George Washington."
      ],
      "answer": "Delaware River"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Alfred Kempe’s false proof of this statement was exposed in 1890 by Percy Heawood. When applied to toroidal graphs, this statement has an upper bound of 7. This theorem was proven by Kenneth (20 pts)",
        "Appel and Wolfgang Haken, who used the University of Illinois’ resources to study nearly 2,000 cases in which different maps may have violated it. The first widely-accepted “proof by (10 pts)",
        "computer” was for, for ten points, what mathematical theorem regarding the number of colors required to shade a map without adjacent regions sharing a color?"
      ],
      "answer": "four-color map theorem ”color” is not needed after said"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Description acceptable. Rupert Vance’s 1932 work about The Human Geography of this location responded to a manifesto from defenders of this region titled I’ll Take My Stand. John Crowe Ransom led a defense of this area against works like H.L. Mencken’s “Sahara of the Bozart,” which lampooned this region’s alleged (20 pts)",
        "intellectual backwardness. Like Harlem, this region enjoyed a literary “Renaissance,” including authors like Robert Penn Warren and (10 pts)",
        "William Faulkner. For ten points, name this broad geographic area that underwent Reconstruction after the Civil War."
      ],
      "answer": "the American South"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader’s administration included Marc Lalonde’s highly unpopular National Energy Program. As Prime Minister, this man agreed to Roy McMurtry, Roy Romanow, and Jean Chretien’s so-called “Kitchen Accord;” that agreement led to this man signing an 1982 act (20 pts)",
        "patriating his country’s constitution and granting his country sovereignty. This supporter of bilingualism cracked down on the (10 pts)",
        "FLQ during the 1970 October Crisis. For ten points, name this two-time Liberal Prime Minister of Canada and father of Canada’s current PM, Justin."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Pierre Trudeau",
        "Joseph Philippe Pierre Yves Elliott Trudeau"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Carl and Louis Stokes, a pair of politicians from this state, testified before Congress after two railroad bridges were damaged near the Republic Steel Mill in an oil fire that inspired the creation of Earth Day. In the aftermath of that disaster, (20 pts)",
        "Time magazine claimed that a water source in this state was so polluted that one “does not drown [in it], but decay” after the polluted water (10 pts)",
        "caught on fire in 1969. For ten points, name this state where the Cuyahoga River “oozes” into Lake Erie after passing through Cleveland."
      ],
      "answer": "Ohio"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country was the site of Operation Blue Bat, where Eisenhower sent 15,000 troops to help president Camille Chamoun end a religious war. To reduce ethnic conflicts in this country, its law mandates that its president must be a Sunni Muslim and its prime minister must be a (20 pts)",
        "Maronite Christian. This country was invaded in 2006 after Hassan Nasrallah organized numerous cross-border ambushes against (10 pts)",
        "Israeli villages. For ten points, name this country where Hezbollah is based in Beirut."
      ],
      "answer": "Lebanon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Crete was occupied by this power, which ruled the Kingdom of Negroponte in the Aegean Sea. This city-state lost the Battle of Agnadello to France during the War of the (20 pts)",
        "League of Cambrai. This city-state’s fort of Famagusta resisted the Ottoman siege of Cyprus, supported by a shipyard capable of mass-producing galleys, the (10 pts)",
        "Arsenale [ar-sen-ah-lay]. The Fourth Crusade was diverted to sack Zara and Constantinople by Enrico Dandolo, a doge [dohj] of this city. For ten points, name this northern Italian city-state built on a series of islands separated by canals."
      ],
      "answer": "Most Serene Republic of Venice"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Robert Morrison’s translation of the Bible hastened the spread of Christianity in this country. The Nestorian Stone tells of how the monk Alopen traveled to this country, which was also visited by the Jesuit Matteo (20 pts)",
        "Ricci. The Three-Self Church was set up in this country when its communist party came to power in the early (10 pts)",
        "1950s. For ten points, name this country where Christianity was suppressed under the Cultural Revolution."
      ],
      "answer": "China"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a legend from this country, a woman who tries to ride her newlywed husband’s horse is thrown off and bounces on her skirt all the way to the moon. Slue-Foot (20 pts)",
        "Sue rode a catfish down a river in this country, and a man in this country dies after beating a steam powered hammer in a steel-driving contest. (10 pts)",
        "Pecos Bill and John Henry are two characters from the folklore of, for ten points, what country where Paul Bunyan’s birth supposedly occurred in Wisconsin or Minnesota?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "United States of America",
        "USA",
        "America"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A polychoral style of music was developed in this city by Giovanni Gabrielli. This city was the final home of a composer who depicted the mistress of Nero in The Coronation of Poppea. Claudio Monteverdi worked in this city, where the (20 pts)",
        "Ospedale della Piet`a employed the “Red Priest” who composed The Four Seasons. (10 pts)",
        "Antonio Vivaldi lived in, for ten points, what Italian city where opera was staged during Carnival and the barcarole was sung by gondoliers rowing along its canals?"
      ],
      "answer": "Venice"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This region’s Catholic nobles formed the Union of Green Mountain to contest George Podebrad’s claim to this region’s kingdom, which he contested with Hungarian King Matthias Corvinus. The House of Luxembourg ruled this kingdom under the (20 pts)",
        "Blind King John, who died at the Battle of Crecy. In 1618, two Catholic regents were (10 pts)",
        "defenestrated in a city in this kingdom, helping trigger the Thirty Years’ War. For ten points, name this region in the modern-day Czech Republic which, because French people in the 19th century believed the Romani came from this region, names an unattached artistic lifestyle."
      ],
      "answer": "Kingdom of Bohemia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During a battle for this city, camels strapped with flaming haystacks were ordered to charge in order to scatter enemy elephants. The Battle of Karnal paved the way for an attack on this city, leading the (20 pts)",
        "Peacock Throne to be carried off by Nader Shah in 1739. An earlier sack of this city was carried out by (10 pts)",
        "Tamerlane in 1398. For ten points, name this seat of the Mughal Empire, a city whose “New” district now hosts the government of Narendra Modi as the capital city of India."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Delhi",
        "New Delhi after “’New’ district” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Josef Terboven helped run this country during its Nazi occupation. The Nazi invasion of this country was discovered after the sinking of the Rio de Janeiro off the coast of (20 pts)",
        "Lillesund; during that invasion, a failed coup in this country was announced over the radio, the first such event in history. The Nazi invasion of (10 pts)",
        "Denmark was simultaneous with the invasion of, for ten points, what Scandinavian country where a pro-Nazi puppet government was led by Vidkun Quisling west of Sweden?"
      ],
      "answer": "Norway"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Near the end of a novel set in this country, two men reconcile when one gives the other a sympathy wreath for his dead wife and the other donates funds to build a new church. In a novel set in this country, the (20 pts)",
        "Smales family migrates to their servant’s village; that novel, July’s People, includes Nadine Gordimer’s prediction of a civil war and was once banned in Gauteng Province. The social activist (10 pts)",
        "Arthur Jarvis is murdered by Absalom Kumalo in this country in Alan Paton’s Cry the Beloved Country. For ten points, name this country, where those novels were written during the Apartheid era."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of South Africa"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A military dictator of this country was famed for making civil servants who were late to work do squat-jumps; that leader won an election as the head of the All Progressives’ Congress with support from this country’s (20 pts)",
        "Hausa ethnic group. This country was once led by Goodluck Jonathan, who lost the aforementioned election after being criticized for his weak response to a terrorist group led by (10 pts)",
        "Abubakar Shekau. For ten points, name this African country currently led by Muhammadu Buhari from the city of Abuja, the home country of Boko Haram."
      ],
      "answer": "Federal Republic of Nigeria"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The memorial site of Castle Hill in this region is sometimes named after Alexander Baranov, who established a provisional capital here in the early 1800s after defeating Tlingit natives. This region’s ports of (20 pts)",
        "Dyea and Skagway boomed in the 1890s as through points for gold prospectors. Sitka was the (10 pts)",
        "Russian territorial capital of this region, which was acquired by the U.S. in 1867 in a move dubbed Seward’s Folly. For ten points, name this modern US state home to the cities of Fairbanks and Anchorage."
      ],
      "answer": "Alaska"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A modern native indigenous to this country is nicknamed “Man of the Hole” due to the large, 6-feet deep holes he digs to trap prey. Claude Levi-Strauss’s Triste Tropiques [treest troh-PEEK] focuses primarily on this non-Asian country, which recently surpassed New (20 pts)",
        "Guinea in having the most uncontacted peoples within its borders. Shantytowns called “favelas” dot the urban landscape of cities like (10 pts)",
        "Sao Paolo and Rio de Janeiro in, for ten points, what Portuguese-speaking South American country?"
      ],
      "answer": "Federative Republic of Brazil"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After natives in what is now this country committed a ritual mass suicide known as puputan, the city of Klungkung fell to European colonists. A ruler of this country established a system called USDEK to implement (20 pts)",
        "Guided Democracy; that system fell apart after the 30 September Movement and gave way to the New Order. Mohammad Hatta served as Vice President and Prime Minister for the (10 pts)",
        "INP in, for ten points, what Asian country, once led by Sukarno and Suharto, whose capital is Jakarta?"
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Indonesia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This river was the site of the second largest flood in geologic history, the Bonneville flood, when the Portneuf River overflowed into this river during the last ice age. This river derived its name from a misinterpreted (20 pts)",
        "Shoshone hand signal for the nearby abundant salmon, the letter S. This river flows through Twin Falls, north of which (10 pts)",
        "Evel Knievel failed to jump across a canyon in 1974. For ten points, name this tributary of the Columbia that flows past Boise to form the northern border between Idaho and Oregon."
      ],
      "answer": "Snake River"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this modern day country, Johann Beaulieu was unable to defend a bridgehead over the river Adda at Lodi [loh-dee]; this set-back, along with Joseph Alvinzci’s defeat at Arcole [ar-co-lay] in this modern day country, ensured that the First (20 pts)",
        "Coalition would have to accept the creation of the Ligurian Republic. Another battle in this modern day country, the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Marengo, began when a commander led his troops atop a donkey through the St. Bernard Pass. For ten points, name this modern-day country where Napoleon crossed the Alps to score a victory near Piedmont."
      ],
      "answer": "Italy"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A leader of this country created a complex system of telex machines in Operation Cybersyn, a plan to aid his economic planning. That leader of this country gained controversy for nationalizing the (20 pts)",
        "copper industry, and later committed suicide in La Moneda Palace after a successful coup against him. Another ruler of this country implemented neoliberal economic policies with the help of the (10 pts)",
        "“Chicago Boys” and, with CIA backing, brutally suppressed political dissent in Operation Condor. For ten points, name this South American country once ruled by Salvador Allende and Augusto Pinochet."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Chile"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Troops from this country captured the city of Dire Dawa from this country’s western neighbor; this country was led by Siad Barre during that battle in the Ogaden War. In the early 20th century, the “Mad (20 pts)",
        "Mullah” founded a Dervish state in what is now this country, near where the Majeerteen sultanates had earlier ruled from Puntland. In 1993, when the US invaded this country’s capital to fight Mohamed Farah Aidid, two (10 pts)",
        "Black Hawk helicopters were shot down. For ten points, name this country on the Horn of Africa where the Battle of Mogadishu took place."
      ],
      "answer": "Somalia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Enemy forces were removed from one of these regions in Operation Hastings, which used the Rockpile as an observation post; that one of these regions was north of the Khe Sanh Combat Base in Vietnam. When Arthur Bonifas and Mark Barrett were killed in another of these regions, US forces responded with Operation (20 pts)",
        "Paul Bunyan, the heavily supported cutting of a poplar tree that was supposedly planted by Kim Il-Sung. (10 pts)",
        "Panmunjom and a Joint Security Area are located in one of these areas along the 38th Parallel between North and South Korea. For ten points, give this term for buffer territory between hostile countries where military personnel are banned. ANSWER:Demilitarized Zone(acceptDMZ;acceptVietnameseDemilitarized Zone;acceptKorean Demilitarized Zone after “Arthur Bonifas” is read) (6) This man asserted he was the rightful ruler of his country in a letter to Pope John XXII [22], the Declaration of Arbroath. The Earl of Pembroke was ordered to hunt down this man, handing him a disastrous loss at Methven. This king was (+) excommunicated after murdering John Comyn at the church of the Greyfriars. This man besieged (*) Stirling Castle, forcing the Battle of Bannockburn. For ten points, name this victorious king of the First War of Scottish Independence."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Robert I",
        "Robert the Bruce"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country was the site of the 1983 Black July pogrom, which triggered a civil war. The first female ruler of an Asian nation, Queen Anula, ruled the Anuradhapura kingdom in what is now this country. The (20 pts)",
        "Pali Canon, an ancient Buddhist scripture, was recorded in this country after being composed in northern India. (10 pts)",
        "Kandy was the last independent kingdom in this modern country, which is connected to the mainland by Adam’s Bridge. For ten points, name this island country, known as Ceylon during its British occupation, found off the coast of India."
      ],
      "answer": "Sri Lanka"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The residents of four colonial towns in what is now this country, including Rufisque [roo-feesk], were granted citizenship thanks to the efforts of Blaise Diagne [dee-ahn]. The Portuguese built a slave trading outpost on (20 pts)",
        "Gor´ee Island in the harbor of what is now this country’s capital. An airport named for this country’s first president, L´eopold Senghor, lies on the narrow Cap-Vert peninsula near the (10 pts)",
        "Pointe des Alamadies, the westernmost point of the African continent. For ten points, name this Francophone African country where Macky Sall holds office in Dakar."
      ],
      "answer": "Senegal"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This territory’s Governor Charles Robinson opposed the expansion of slavery as promoted by its Lecompton Constitution. Several settlers were killed in this territory at Pottawatomie by (20 pts)",
        "John Brown in retribution for the sacking of its town of Lawrence; that sacking was a response to Charles Sumner’s beating for denounced the pro-slavery (10 pts)",
        "“crime” against this territory. For ten points, name this territory that was “bleeding” over slavery in the 1850s and whose early Topeka Constitution banned slavery."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Kansas",
        "Bleeding Kansas"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1997, Borge Ousland completed a solo, kite-aided journey across this region. In December 2018, Colin O’Brady completed a 921-mile journey across this region, finishing with a stretch of 32 hours without sleep. The Nimrod (20 pts)",
        "expedition attempted a journey in this region, where it was based in McMurdo Sound. In 1915, Sir Ernest Shackleton lost the Endurance in an (10 pts)",
        "ice flow while exploring, for ten points, what continent where Roald Amundsen led the first party to reach the South Pole?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Antarctica",
        "South Pole until “continent” is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country celebrates the feast of Epiphany with a celebration called Timkat. A community of Jews from this country called Beta Israel claims to be descended from the Queen of (20 pts)",
        "Sheba. This country is home to ancient rock-hewn churches at Lalibela. It’s not Jamaica, but (10 pts)",
        "Rastafarians regard a former monarch of this country to be the Second Coming of Christ. For ten points, name this country whose Christian church claims to have the original Ark of the Covenant, an African country with capital at Addis Ababa."
      ],
      "answer": "Ethiopia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This is the most populous city founded by James Robertson, who helped lead the Watauga Association. The inhabitant of a famous residence in this city married a woman he met here named Rachel (20 pts)",
        "Donelson. The Hermitage is located in this city, where a $1 million grant led to the 1873 creation of a (10 pts)",
        "university named for a New York tycoon. Andrew Jackson lived much of his life in, for ten points, what city which is home to Vanderbilt University, located in Tennessee?"
      ],
      "answer": "Nashville"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country was defended by qenderzjarri forts designed by Josif Zigali and the Sigurimi secret police. Roughly 5.7 bunkers per square kilometer were constructed in this country, whose government justified it as preparation against a joint (20 pts)",
        "NATO-Warsaw Pact invasion. After a disagreement, Nikita Khrushchev withdrew grain shipments from this country, which broke with its last ally, China, over the Three Worlds Theory. This country, the (10 pts)",
        "poorest in Europe during the 1980s, proclaimed itself the world’s first atheist state. For ten points, name this isolationist Balkan nation once led by Enver Hoxha [ho-cha]."
      ],
      "answer": "Albania"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country birthed a tradition of musical composition known as “kuchkism.” Numerous works written in this country, including Ruslan and Lyudmila and Kashchey the Immortal, use the (20 pts)",
        "whole tone scale to give a sense of foreboding evil, a technique developed by a group that included Cesar Cui and was led by Mily (10 pts)",
        "Balakirev. For ten points, name this country where nationalism was promoted by The Mighty Handful, a group of five composers including Modest Mussorgsky, Alexander Borodin, and Nikolai Rimsky-Korsakov."
      ],
      "answer": "Russia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A man born in this city posed a problem about the growth rate of a rabbit population in his book Liber Abaci. A value approximating the Golden Ratio can be found by dividing two successive terms in a sequence named for that man born in this city, (20 pts)",
        "Fibonacci. Vincenzo Vivani claims that De Motu’s central idea, that objects of different masses have the same (10 pts)",
        "acceleration, was verified by a man’s experiment in this city. For ten points, name this Italian city, where balls were allegedly dropped by Galileo from its namesake leaning tower."
      ],
      "answer": "Pisa"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While searching in this body of water in 1935, Lorenzo Hagglund found the remains of a ship that is now displayed in the Smithsonian. The gundalow Spitfire sank in this body of water after the Battle of Valcour Island. (20 pts)",
        "Alexander Macomb was known as “the Hero” of a battle located on this body of water, where Thomas Pringle and Guy Carleton led a 1776 attack. (10 pts)",
        "Benedict Arnold stalled the British invasion of the Hudson River Valley by winning a naval battle on, for ten points, what lake, overlooked by Fort Ticonderoga, that straddles the border of Vermont and New York?"
      ],
      "answer": "Lake Champlain"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A shopkeeper named Consider Tiffany wrote about this man’s capture. William Hull popularized a quote given by this man, who was most famous for an action that occurred simultaneously with one group’s escape to Morningside (20 pts)",
        "Heights. This man was caught a day after the Great Fire of New York following the Battle of Long Island, in which he was tasked with providing (10 pts)",
        "information on the British. For ten points, name this Revolutionary War spy who said “I only regret that I have but one life to lose for my country.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Nathan Hale"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) William Richardson was the first person to receive a land grant in this city, in which he names a bay. A popular destination of bootleggers during Prohibition was the fishing village of Sausalito near this city. A dangerous (20 pts)",
        "neighborhood in this city received its name after policemen working in it claimed you could afford a high-quality steak from working shifts in it. This home of the (10 pts)",
        "Tenderloin District is also home to a one end of a structure designed by Joseph Strauss and Charles Ellis that links it to Marin County by crossing a namesake bay. For ten points, name this home city of the Golden Gate Bridge."
      ],
      "answer": "San Francisco"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A governor of this city committed suicide after being unable to stop the HMS Phaeton from harassing ships in its harbor. Inhabitants of this city nicknamed arriving carracks “black ships” while it was briefly under Portuguese rule. During a period of seclusion, only (20 pts)",
        "Dutch traders were allowed to trade with this city via its artificially built Dejima Island. Because cloud cover obscured Kokura, the (10 pts)",
        "Fat Man weapon was used against, for ten points, what city that was attacked with a nuclear weapon three days after Hiroshima?"
      ],
      "answer": "Nagasaki"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one war, this country favored holding the towns of Ebeltoft and Fredericia to force attackers into a defensive line known as this country’s “earthwork.” This country passed the November Constitution to exert influence over a region it promised not to (20 pts)",
        "annex, leading to the violation of the London Protocol and subsequent invasion. After this country was decisively defeated at Dybbol, it surrendered the region of (10 pts)",
        "Lauenburg. For ten points, the Treaty of Vienna was signed after an Austrian and Prussian coalition forced what Nordic country to give up Schleswig and Holstein?"
      ],
      "answer": "Denmark"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Religious practices in this modern-day country include the Shaking Tent ritual and a regular re-burial of the corpses of those who had died peacefully, the Feast of the Dead. The Montagnais lived in this nation, where the (20 pts)",
        "Northwest Company operated. The city of (10 pts)",
        "Stadacona was visited by the explorer Jacques Cartier in what is now, for ten points, what country where Samuel de Champlain founded Quebec City?"
      ],
      "answer": "Canada"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This dynasty’s greatest ruler rose to power on the “Night of the Three Caliphs,” named because his son Mamun was born while the king Hadi died. This dynasty was established following a battle at the Great (20 pts)",
        "Zab in which its founder, as-Saffah, prevailed. A river allegedly ran black with ink from destroyed books after (10 pts)",
        "Hulagu Khan sacked this dynasty’s capital and desecrated the House of Wisdom that had been built by Harun al-Rashid. For ten points, name this caliphate that lasted until the 13th century in Baghdad."
      ],
      "answer": "Abbasid Caliphate"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country’s namesake river passes through its agriculturally rich Fouta region. The MFDC has advocated for the independence of this country’s Casamance region. A holding center for African slaves waiting to be exported operated on this country’s (20 pts)",
        "Goree Island. Leopold Sedar Senghor Airport is in this country, the home of the Serer and Wolof ethnic groups. The (10 pts)",
        "Gambia is surrounded by, for ten points, what former French colony, an African country with capital at Dakar?"
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Senegal"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man infamously allied his Catholic country with a Protestant nation by signing the Treaty of Barwalde. On the Day of the Dupes, this man nearly lost power when Marie de (20 pts)",
        "Medici attempted to sway opinion against him. A seawall was constructed to obstruct shipping to La Rochelle, a (10 pts)",
        "Huguenot fortress besieged by this man. This man, who was known as the Red Eminence, served as the adviser of Louis XIII. For ten points, name this French cardinal who was succeeded by Mazarin in 1642."
      ],
      "answer": "Cardinal Richelieu or Armand Jean du Plessis"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Poet Duncan Campbell Scott established a boarding school system in this country in the 1920s. This country’s government used eleven Numbered Treaties to take land and resources from its indigenous people. An 1869 rebellion of the (20 pts)",
        "M´etis [may-TEE] people was led by Louis Riel, who was executed on orders of John A. (10 pts)",
        "Macdonald, this country’s first prime minister. The Cree and Ojibwe are the largest subgroups of the First Nations, one of the indigenous groups of, for ten points, what largest North American country?"
      ],
      "answer": "Canada"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In fighting near this city’s San Cosme Gate, future general Ulysses S. Grant disassembled a howitzer and reassembled it in a church, leading to his promotion to captain. The so-called Boy Heroes were killed in this city’s (20 pts)",
        "fortress of Chapultepec by US forces led by Winfield Scott. In the (10 pts)",
        "Marines” Hymn, this city’s battlefields are referred to as the “Halls of Montezuma.” For ten points, name this capital city that was taken by the US in the Mexican-American War."
      ],
      "answer": "Mexico City"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2013, this country finally released the decades-old Sunderlal Committee report, which investigated police actions during the Telangana Rebellion. The 3rd of June Plan established this country’s western border at the (20 pts)",
        "Radcliffe Line. After it achieved independence, this country launched Operation Vijay to reclaim Goa. This country was partitioned from its western neighbor on the request of Muhammad Ali (10 pts)",
        "Jinnah’s Muslim League. For ten points, name this former British colony that gained independence in 1947 after the efforts of Jawaharlal Nehru and Mohandas Gandhi."
      ],
      "answer": "India"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country was the site of Operation Dragon Rouge, where foreign special forces had to be deployed to rescue hostages during the Simba Uprising. A crisis in this country was almost mediated by UN Secretary-General Dag (20 pts)",
        "Hammarskjold [“hammer”-sk’yold], who died in a plane crash in Northern Rhodesia en route to a peace conference. The (10 pts)",
        "Katanga Crisis took place in this country, where Joseph Kasa-Vubu was replaced by a man who briefly renamed this country Zaire. For ten points, name this African country where Mobutu Sese Seko led from Kinshasa."
      ],
      "answer": "Democratic Republic of the Congo"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this country, student Benno Ohnesorg was killed during a protest against the Shah of Iran. This country was the subject of a declaration by French foreign minister Robert Schuman that paved the way for the European (20 pts)",
        "Coal and Steel Community. An economic miracle in this country began under Konrad Adenauer, and it adopted the policy of (10 pts)",
        "“ostpolitik” under Willy Brandt to ease tensions with its neighbor. For ten points, name this former country with capital Bonn that was re-unified with its eastern neighbor in 1990."
      ],
      "answer": "West Germany"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Hundreds of this region’s peasants were killed on Christmas 1705 in the Sendling night of murder. Part of this region known as the Innviertel was given to the Habsburg monarchy following the Treaty of Teschen. The (20 pts)",
        "Wittelsbach claim to this region was challenged in the Potato War. This region’s “mad king” Ludwig II ordered the construction of Neuschwanstein [noysh-van-stein], the inspiration for the (10 pts)",
        "castle in Sleeping Beauty. For ten points, name this home of Oktoberfest, a German region with capital Munich."
      ],
      "answer": "Bavaria or Bayern"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Artemis Ward ordered colonial militia to fortify the area surrounding this city. Cannons captured at Fort Ticonderoga were brought to the Dorchester Heights outside of this city by Henry Knox in the Noble Train of Artillery. (20 pts)",
        "Israel Putnam likely gave the order “Don’t fire until you see the whites of their eyes” in a battle fought near this city. Skirmishes at (10 pts)",
        "Lexington and Concord preceded a siege of, for ten points, what Massachusetts city that was the site of the Battle of Bunker Hill?"
      ],
      "answer": "Boston"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1999, this country’s town of Magdalena was hit by the largest freshwater oil spill in history. This country’s Mar Chiquita, or Little Sea, is found in its Cordoba province. In the 1980s, this country initially complained about the construction of the (20 pts)",
        "Itaipu Dam on the border of two of its neighbors because the dam threatened the flow of the Parana River, which empties into the Rio de la Plata between this country and (10 pts)",
        "Paraguay. For ten points, name this South American country where, in 1536, Spanish conquistadors founded Buenos Aires."
      ],
      "answer": "Argentina"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In negotiations with this man, George Mikan declined to present him with a certified check for one million dollars, costing Mikan his job as commissioner of the ABA. While playing for John Wooden at UCLA, this man converted to (20 pts)",
        "Islam. In 1974, he requested a trade from Milwaukee to a city with a more diverse culture; he landed in Los Angeles, where he won five titles while playing with (10 pts)",
        "Magic Johnson. The “skyhook” was the signature play of, for ten points, what center for the Bucks and Lakers who scored the most points in NBA history?"
      ],
      "answer": "Kareem Abdul-Jabbar or Lew Alcindor"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Supreme Court ruled in Cooper v. Aaron against this city’s plan to wait over two years to implement a proposal by Virgil Blossom. Ronald Davies issued a desegregation order in this city, which led to an iconic photo of (20 pts)",
        "Elizabeth Eckford. This city’s mayor, Woodrow Wilson Mann, sent a telegram asking for federal troops to President (10 pts)",
        "Eisenhower. Governor Orval Faubus tried to thwart the Brown v. Board decision at Central High School in, for ten points, what city where, in 1957, nine black students helped desegregate public schools in Arkansas?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Little Rock",
        "Little Rock Nine"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the 1980s, this country experienced a Mountain War in which Christians were displaced from its Chouf region. A massacre of a refugee camp in this country was conducted as retaliation for the assassination of Bachir (20 pts)",
        "Gemayel, who founded this country’s Phalangist party. The Taif Agreement ended a civil war in this country, where the Sabra and Shatila massacres occurred. The militant group (10 pts)",
        "Hezbollah is based in, for ten points, what country once led by Rafik Hariri, who was assassinated in Beirut?"
      ],
      "answer": "Lebanon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The world’s oldest Chinatown is this city’s township of Binondo, a district originally meant to house recent converts to Catholicism. The Pasig River flows through this city, and a ring highway around it nicknamed “EDSA” names a 1986 revolution whose leaders included (20 pts)",
        "Cardinal Jaime Sin. This city was connected by the first permanent route across the Pacific Ocean to Acapulco in New Spain. Except for a stint from 1948 to 1976 by (10 pts)",
        "Quezon City, this city has served as a capital for centuries. The People Power Revolution toppled Ferdinand Marcos in, for ten points, what capital city of the Philippines?"
      ],
      "answer": "Manila"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The remains of dome shaped huts have been found on this island at Mount Sandel. Hundreds of wedge tombs, including the Hag’s Bed, were built facing the setting sun in the north of this island. This island’s Neolithic monument (20 pts)",
        "Newgrange features a burial chamber that lights up during the winter solstice; that monument is found just west of Drogheda [draw-duh] on the (10 pts)",
        "River Boyne. For ten points, name this European island that was settled by the Gaels before the 1169 Norman invasion from Britain to the east."
      ],
      "answer": "Ireland"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Among the thousands of birch bark manuscripts excavated in this city are homework assignments from a six-year-old named Onfim. A ruler of this city ascended to the throne after overthrowing his brother with the assistance of Sartaq Khan and the Golden Horde. This city was saved from a (20 pts)",
        "Swedish invasion by the victory of a teenage prince at the Battle of Neva. This city’s namesake republic was annexed by Muscovy under Ivan III. A prince of this city defeated the (10 pts)",
        "Teutonic Knights on the frozen Lake Peipus in the 1242 Battle of the Ice. For ten points, name this powerful medieval Russian city, the home of Alexander Nevsky."
      ],
      "answer": "Novgorod"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this battle, one side’s advances up Edson’s Ridge forced the other side to call up reinforcements from the Kokoda Track. Supplies in this battle were taken down “the slot” under a system known as the Tokyo Express. This battle was codenamed Operation (20 pts)",
        "Watchtower and featured the capture of Savo and Tulagi Islands. This battle was initiated to capture the airstrip at (10 pts)",
        "Henderson Field, which was to be used as a base for further attacks in the Pacific. For ten points, name this 1943 battle over a namesake island in the Solomons."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Guadalcanal"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader was supported by the British contingency plan Giralda, which would have prevented a coup attempt by the rival Umma party. Many of this leader’s reforms were undone by the “everything goes” policy of successor Ali Mwinyi. Following a dispute over his country’s (20 pts)",
        "Kagera region, this leader restored Milton Obote to power in Uganda over the defeated Idi Amin. This leader’s policy of (10 pts)",
        "ujamaa was outlined in his Arusha Declaration, a manifesto of African socialism. Zanzibar and Tanganyika were unified during the tenure of, for ten points, what first president of Tanzania?"
      ],
      "answer": "Julius Nyerere"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1034, this river flooded following heavy rainfall at Henglong. This river carries sediment from the Loess plateau and has a large bend in the Ordos Loop. Historically, this river once went through Dalu Lake and Daye Lake but shifted due to floods, one of which ended the (20 pts)",
        "Xin [[SHIN]] Dynasty of Wang Mang. 890,000 people died when this river flooded after the KMT destroyed levees to stop the (10 pts)",
        "Japanese invasion. For ten points, name this second-longest Chinese river known for its muddy color."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Yellow River",
        "Huang He ]"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A politician from this nation was elected “Regenerating President” after calling for peace in the “Cry of Montán.” An admiral from this country was nicknamed the “Gentleman of the Seas” after rescuing the crew of the Esmeralda when he defeated them at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Iquique [[ih-KWEE-kweh]]. This nation’s monopoly on saltpeter sparked a war with neighboring (10 pts)",
        "Chile. For ten points, name this ally of Bolivia during the War of the Pacific, which in 2020 elected President Francisco Sagasti to govern from the House of Pizarro in Lima."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Peru"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Étienne Gérard defended this country in a failed attempt to reconquer it known as the Ten Days’ Campaign. A revolution in this country began during a performance of the opera The Mute Girl of Portici [[por-TEE-chee]], presented during a celebration of William I, Prince of (20 pts)",
        "Orange-Nassau. This country’s independence was recognized at the London Conference, but it took nine years for the (10 pts)",
        "Netherlands to accept it. For ten points, name this country whose 1830 revolution led to the establishment of a government in Brussels."
      ],
      "answer": "Kingdom of Belgium 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 2"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city's Municipal Police opposed the Metropolitan Police after the appointment of Charles Devlin as City Street Commissioner by Mayor Fernando Wood. In another incident in this city, supporters of actor Edwin Forrest fought fans of William Charles Macready in the (20 pts)",
        "Astor Place Riot. In 1863, working-class Irishmen in this city burned down the Colored Orphan Asylum while protesting the (10 pts)",
        "Conscription Act. For ten points, what city endured civil war draft riots along Third Avenue, as well as protests against Tammany Hall?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "New York City",
        "NYC"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The construction of this river's Lower Monumental Dam in 1968 caused the Marmes Rockshelter, one of the best-preserved Native American archaeological sites along this river, to permanently flood. In 1893, the steamship Annie Faxon sank on this river while transporting copper ore from (20 pts)",
        "Hells Canyon to Lewiston. In 1805, Lewis and Clark traversed the modern state of Idaho in dugout canoes along the (10 pts)",
        "Clearwater, this river’s largest tributary. For ten points, name this river of the Pacific Northwest, whose headwaters begin at Yellowstone National Park."
      ],
      "answer": "Snake River"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this modern-day country, researchers discovered what is considered “the oldest naturalistic life-sized sculpture of a human,” called the Urfa Man. Berlin’s Altes Museum contains an altar discovered by Carl Humann [[HOO-mon]] in this modern country at the site of ancient (20 pts)",
        "Pergamon. Near this country's city of Hisarlik, Heinrich Schliemann [[SHLEE-mon]] discovered many copper and gold artifacts belonging to (10 pts)",
        "Priam's Treasure. For ten points, name this country, where excavations have been going on for over 150 years around the ruins of Troy."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Turkey"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this country, Imam Yahya prohibited Jews from building their houses higher than Muslim homes before his assassination in the Alwaziri Coup. Many Jews from this country were brought to Israel in Operation Magic Carpet. In 2000, the USS Cole (20 pts)",
        "was bombed by al-Qaeda in a suicide attack off the coast of this country. This country's first president, Ali Abdullah (10 pts)",
        "Saleh, was assassinated by a sniper in 2017. For ten points, name this Middle Eastern country, whose ongoing civil war has involved fighting in cities like Aden and Sana'a."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Yemen 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 5"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city includes the well-preserved cisterns of La Malga. The Baths of Antonius are located in this city where the physician Constantine the African was born. This city, the site of an exarchate and praetorian prefecture of Africa, long rivaled (20 pts)",
        "Utica. The first transmarine Roman colony, Colonia Junonia, was at the site of this city, where the earth was salted after Zama. Legendarily, Alyssa or Dido founded this city, which fought with (10 pts)",
        "Rome in the Punic Wars. For ten points, name this Tunisian city, home to Hannibal."
      ],
      "answer": "Carthage 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 5"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country's Sakalava people exchanged slaves for weapons with Omani Arabs. In a namesake charter, Joseph-François Lambert was given control of all natural resources during the reign of Radama II, a king of this country's Merina (20 pts)",
        "Kingdom. Several Christians were hurled off cliffs as part of this country's persecution of Christianity under queen Ranavalona I. This country's president Andry Rajoelina [[rah-djow-LEE-nah]] belongs to its (10 pts)",
        "Malagasy ethnic group. For ten points, name this island country which the French took over during the invasion of Antananarivo."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Republic of Madagascar or Merina Kingdom",
        "or Kingdom of Imerina",
        "or Kingdom of Madagascar 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 1"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Cities that have hosted this event include San Diego, Newport, New York City, and Valencia, Spain. This event was first held near the location of Queen Victoria’s final home, Osborne House, at East Cowes. A trophy awarded to one (20 pts)",
        "club that earns the right to participate in this event has, since 1983, been named for Louis Vuitton. Harold Vanderbilt, Ted Turner, and Larry Ellison have earned this trophy, which was won by a US (10 pts)",
        "skipper for 126 consecutive years. For ten points, name this oldest international sporting trophy, named after a schooner, not a country."
      ],
      "answer": "America’s Cup or the Auld Mug"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1948, one of this sea’s many islands, which is now part of the mainland, became the site of a secret bioweapons facility. In the early 1960s, the Amu Darya and Syr Darya rivers were diverted from this sea to provide desert (20 pts)",
        "irrigation in support of the burgeoning Uzbek cotton farming industry. The Dike Kokoral dam was completed in 2005 in an attempt to replenish this sea’s (10 pts)",
        "diminishing water level. For ten points, name this sea, whose drainage basin encompasses nearly 600,000 square miles in Central Asia."
      ],
      "answer": "Aral Sea"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Iron Age kingdom of Fortriu is synonymous with this tribe. By the year 900, this tribe merged with the Gaelic kingdom of Dal Riata to form the Kingdom of Alba, which by the 13th century had expanded to include the formerly Brittonic kingdom of (20 pts)",
        "Strathclyde. This tribe’s eponymous monumental stele [[STEE-LEE]] were created between the 6th and the 9th centuries, the period of this tribe’s conversion to Christianity. Located north of the rivers (10 pts)",
        "Forth and Clyde, the Ptolemy world map calls this tribe the Caledonii. For ten points, name this Early Medieval Scottish people."
      ],
      "answer": "Picts"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this country, national hero Keppetipola Disawe [[dih-SAH-weh]] launched the Uva Rebellion of 1818 against Governor Robert Brownrigg. A conflict in this country was fought between the government and a group that wanted to establish an ethnic homeland called (20 pts)",
        "Eelam, the latter of which assassinated Indian Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi. The Dutch gained control of this country's coastal areas during its (10 pts)",
        "Kingdom of Kandy. For ten points, name this island country that faced a civil war between a Sinhalese government and the Tamil Tigers."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Democratic Socialist Republic of Sri Lanka",
        "Ceylon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this country, people including Jeremiah Chitunda were killed in the Halloween Massacre, which occurred in response to the Bicesse Accords. The Ovimbundu cities of Kuito and Huambo in this country were destroyed during a conflict which included the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Cuito Cuanavale. During this country's civil war, Holden Roberto’s FNLA and Jonas Savimbi’s UNITA fought against Agostinho Neto’s (10 pts)",
        "MPLA. This African country was the primary source of slaves for Brazilian plantations. For ten points, name this former Portuguese colony governed from Luanda."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Angola 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Finals"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2013, this island became its own governorate after detaching from the Hadhramaut [[hah-drah-MAWT]] Governorate over 250 miles away. A local legend claims that Thomas the Apostle shipwrecked on this island in 52 CE on his way to evangelize (20 pts)",
        "India. This island is home to nearly 700 unique, endemic species, leading some to call it “the most alien-looking place on earth.” This island, which constitutes approximately 95% of the landmass of its namesake archipelago, is closer to (10 pts)",
        "Somalia than the country to which it belongs. For ten points, name this Yemeni island located in the Arabian Sea."
      ],
      "answer": "Socotra"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The polymath Pindar labelled this body the \"Inhospitable Sea\" and considered travelling in it to be an ill-omen. A \"deluge\" hypothesis involving this body of water might have inspired the story of (20 pts)",
        "Noah's Ark. A Russian victory on this body of water during the Battle of Sinope [[see-NOH-pee]] led to the British and French entering the Crimean War. The Montreux [[mon-TROO]] Convention allowed foreign vessels to pass to and from, (10 pts)",
        "for ten points, what sea which borders countries like Ukraine and Turkey?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Black Sea",
        "Chyornoye more",
        "Karadeniz"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "In Map of True Places, Zee Finch returns to this city to check in on her ailing father. In a novel set in this city, Matthew Maule lays a curse on the entire (*) Pyncheon family as well as their residence, The House of the Seven Gables. This city's Pickering Wharf appears in the beginning of Nathaniel Hawthorne's Scarlet Letter. Giles Corey is executed in an Arthur Miller (*) play in, for ten points, what Massachusetts city in which a series of 1692 Witch Trials took place?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Salem, Massachusetts",
        "Salem Witch Trials"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This U.S. state's largest city was the site of Fort Christina, the capital of New Sweden, which occupied the lower reaches of its namesake river. This state's only serious engagement during the American Revolution was the Battle of Cooch's Bridge. (20 pts)",
        "This state's \"Blue Hen's Chicks\" regiment fought at the Battle of Brandywine in a namesake county in (10 pts)",
        "Pennsylvania. For ten points, name this state which saw a British occupation of its largest city, Wilmington."
      ],
      "answer": "Delaware"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Among this document’s new protections was that “no freeman is to be taken or imprisoned… save by lawful judgment of his peers or by the law of the land.” This document was signed on neutral territory between the royal fortress at Windsor Castle (20 pts)",
        "and the headquarters of a group of rebellious barons in a water-meadow alongside the River Thames [[TEMS]] called Runnymede. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this document that King John signed in 1215, placing limits on royal power."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Magna Carta Libertatum",
        "Great Charter of Freedoms"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Kingdom of Kapisa [[kah-PEE-sah]] once ruled this country, which hosts the now-ruined Greek-inspired Buddhas of Bamiyan [[BAH-mee-yahn]]. Those statues were demolished in this country by a (20 pts)",
        "Deobandi [[deh-oh-BAHN-dee]] fundamentalist regime, which took power following a Soviet withdrawal. Once led by Hamid Karzai [[hah-MEED KAR-zye]], this country is often referred to as the (10 pts)",
        "\"graveyard of empires.\" In 2021, the U.S. pulled its military out of, for ten points, what Pashtun-majority Middle Eastern country controlled by the Taliban?"
      ],
      "answer": "Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 2"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) 1906 race riots in this city were sparked by the gubernatorial race between Hoke Smith and Clark Howell. The Rhodesian Bush War's end was negotiated by a politician and future mayor of this city, Andrew (20 pts)",
        "Young. The 35-year old Maynard Jackson served as mayor of this city in the 70s and 80s, when he became the first Black mayor of a major Southern city. During the U.S. Civil War, city was the starting point of Sherman's March to the Sea. Martin Luther (10 pts)",
        "King. Jr. was born in, for ten points, which Georgian metropolis?"
      ],
      "answer": "Atlanta"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Following the U.S. Invasion of Grenada, the Edward Seaga-led Labour Party won every seat in this nation's elections due to boycotts by the People's National Party. Back to Africa proponent Marcus (20 pts)",
        "Garvey was from this island nation, which saw multiple \"Maroon Wars\" against the British government. The destruction of Port (10 pts)",
        "Royal by a 17th-century earthquake led to the founding of, for ten points, which Caribbean nation's capital of Kingston?"
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Jamaica or Jumieka"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The crowning of Joseph Bonaparte led the First Junta [[HOON-tuh]] of this city to depose Viceroy Hidalgo de Cisneros [[sis-NEH-ros]] as part of the May Revolution. A women's movement in this city marched in support of those who \"disappeared\" during the (20 pts)",
        "Dirty War. This city's Plaza de Mayo and Casa Rosada presidential palace were bombed by its own air force following a pro-Juan (10 pts)",
        "Peron demonstration. The capital of the Viceroyalty of Rio de La Plata was, for ten points, what largest city in Argentina?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Buenos Aires",
        "Autonomous City of Buenos Aires",
        "or Ciudad Autónoma de Buenos Aires 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 6"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this colony, former indentured servant Maryn Adriansen committed a massacre of natives during Kieft's War. The Treaty of Breda formally handed over this colony to Charles II's England, and it was led by Director-General Peter (20 pts)",
        "Stuyvesant [[STY-veh-sahnt]]. Using a cache of trade goods, including glass beads, Peter Minuit bought the island of (10 pts)",
        "Manhattan for this North American colonial venture. New Amsterdam served as the capital of, for ten points, what Dutch colonial venture in the Mid-Atlantic region of the modern U.S.?"
      ],
      "answer": "New Netherland or Nieuw Nederland"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Isser Harel called for a two year manhunt in this nation which aimed to bring Nazi war criminal Josef Mengele to justice. The dictator José Gaspar Rodríguez de Francia was known in this country as \"El Supremo.\" The Battle of Cerro Corá [[SEH- roh koh-RAH]] saw the death of this country's president Francisco Solano (20 pts)",
        "López, ending the six-year-long War of the Triple Alliance that pitted this country against three neighbors: Brazil, Argentina, and Uruguay. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this landlocked South American country."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Paraguay or Republica del Paraguay 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 8"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Young Turk Enver Pasha ordered this city's \"September Days,\" a series of anti- Armenian pogroms committed by the \"Army of Islam.\" A part of the larger \"Case Blue,\" Operation Edelweiss [[AY-del-vice]] (20 pts)",
        "was a Wehrmacht [[VARE-mahkt]] advance meant to cripple the Soviet petroleum supply by capturing this city's (10 pts)",
        "oilfields. For ten points, which Caspian port city was made capital of independent Azerbaijan following the dissolution of the USSR?"
      ],
      "answer": "Baku or Baki"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A “Great” revolt against colonial rule in this country in the 1920s was led by Sultan Pasha al-Atrash [[ah-TRAHSH]]. Michel Aflaq [[ah-FLAHK]] created the first (20 pts)",
        "Ba’ath [[bah-AHTH] party in this country. United with another Arab country in the United Arab Republic, this country lost the Golan [[GOH-lahn]] (10 pts)",
        "Heights to Israel in the Yom Kippur War. For ten points, name this country, united with Lebanon in a French mandate and now ruled by the Assad [[ah-SAHD]] family."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Syrian Arab Republic or Al Jumhuriyah al Arabiyah as Suriyah",
        "Arab Kingdom of Syria",
        "State of Syria"
      ]
    }
  ]
}